Xin chào, tôi là Scott Allen và trong chương này chúng ta sẽ dành thời gian
to understand how controllers work in the mvc framework.
Specifically we're going to look at the routing rules which deliver in the incoming requests
for from the web to our controllers and then look at controller actions.
You might remember from the introduction
that the controller actions are the public methods on our controllers.
They have the ability to respond to an incoming http request from the web.
We'll also be taking a look at action filters which can introduce pre and post processing
to an action and then see how we can input data to an action with action parameters
and output different types of results from an action using different action results.