One of the questions that we left unanswered in the introduction was this,
how does the sp dot net know how to deliver a request like slash home,
slash about to our home controller.
And the answer to that question is in the routing engine.
The routing engine is a core part of asp dot net, it's not tied to the mvc framework,
you can use the routing engine to route requests for web forms, WCF services,
really any type of resource but in mvc we use this routing engine
to direct requests to our controllers.
To do this we give the routing engine a map to follow using a map route API.
A route map allows us to provide a friendly name for the route, a pattern for the route
and default parameters for the route, the most important pieces to look
at are the pattern and the default.
Think about the goal of the routing engine, its job is to examine a URL and figure
out where to send it for processing.
When it examines the URL it needs to pick put pieces of data from that URL,
little hints about where to send the request.
In an MVC application we want the URL to specify the controller and action to invoke
and perhaps some other data so we give the routing engine a pattern it can use
and apply to find parameters in the URL.
The words inside those curly braces will be the parameter names,
if the routing engine doesn't find the specific piece of data in the URL
like the controller name or the action name it can use one of the default values
that we specify in the parameter defaults.
Let switch into visual studio and experiment with this.
Inside a visual studio let me introduce you to the global dot asax dot cs file.
This is a bit of a magical file in asp dot net.
If I open it up you can see we have a class here derived from http application and this allows us
to hook into hook into some application level events like application start,
this method will be magically invoked by asp dot net before you process the first http request.
So when your application starts running the code here will execute one time before any
of your controllers start executing and so this is where we put in some configuration
that the application needs like the routing configuration.
The routing configuration is done by this line of code, route config dot register route,
what we pass in is the global routing table the table
that contains all the routs for the entire application.
It will be empty initially but when we call register routes
that will add entries into the routing table.
I can get into the definition of this method
if I just put my cursor tight here on the method and press F12.
Now we are inside of a class called route config, this class actually lives
in the app start folder, you can find it right here.
It's given to me by default by visual studio when I created this application
so all this code was already written for me and if you've been working
with mvc previously this is a little bit different in mvc 4 than it was
in previous versions because all of the start up code that used to be inside
of global dot asax dot cs has now been factored into classes that are in this app start folder.
All these classes are called
from the application start method in global dot asax dot cs.
Here's the code that you saw on that previous slide, we're walking up to the route collection
and saying let's add a new route, we'll call it default and here's the type of URL you're going
to look for so if you see something that looks like slash home slash index,
treat home as the controller name, index as the action name and you can also look for an ID
but if there's not one that's okay we've provided a default value for it.
And in fact if you don't see an action name just treat the default action name as index.
When the routing engine picks apart a URL into these pieces it builds up a data structure
that it passes along to the mvc framework and then the framework can look
at that data structure and say what did you find for a controller and what did you find
for an action and it uses that information
to direct the request tour controller like the home controller.
In fact that information is available to us, it's available any where throughout the request.
Let's swing over to the home controller and see if we can inspect these values.
Instead of building a message that says something about modify this template,
let me build a different sort of message.
What I want to do is see what kind of controller we're inside of and I can do that by going
to the route data data structure, this is the data structure that's built
by the routing engine, it'll have a collection of values inside and I can basically walk
up to the values and say what do you have for a controller value,
I could also ask it what it has for an action value and finally I can say what do you have
for an ID value if any route data dot value sub ID and I can put all these pieces together
into a message, let's use string dot format and I want parameter 0
which will be the controller name, parameter 1 which is the action name
and parameter 2 which will be the ID.
So controller action ID and this is now the message that I'll display on the home page
so instead of modify this template we'll put a message here and let me run the application.
And what we should be able to see that just by going to the root of the application,
just local host slash we get a value of whom for controller and a value of index for the action
and what happens if we go to slash home, same values, home and index.
So I can go to slash home slash index slash 5 1 2
and you can see you get the value 5 1 2 for an ID.
What we're going to see in just a little bit is that it is actually very easy to get
that ID parameter, we do not have to look inside of route data explicitly
but for just right now I want to demonstrate the whole goal of the routing engine is
to pick apart that URL and then build this data structure that is available not only
to the mvc framework to figure out where it's going to go but also to us,
it's available inside of controllers, route data is also available inside of a view.
Typically our code is not going to be looking into route values like this,
it's the mvc framework that does that to find a controller and you'll notice that the value
of the controller which is home tells the mvc framework to go out and append controller
to that word home controller and look for a class by that name.
It's a case and sensitive search.