Now that we know a little bit about how routing works let's go into route config dot cs
and define a new route, this is only something you need to do if a default route doesn't work
for you but let me show you a scenario where a new route can help.
Let's imagine that the user expects to be able to come into the application and search
for a cuisine by its name, so French cuisine or Italian cuisine, in this case at second entry
in the URL the second segment of the path isn't really an action identifier it's more
of a parameter, it can be French or German or Italian.
So the default route really won't work very well for us because we don't want to add an action
to our controller for every type of cuisine that we have we just want
that path sent to the action as a parameter.
So I'll define a new route for this and I need to be careful where I define this route
because the order in which rotes are added to the global route collection is significant,
what the routing engine will do is evaluate each mapped route that we place
into the route collection the first one that matches the URL will win.
The default route entry that we have here is very greedy;
it matches nearly any URL that you want to throw at it.
It matches slash home slash index, it matches slash home, we've even seen it work
when you just go to the root of the application and it can do this
because it provides default parameter values to anything that's missing in the URL.
IF we want to define our own route we'd probably want to place it in front of that default route
and make that URL a little more restrictive.
So for example let me map a route and we'll give it the friendly name of cuisine
and we'll say the URL to match for this has to start with the word cuisine
and then it can have a parameter which we'll call name which will be the second segment
of the URL and you might say how can this work there's no control, there's no action.
Well, the mvc framework does need to know what the controller will be
and what the action will be so let me add those as defaults.
I'll create a new anonymously typed object and say controller equals the cuisine controller,
the default action, let's give it a default action of search
and name will just make it an empty name and that defines our new route.
Now if we have a request come in for slash cuisine the routing engine should see that,
that matches the cuisine route and send things off to a cuisine controller.
But if a request comes in for slash home,
slash index that doesn't match the cuisine route it doesn't start with the word cuisine
so we'll go to the next route entry which is the default route entry slash home slash index will
match that one.
As a side note let me briefly mention the purpose
of this routes dot ignore route method call, the routing engine will not try to process a request
that going to reach a real file on the file system.
That's why we can have a request for something like slash content, slash site dot css
and the routing engine won't interfere with that request.
The server can simply send back that css file in response, we don't need this request routed
to a controller, the file already exists we just need to pick it up off the disk and send it back
to the browser and that's what will happen because the routing engine will see that,
that's going to reach something on the disk
and it doesn't interfere and try and route things around.
But there are some files served up by asp dot net that end with a axt extension
and these files don't actually exist on the file system they're virtual files
but asp dot net knows how to serve them up.
If you've ever worked with asp dot net tracing you might be familiar with trace dot exd.
We'll take a look at a situation where we have an axd end point later in the course
but for now just know this is a way to tell a routing engine if you see something
like trace dot axd in the request just ignore it and don't try to route it,
someone else will take care of that even though the file doesn't actually exist on the disk.
Now that we have our new route to find let me run the application by pressing control F 5
and let's try to come into the cuisine controller and look for Swedish food.
The response I get back from my application is an acdp 404 error, this is the error code
that is recognized throughout the noon universe as meaning I cannot find what you're looking
for which is exactly what I would expect because I told the mcv framework to go looking
for a cuisine controller but I do not have a cuisine controller in the application.
So let's fix this problem, I'm going to right click on the controller's folder
and select add controller, this will bring up a dialogue box
where I can give my new controller a name, I'll call it the cuisine controller.
There's a number of other options inside of this dialogue which we'll talk about later
in the course, for right now I'll just leave the empty NBS controller template selected
and click add, this will add a controller to my controller's folder.
If it isn't quote empty it does have an index method inside,
it is derived from that base controller class and if I build this application
and run it again, refresh the browser we'll still have a 404 error message
because we also told the mvc framework inside of val config
that the action should be the search action and this controller does not have a search action.
There's also no way to specify the action in the URL we didn't provide
for that flexibility inside of this route.
So we really need to call the index action, the search action, we also don't have a view as yet
but that's okay I'm going to do the simplest possible thing inside
of an action which is just to return content.
When you return content you just send a string back down the browser,
there's no html involved unless you put html in the string, there's no view involved,
I could just say hello, just to prove that we're reaching the search action properly
and if I refresh again now we have a result, we have reached that method inside the controller.
Now let's see if we can pull out that name parameter out of the URL but before I do
that let me just oint out that actions are nothing more
than public methods inside of a controller class.
Anytime you add a public method to this class or any controller class you have to think about it
as something that will be URL addressable depending on your routing configuration.
If someone types the right thing into their browser address bar they might be able
to invoke a public method inside of a controller so don't add any methods inside of here
that you wouldn't expect to be called via a URL.
So just keep that in mind as you move forward.
Right now we're going to try to pull out the name value from the URL
and I've already demonstrated that we could get to that through route data,
I could ask for route data dot value sub name but it turns
out asp dot net mvc makes this even easier because if you add a parameter
to an action what the mvc framework will do is go out and try to find something that matches
that parameter name and then just give it to you.
It will do everything it can to populate that parameter,
it will look all around the request it will look in routing data,
so things that were picked out of the URL.
It will also look in the query string and it will look in posted form values.
In the case of coming to slash cuisine slash Swedish the mvc framework will see I need a
parameter called name and something called name was extracted from the URL
and it will automatically pass that into me.
What I want to do is just echo that fact when I return this content but before I do
that what I want to do is make sure I properly encode this value,
so I'll say message equals server dot html encode name server is a property that I inherit
on my controller that I can use to get to server type utilities
and variable including html encode which ill make sure if a user snuck through some sort
of malicious script tag or something like that it will render as text
and it will prevent a cross-site scripting attack.
The razor view engine will do this automatically for me
but since I'm using a content result I have
to be a little bit more careful about how I manage user input.
Let's just take that encoded message and return it as the content of our message,
now I will do a build, I will come back and refresh the browser
and you can see we get the name of the cuisine even though it is misspelled,
we get the name of the cuisine back out and we can show it in the browser.
Now currently the way our route is defined I can come to the cuisine controller and not pass
in a cuisine name and it renders just fine that's because in our routes we said
that if you do not find a name just use and empty string.
If I take this default out of here though something else will happen,
let me do a quick build and refresh now we're back to a 404 error message
because essentially what has happened is that we've told the mvc framework that an order
to match this route you have to have a name it's not optional, we didn't provide a default value
for it, therefore we didn't match the cuisine route we went to the default route,
we probably went to the index action of the cuisine controller which doesn't exist
and that's why we have this problem.
So let me put this back in and instead of specifying an empty string I'm going
to specify URL parameter dot optional, that's just telling the mvc framework it's okay
for this to not exist inside of the URL and now if I do a build and refresh we're getting
to the cuisine controller again there's just no value present for the name.
If I wanted to provide a default value I could say name equals French or name equals Swedish,
I could also do that using c sharp and saying that this has a default value of say French
and now if I do another build and refresh the french value comes
through even though I didn't specify that in the URL and just to show you
that the mvc framework is looking around in different places
for something called name let me enter a query string so I'll go to the cuisine controller
but say query string name equals a Italian and we get Italian comes
through so even though the routing engine didn't find a name
in the URL the mvc framework found something called name in the query string
and it just passed it into the action force automatically.
So you almost never inside of a controller action directly inspect route data
or directly inspect the query string which you could do by going
to request dot query string inside of a controller method,
all of those things are taken care of for us by the mvc framework,
it's just going to find things in the request and pass them into us.
And of course it should still work if I say slash cuisine slash Swedish
and actually spell it correctly this time that value of course was found in the URL.
As we move further along in this course we'll see more advanced scenarios involving multiple
action parameters and even complex types here with multiple properties
and see how the mvc framework behaves with those.