At this point we've used routing data and query string values as inputs
to our cuisine controller search action and that will prove to be useful knowledge later
when we start doing data access and need to use those incoming values but for now I want
to talk about the output of an action.
We just used the content result to return a string literal from our action
and the producing method which is a factory type method that produces
and action result, its called content.
So that's simply the method that you need to invoke to create a content result.
There's many other types of action results available the name column represents the type
that is derived from action result, the type of the object that you'll create
and produce in return from an action.
So all of the class names that you see here they all derive from action result
and the producing method is the factory method you can invoke
to construct a particular result, it puts things together for you.
Previously we've also used the view method to produce a view result and we saw
in the introduction how this will render a view that is somewhere inside of our views folder,
there are also results we can use to return a file back to the client,
return data in java script object notation for java script to consume and also a result
to tell the browser to redirect to a different URL.
Let's see how some of these different action results behave
by switching back into visual studio.
We've seen how the content and view results work, let's try a different result,
let's look at one of the redirect results,
you can see just in the intelliSense window there's many types of redirects,
for instance there is a redirect permanent, this returns an http 3 or 2 status code
which would basically say if someone came to this cuisine controller it would say go
over the Microsoft dot come and never look back this is a permanent redirect,
you never have to come here again.
There's also redirects that you can use to go to specific actions in the same controller
or an action on a different controller that is in this application so I could say when you come
to the cuisine controller what I want to do is redirect you to the index action
of the home controller and I can even pass along values with this.
This is a temporary redirect and I'll show you later in the course why these types
of redirects are very common for some scenarios.
What's interesting about this redirect to action is that it actually coordinates
with the routing engine behind the scenes, it walks up toe the routing engine and says
if I want to go to a URL that would reach the index action of the home controller what would
that URL look like and based on the way we've configured the routing engine,
the routing engine will reply with the proper URL
and you can even pass along additional parameters, if the parameters are known
to the route they're actually in the URL, the routing engine will produce a URL
that has the value in the URL but I can also say let's go to the index action
of the home controller and pass along the name so the way you do this is
to pass an anonymously typed object in as the third parameter, mvc framework will pick
that apart and decide that okay you need to get a parameter called name over here.
So what would this look like, let me do a build, we're currently at cuisine slash Swedish
so the cuisine is Swedish but after I've built the application if I refresh this we should end
up back on the home page and notice the URL is just slash query string name equals Swedish
because there is no name in the URL when we go to that default route
to reach the home controller and so the framework decided to build this URL
with the name parameter in the query string.
We know now that it's very easy to pull that value out of the query string if we need it
and this was a redirect result so if you're not familiar with that the browser
of requested slash cuisine slash Swedish and the server responded with an http code
and a location basically saying no you don't want this URL you want to go over here
so the browser had to issue another get request and come back here
to the home controller, that's how we ended up here.
You can also if you need to redirect to a route by name so here I could say redirect to route
and say please redirect to the default route and now I could plug in values if I wanted to,
I could say please pass along so that we reach the home controller and the about action,
so with redirect of the route you don't pass the controller
and action name was parameters you have to pass them in an anonymously typed object
but those values will match up with however the route was configured.
Let's try a couple other different type of routes,
just for kicks let's return a file result, so I can return file and here I can pass
in the file contents if I already have them loaded into a byte array,
there's different overloads of this, just pass in a stream if I already have a stream open
or pass in a file name the mvc framework will figure out how to pick
that up off disk and pass it back.
I'm going to pick the overload here where I just need to pass a file name and a content type.
So this will be a little bit weird but let's just say when the user comes
to the search action of the cuisine controller we want to return our site style sheet,
site dot css it's in the content directory.
So I'll need to come up with the physical path to that file, I can do that...do
that server property here it is one more time, this time I'm going to use the map path method
on that and from here what I can do is pass in a virtual path,
the path that's in my web application slash content slash site dot css
and server dot map path will turn that into a physical path
that the operating system understands and I can say
that the content type of this is text slash css.
Let me do a build and let's see what happens when I come back out to the browser
and refresh the cuisine controller this time, now what I'm looking
at is essentially our style sheet, site dot css, we returned that as the action result.
Let's try one more, let's come back and return a Json method and then pass in an object.
Behind the scenes what will happen is the framework will run a java script serialize
over this object to turn it into java script object notation.
And this object can be pretty much anything, it can be one of your models,
it can be just an anonymously typed object so I could say give me an object with message equal
to that current message that we computed and I'll just throw in something extra just
for the fun of it so I don't have a name property called Scott and I need
to add one more parameter here to allow this to work when I get request,
I need to explicitly say allow a get request to retrieve this Json and now do a build.
Let's come back to the browser and refresh and there you can see Json appears
in the browser window, message is French name of Scott.
Later in the course we'll see just how easy it is to take that and consume it
from java script then turn it into anything we want, turn it into an html display.