When the mvc framework is selecting one of your controllers public methods to invoke
as an action it will use any action selector attributes that might be present
to find the correct action to invoke.
One such selector is the action name selector, when you apply this attribute
to a controller action it specifies the action name for the method or the edit method
that we see here we can no longer reach this method as an action named edit we have
to reach it as an action named modify, action name is an attribute you can use when you went
to alias, the name of your action methods.
Accept verbs on the other hand will specify the http verb that is allowed
to reach a particular action, you can say that an action method is only reachable
with an http get request or an http post request or delete or put
or some combination of those verbs.
The accept attribute will become extremely important later when we start modifying data,
we'll be using both get and post then but right now we're just using get
but I'm introducing this topic now so you're ahead of the game.
Let's see how this works in visual studio.
Inside of our search action let's change it back to returning a simple content result
with a message that we've computed
but I will make one more change I will add an attribute here that says
that you can only invoke this during an http post message and now if I do a build
and refresh the browser on slash cuisine I'll get the 404 error message,
essentially the mvc framework could not find an action it could invoke
in response to this get request.
A get request is what a browser sends off by default if you just type some something
into the address bar and hit enter.
On the other hand if I had specified http get and now do a build
and a refresh everything should work just fine because now the mvc framework can find an action
to invoke and we see French again because that's the default value for this parameter.
Let me give you a preview of why this is extremely useful.
What happens if we had two actions both with the name of search, the first problem here is
that the c sharp compiler will be unhappy
because these methods have the exact same signature, the same name or the same number
of parameters we wouldn't be able to get this to build but let's take the parameter off
and instead of returning content with the message, let me just return content
that says search and now do a build and come out and refresh the browser.
We'll get a different sort of error, the mvc framework sees
that it should invoke a search action but it's not going to try to distinguish
between the two search actions that we have, one that takes a string,
one that doesn't have any parameters it's just going to throw
up its hands and throw an exception.
There's some scenarios later in this course where it's going to be very useful
to have two different versions of an action and have one respond to an http get request only
and have the other one respond only to an http post request
and now by placing these attributes here the mvc framework can clearly see
that if it's a get request for search it should go to this action and display research,
if it's a post request for search it will come over to this one.
So I just did a build and if I refresh now we should get rid
of the error and we get a search text.
Again that's because the mcv framework chose this one, it was an http get request,
it saw the search action...it saw
that this first one was only legal during a post so it selected the second one.
Just remember this discussion when we come back to modifying data later.