In addition to the action selector attributes we just looked at there are also a number
of action filter attributes you can use.
Action filters apply pre and post processing logic to a controller action and its result.
Action filters are the components that you want to use to apply cross-cutting logic that's logic
that has to execute across multiple controller actions but you don't want
to duplicate code inside of individual controllers.
One example is the output cash attribute this tells the run time that it's allowed
to cash the final output of some action and to use
that cashed result to service future requests.
When you apply this attribute in the right places you can dramatically increase the
through put and scalability of an application,
we'll take a look at cashing later in this course.
Another example is the authorize attribute, authorize allows you to ensure a user is logged
in and perhaps a in a specific role like the admin.
role before the action is allowed to process that user's request.
We'll be looking at most of these filters during the duration of this course
but right now I just want to show you how to apply a filter and also take a quick look
at building your own custom action filter.
Here inside of visual studio let's get rid of our second search action result and go back just
to a single search action result, we'll have it respond to both a get and a post
and I'm going to use the authorize attribute.
You can just use the authorize attribute without any parameters, you can also specify something
like roles equals admin., that means the user has to be logged in and they have to be
in the admin role before we can invoke this function, you can also specify user names inside
of here, I'm just going to use the authorize attribute without any parameters,
what that tells the mvc framework is the user has to be logged in in order
to be able to use the search action.
Now if I do a build and I come back to refresh the application
and what has happened is we've been redirected to the log on page because I've tried
to go somewhere that requires me to be authorized, it requires me to be authenticated
and the run time will see authorized attribute and it's smart enough to redirect me to the log
on page where if I were to register on this site I could create an account and the log in.
After I log in I'd be redirected back to the cuisine controller where I originally tried
to get to, back to the original URL that I tried.
We'll be looking at authentication and authorization and other security topics
in a later module but right now I just want to focus on action filters and I want
to demonstrate that you can place them not only on an individual action
but you can also place them on a controller and when they're at the controller level they apply
to all the actions inside of that controller so again if I tried to get
to the cuisine controller now that we've rebuilt I'll still be redirected to the log on page,
I need to log in before I can get past that authorized gate keeper.
In addition to applying action filters at the action level
and at the controller level you can also have what's known as global filters.
Global filters are typically registered during application start
up which means we register them during the application start event to let me return
to the magical global dot asax dot cx file and there's the application start event one
of the calls that you can see in here is a call to filter config dot registered global filters,
I'll put the cursor right on that method, press F12 and we'll jump over to that class
which by the way it's also inside of the app start folder.
Here you can see that we're registering a single global filter, it's the handle error attribute.
A global filter like handle error attribute will be in effect for every single request
that is processed by any controller inside of your application.
The purpose of the handle error attribute is to display a friendly error page
to users when something goes wrong.
Let's see how this works, let me return to the cuisine controller,
we've commented out the authorized attributes so we should be able to get inside of this action
without logging in and we'll pretend
that something terrible has happened during the execution of our program
and we'll throw an exception that's going to escape the action.
That means if I come back to the cuisine controller, let's go to cuisine,
what we'll see is affectionately known as the asp dot net yellow screen of death.
It's the screen that shows you there was an un-handled exception on the server
and it gives you a stack trace and some additional information that you
as a developer probably will find useful because it can help you track down a problem
but your users don't want to see this in fact it can be dangerous
because it can give away information that someone who is
up to no good can use to try to attack your server.
But in actuality your users will probably never see this page because by default this level
of detailed error information is only shown when the request originates from the same machine
that the application is on so on the local host.
If we want to see what the user is actually going to see we just have
to configure our application a little bit differently.
Configuration is another topic that we'll cover later in this course
but for now let me introduce you to the web dot config files that is inside of this project,
this controls configuration settings for the entire application
and one of the things I can configure in here is how to handle errors, I want custom errors
and I want the mode to be on by default it is that third option there,
remote only which means it only shows a pretty error page to remote users.
I'll just type in that xml element that's inside of the system dot web section,
save the web dot config file and now let me come back and refresh this page,
the application will restart any time that you twiddle with the web dot config file
and this is the pretty error page that the users will see.
Of course pretty is in the eye of the beholder but the reason we end up here is primarily
because of that handle error attribute, it is providing post processing logic on an action
and when it sees that an exception has escaped
from an action it will display an error view instead of the yellow screen of death.
The error view is actually in your application by default you can find it if you go
into the solution explorer window and look under views shared,
views that are in this folder are available to controllers throughout the application,
there's an error dot see html view here so the error view is just a razor view
like all the other views we are using and it's inside of here
where you can provide some additional information or additional messages
or give someone the number to the help desk
so that they can call them in the middle of the night.
Let me just change that view and if I refresh we'll be able to see
that change reflected in the browser.
Let me also demonstrate that if that if we were to go into our app start filter config
and comment on this line it places the handle error attribute
into the global filter collection then after I do a build
and refresh we get a slightly different error, well actually it's the same error it's just
that asp dot net is displaying a different page it's not giving out a level of detail
in this error because we have custom errors mode equals on we're going
to see exactly what the user sees here,
they're not going to see a stack trace they're just going to be aware
that something is wrong on the server.
What I should do is come back and put this filter into place
so that we have friendly errors and also go into web dot config and change this mode
to remote only, that means our end users will see custom error pages
but when we're developing here on local host we'll still get to see stack traces
which can be very useful for debugging.
Now before we finish this module I also want to demonstrate that it's very easy
to build your own custom action filters.
I'm going to go to the filters folder that's already in this application and click add class,
what we're going to build is a logging attribute so I will call this log attribute,
that will create a class, log attribute, I'm going to derive it from action filter attribute
that is in the system dot web dot mvc name space and once I derive
from the base filter attribute class what I can do is override one of four important methods.
On action executing is a method you can override to look
at the request before an action even executes where as
on action executed is a method they you can override and you get to poke around inside
of what happened at a point in time after the action executes.
You can also catch before the result is executed and after the result is executed
so for instance before a view vendors and a view vendors
and these action filters are very powerful, you can change the environment,
you can change results you can change parameters,
let me just go ahead and override these methods.
Let's override on action executing and override on action executed, override on result executing
and override on result executed and then I will come in and press F9 at the top of each
of these methods to set a break point and now let's apply this attribute
to our cuisine controller and see how it behaves.
All we need to do that is place it on an action or at the controller level,
this log attribute is in a different name space so I'll need to bring in the name space ode
to food dot filters, but at this point I should be able to run
with the debugger and see where we break.
Let me go to slash cuisine and you can see we get inside
of on action executing even before we get inside the action itself
and one of the things I could look at inside of here is the filter context.
From filter context you can find out all sorts of things,
you can find out what parameters are being passed to an action, you can add parameters,
you can modify parameters, if I continue on and press F5 you can see now we're in the action,
we're throwing and exception, something terrible has happened, press F5 to continue again
and now we're in one action executed, this also has a filter context,
this filter context can have more information on it because now the action has executed.
You might have a result that you want to inspect or you might have an exception that you want
to inspect so here we can see that an un-handled exception escaped from that.
If I was really writing a log attribute I would probably record that exception somewhere,
I'd probably also be recording what time the controller started executing
and what time it finished and I could do all sorts of interesting
and useful things with attributes.
I'd probably also install this log attribute as a global filter attribute so it would execute
for everything inside the application but for now I just want you to know
that these are available when you see attributes on actions and controllers you'll have an idea
of what they can do and you can see how easy it is if you ever need
to write your own attribute, how easy that is to do.