The Razor view engine allows us to use Razor templates to produce HTML.
Razor views if you remember from previous modules,
those are the files with the CHTML extension.
Think of them as templates that consist of mark up which is your HTML
and C sharp code expressions that are evaluated to place data into the mark up.
So if I have a view and my model is a RestaurantReview I'll take properties
of that review like the restaurant name and address and place those property values
into specific locations in the HTML.
When it all comes together I render a full HTML page of the client's browser
that gives them all the information that they want to see.
Let's look at this in an application to make the concept all the more concrete.
Imagine that in the application we want to have a place where you can come in
and see the latest reviews in the data base, we'll call that slash reviews.
We won't be working with the data base just yet, we're going to focus on views
but we cannot even get to a view yet because we do not have a reviews controller and as we saw
in the last module, that leads to a 404 error message.
So let me right click on the controller's folder and add a new controller.
We will call this the reviews controller and instead of using the empty template I'm going
to pick the MVC controller with empty read write actions.
This will give me an index method the default action for a controller
but it will also give me other actions that will ultimately allow me to edit a review.
Create a review, delete a review, none of the code will be there as yet
but we can fill it in as we go along.
It's the index action where you typically would display a list of everything.
But we don't even have anything that represents a RestaurantReview yet, so let me also go
and add a class called RestaurantReview and add this to the project.
We'll give it just a few simple properties.
Ultimately one day we'll have a data base behind this and we'll need some sort of property
to hold a primary key so I will add an integer ID property to the RestaurantReview.
We'll also give this a place to store the name of the restaurant,
the city that the restaurant is in, the country, and finally some sort of rating.
And that's all I need for a RestaurantReview.
One day, this will be in the data base.
But for right now in the reviews controller, what I'm going to do is come
down to the very bottom and just give us some in memory data to work with,
so we don't focus on data access yet, we can focus on views.
So I'm going to paste in some code that is just a static private list of RestaurantReview.
I need to bring the name space in the scope using OdeToFood.Models
and now this is legal C sharp code and this is not something I suggest that you usually do
which is keep around a static list of in memory data in your controller that never works.
This is just so that we don't have to get a data base involved just yet.
What this will allow me to do is to come back into my index action and say that my model
for this action is going to be from R in reviews, we'll do a little link query here,
let's order by R dot country and select every review.
And that will be my model for the view that doesn't exist just yet.
But even though it doesn't exist it's still educational to build this application
and come back to a browser and refresh to see how it behaves.
And what we're looking at now is not the 404 error
that we have before but we still do have an error.
We've told the MVC runtime that we want to render a view and the runtime has gone looking
for what we call the conventional view.
Since we're inside the index action of the reviews controller the MVC runtime went
to the reviews folder and looked for something called index,
that has the same name as the action.
And it looks for a couple of different types of index files
because there's actually two view engines that are registered by default in the MVC runtime.
One view engine is the web forms view engine and web form views have the extension ASPX or ASCX.
The other view engine is the Razor view engine with the CSHTML extension,
and since both of these view engines are around by default, the runtime is looking
for all these different types of files.
And it looks for these files in the Views slash reviews folder
since we are in the reviews controller.
The convention is to have a views folder with the same name as your controller,
but the runtime also went looking in the Shared folder because views on the Shared folder are
as you might have guessed from the name, shared among all of the controllers.
But the runtime didn't find that view anywhere, we need to create that view.
An easy way to add a view is just to right click inside of a controller action
like this Index action and select the Add View.
You can also hit control M control V. This will launch a dialog box
and the dialog is rather smart, it knows on inside the index action.
So it wants to create an index view which is perfect.
I do want to use the Razor view engine and I want to create a strongly-typed view.
Remember in the introduction, we talked about strongly-typed views.
This is where the view knows the exact type of model object that you are passing into it.
I'm going to tell it that my model is a RestaurantReview.
In fact, I'm going to have a list of RestaurantReviews.
And I'm also going to pick a scaffolding template of list.
What scaffolding in Visual Studio will do is reflect upon your model object,
figure out what properties are interesting and then build out a basic UI for you.
It will create a view and it's something that you can go in and modify and customize.
But it gives you a starting point and the list scaffold template assumes
that you have multiple model objects that you need to display.
There's also a scaffolding to create, and edit, and delete,
we'll be looking at those in this course too.
I'm going to leave all the other settings in place and just click Add,
and you'll see what happens as we now have a Reviews folder in the views folder.
That reviews folder has an index view.
The index view itself is strongly-typed against the IEnumerable of RestaurantReview
so it expects a collection of RestaurantReviews.
And it's going to build a table to display those multiple reviews.
The table will have header cells with the name the City, the Country, the Rating,
and then for each item in the model, we'll be writing out a table row with cells
that show the name, the City, the Country, the Rating and then a whole bunch of links.
We're going to come back and talk about the syntax and what this HTML thing is.
For now, let me just save everything, do a build to make sure everything is up to date
and I should be able to refresh my view.
And now, we have a list of reviews on the screen.