Inside of a Razor view like this index view for RestaurantReviews our responsibility is
to take the model object given to this by the controller
and present the model in a user interface.
And the user interface in the web application is generally built using HTML.
As we talked about earlier, you can think of Razor as a template,
where you combine literal text with pieces of data from your model
that you pull out using sharp C sharp code.
The literal text is like the h2 and Index text too in this view.
If I want a view to display a more descriptive header, I can change this text.
Let's say that this will display, the Latest Reviews.
I can just save a view, refresh the browser and I can see that literal text appears here.
Razor just output that without changing anything, the text gets sent to the browser
where the h2 element becomes a level two header, so it gives this a bit of a title effect here
to announce that these are the Latest Reviews.
When you see an at sign in Razor, chances are then you are not dealing with literal text
because an at sign can introduce C sharp code
and the C sharp code can contain an expression for Razor to evaluate.
So I can use C sharp code to reach into my model and pull out data.
I could have something like we are showing the latest at Model.Count reviews.
Save this, put parenthesis because count is a link operator,
it needs to be invoked and now refresh the view.
And we get-- we are showing the latest 3 reviews.
So we didn't output at Model.Count, instead Razor saw that that was C sharp code,
it evaluated it, it produced the number 3, so it sent that number 3 down to the browser.
And technically, you don't need to only access the model in the view.
You could also access ViewBag.
In fact, you could access anything.
Let me just put out a property that is inherited by a view.
The views VirtualPath and save this.
And when I do that I can see
that the VirtualPath property contains the path of the view in this application.
So I don't need to stick to just the model property.
I can go anywhere to pick up data but remember there is no data access or calculation logic
in the view at least not heavy calculation logic.
Because data access in calculation logic, that's what controllers and models do.
And while I'm looking at it,
a tilde is something we've seen before but I'm not sure I explained it.
A tilde represents the root of the application so tilde slash Views would mean go
to the view folder from the root of this application.
It's common to use a tilde everywhere you specify a path
because without the tilde you need to be careful of your app
that gets deployed into a subdirectory.
You have to know the name of the directory where the app is deployed
in order to hand out correct links.
And that gets very messy.
So anytime you need to point to something in the application whether it's a JavaScript file
or an image or another view, using the tilde is a safe and easy approach.
Let's go back to the code we have before.
I'll hit Control Z a couple times and we're back to at Model.Count.
You can think of the at sign here a bit like response dot right if you've ever done
that in ASP.NET or classic ASP, the result of the C Sharp expression Model.Count is sent
down to the client essentially with a response dot right but there is a significant difference
between this code and response dot right
because Razor will automatically HTML encode any output sent through the at sign
to help prevent cross-site scripting attacks.
Let me demonstrate this.
If we switch over into the ReviewsController and come down to our data that we're displaying,
what we could do is change the city for the Marrakesh restaurant from Washington D.C.
to something like script alert XSS which stands for cross-site scripting attack slash script.
So what this represents is what would happen if somehow, someway a malicious user was able
to get something into your database that was a malicious script.
And if I build the application and refresh the browser, what we'll see is that Marrakesh,
the city is now script with an alert box.
Now an alert box is just an annoyance.
But if someone actually did get a malicious script into the database
and Razor was not HTML encoding this,
the browser would actually see a script tag and execute that JavaScript.
Cross-site scripting attacks can do terrible things.
They can steal cookies from users,
they can display fake password dialogs and steal user's passwords.
Cross-site scripting attacks are very dangerous
and unfortunately they are the number one vulnerability on the web.
So you have to be very careful when displaying data that the user has given to you
and make sure you HTML encode that data which again fortunately Razor does that by default.
We can see that if we do a View Source here and I do a quick search for XSS,
instead of actually outputting a less than character which would allow the browser to see
that this is a script tag and start executing JavaScript, instead Razor converted that less
than character into ampersand LT colon which is a way to tell the browser I want
to display a less than character.
And so now what we have is a script that's showing up in the city which is a lot better
than actually having executable script.
And just to show you what happens if you really want to display something
without HTML encoding, you can do that in Razor.
What we'll do is we'll come down to this line of code that is displaying the city and we'll talk
about what HTML.Display for does in just a bit.
But the way to do this in Razor is to use HTML.Raw,
that's a way of saying take this expression, take the string, do not HTML encode it.
So if I just put item.City in here, save everything and refresh the browser.
Now we have actual executable script on the page which in this case is an annoyance
if that really was a malicious script, terrible things could happen.
So let me quickly get rid of that script.
I'm into the ReviewsController, just set Control Z to get back to Washington D.C.
And now we can move forward again.
And now, let's look at item.Rating.
I'm going to comment out this line of code because we're not quite ready
to talk about what display for does.
I just want to show you that I can also output the item rating juts by saying at item.Rating.
And if I save everything and rebuild, we've gotten rid of our script
but we should still be showing the rating as a 10 which is correct.
And the at item.Rating is what we will call an implicit code expression in Razor.
We'd let Razor figure out what a C Sharp code and what is mark up.
It's smart enough to know that at item.Rating is a C Sharp expression whereas less
than slash TD are going to back into mark up.
But what if we have some text displaying right after this rating?
So the rating is on the scale of 1 to 10 but if we wanted to let someone know
that by saying 10 out of 10 or 3 out of 10.
I just put a slash 10 here.
There's two ways to interpret this.
You could say take the rating and divide it by 10 because this is all a C Sharp expression
or show slash 10 as literal text.
And by default what Razor will do is figure that that is text,
not part of the C Sharp expression, so we get 10 out of 10.
But what if we really did want to take the rating and divide it by 10?
Then we would need what's known as an explicit code expression where you use parenthesis
and the at sign to explicitly denote what your C Sharp code is.
And if I'll save this version of the view, all the ratings turn into 1
because we're taking 10 and dividing it by 10.
But for the most part, Razor is really good at figuring
out what is C Sharp code and what is not C Sharp code.
If I turn this back into an implicit expression, let me just show you a couple other edge cases.
Imagine I wanted to prefix the rating with an R. So if I put the letter R here and we want
to have an R10 or an R3 and I save this and refresh,
what we see is at item.Rating is now output as literal text.
That's because Razor makes a special case for e-mail addresses and when it sees something
at something dot something, it assumes you might want to display an e-mail address
so it doesn't evaluate this as C Sharp code.
The nice thing about this is if you actually have an e-mail address
and you put it there something like scottallen@Pluralsight.com,
you don't need to worry about escaping anything.
But in this scenario where I really do want to say something like R1 or R10,
I need to go back to using an explicit code expression
and surrounding my C Sharp there with parenthesis.
Now that will be treated as C Sharp code and I get the R10 out.
So Razor is smart enough to figure out e-mail addresses
because of the presence of the at sign.
Well what happens if I want to put out something that has an at sign in it like a Twitter handle?
Now this Razor handle this.
Well, it thinks at OdeToCode should be a C Sharp expression.
It goes off looking for something called OdeToCode but it doesn't find one.
This would a case where I just need to escape the at sign by using a double at sign.
And now if I save the view, now we're outputting at OdeToCode literally
which is what we intended to do for a Twitter handle.