In addition to code expressions, both implicit and explicit, Razor also supports code blocks.
We can see an example of this here at the top of the view.
You can see a block of code that starts with the at sign
and has an opening curly brace and a closing curly brace.
In between those curly braces, we can place as much C Sharp code as we want inside of a view.
But remember, keep the view simple.
So a lot of code is usually a bad sign.
The C Sharp code that is inside of this block is going to execute.
It's not going to have its expressions evaluated and written to the client.
It simply executes or produces side effects.
We can set things on the ViewBag like you can see us setting the ViewBag.Title property.
We'll see the significance of that line of code in just a little bit
when we talk about layout views with Razor.
I can even declare variables and use them inside of the code block
so I could say let's create a variable called firstReview that is equal to Model.First.
So it literally gave me the first item in the collection that is my model.
And inside of the code block, you have
to observe the correct usage of semicolons for C Sharp codes.
We'll terminate that with a semicolon.
Now we can use firstReview anywhere else inside of this view.
So at the top of the view, I could now say firstReview.Name,
we'll up the name of the restaurant.
And you can see we get the name of the restaurant, the first restaurant
and all of the reviews here at the top.
Another example of a code block is the foreach statement here in the middle of the view.
This foreach statement allows us to iterate
through the model pulling out one item at a time.
And you can see that Razor allows us to transition
between C Sharp code before each statement and back into HTML without making any explicit marks
or using any sort of delimiters to tell it when we're transitioning from C Sharp code to HTML.
We simply have the opening curly brace and then we have a TR to start the table row.
It works in the other direction too.
So at the bottom of the foreach, we have a closing curly brace.
Razor is smart enough to figure out that the slash TR at the bottom is HTML
but that closing curly brace is part of my C Sharp code
that terminates the foreach statement.
Let me demonstrate a few other features of code blocks by removing this table
and we'll rewrite this a different way.
I'll remove the table.
I'm also going to remove the bit about a firstReview to clean up this view a little bit.
And now here above the create link, let's write a new each statement.
So for each review that we have in the model, let's-- instead of writing out a table,
let's write out a div for each review.
And in the div we'll have an h4 that has the name of the restaurant.
We'll include a span that has the rating associated with that restaurant.
And then perhaps just a paragraph tag that has the city--
And the country.
And then, for one last touch, let me go in to the div and give it a class of review
and I'll come in to our style sheet for the Site.css.
And down here at the bottom, I'm just going to paste
in some code that will pretty up our review.
Give it a bottom border, add some color to the h4 tag that we've added just
to make it appear a little bit better.
I'll save the style sheet.
If I'll go save everything and build and let's refresh,
we're still displaying our reviews now, we're just not using a table.
We're using a series of divs.
And now I'd like to show you a couple things about code blocks.
For the most part, when I wrote that code block, I didn't have to worry
about when I was writing C Sharp code and when I was writing HTML.
I know I have to use an at sign when I want to write a C Sharp expression and I just do that.
But you'll notice that a comma became part of my literal text that's outputted in the view.
Again, no explicit delimiters there.
But again, there's a couple special edge cases here.
For instance, what if I wanted the text review to appear before this div
and not inside of its own HTML element?
So if I just put review here and save the view and refresh, Razor gets a little bit unhappy
and essentially that's because it didn't make the transition
from C Sharp code back into literal text.
It thinks that review is part of my C Sharp code.
The easiest way to fix this, if you really don't want review inside of some sort of HTML element,
is just to use at colon that tells Razor that this is literal text.
And now if I refresh, we'll have the word review in front of every div.
The same thing could be used if we, for some obscure reason,
wanted to have a closing curly brace underneath of every div and have
that actually display in the view.
Fairly, if I refresh that doesn't display.
Razor thinks this is part of C Sharp code
and it thinks this second closing curly brace is literal text
so that appears at the bottom of the view.
I wanted this curly brace to be part of my text.
Again just use at colon and now we have the closing curly brace appearing where we wanted.
But those are edge cases you probably won't run into this very often, for the most part,
just write what you feel in Razor, it will figure out the proper thing to do.