Next, let's turn our attention to what was not in our index view or restaurant reviews.
What was not in our index view was the navigational menu that you see
in the application, at home, about and contact links or the Ode to Food logo
or the copyright at the bottom of the page.
All the code and mark up in our index view was there only
to output the review information into the middle of the page.
As I alluded to in the introduction, there is another type of view at work here
to handle these common things that appear everywhere.
Every application has some common UI structure.
You need navigation links and headers on every page and maybe a footer.
To provide that structure in Razor, we use a layout view.
If you're familiar with ASP.NET web forms, then you have probably used master pages.
Razor layout views are similar to master pages but really, they're much,
much better and easier to understand.
In this layout views, that's typically where you have your doc type, your head tag
and all the common markup that you need.
And then a layout view has two special methods that I can call render body and render section.
These methods allow the content views like the index view that we wrote to plug in their pieces
of the UI into specific locations of the layout.
Let's look at an example.
Inside of the index view that we've been working on, let me remove some of the experiments
that we've done with code blocks and save the view and refresh.
And just point out again that the only thing we're really rendering here is the middle
section, the latest reviews.
All the other pieces like the logo and the menu, those are handled by the layout view.
You can find the layout view if you go into the Solution Explorer, go into view Shared folder
and here is underscore layout.csHTML.
There's nothing special about that underscore.
Many developers use underscore just as a convention to identify views
that are not primary content views like the index view that we wrote.
It's not a view you would typically return as a view result from a controller.
But the layout view itself is really nothing special.
For the most part, it's just another Razor view.
It has literal text that can have C Sharp code expressions, it can have code blocks.
It's where you typically have your doc type.
It's where you want to have your head tag
and you typically have a definition for the body element.
And any changes that I make here will be reflected across the entire application
because in this application, this is the only layout view that we're using.
You can have more than one but we may now have only one.
I can demonstrate that if I collapse this header section
and then let me just use Control K, Control C to comment that out.
I'll save the view and refresh.
And you can see not only did our restaurant review is changed but also if I was able
to navigate to the homepage, it's also missing that section now too.
To undo commenting that out and scroll down here a little bit,
and here is where you can see the call to a RenderBody.
When a layout view calls RenderBody, that is on the content view,
our Index.csHTML that is one it will render and output it to HTML
and that HTML will be inserted right here where RenderBody is.
One obvious question at this point might be,
how does the MVC runtime know to use this layout view?
We're not saying anything inside of the layout view that would be particular
to telling everyone that this is the layout view for the application.
We're certainly not doing anything inside of Index.csHTML that indicates
that that's the layout view we're using.
And the answer to this question actually comes
from a small magical file called underscore ViewStart.csHTML.
You'll find it in the root of your Views folder.
When I open that file up you can see there's a code block inside of here
that sets a layout property equal to tilde slash Views slash Shared slash
underscore Layout.csHTML.
So the secret here is that underscore ViewStart.csHTML has the ability
to execute this code before my view starts rendering and it sets this property.
And this is just a convention with the Razor view engine.
If you have a file called underscore ViewStart.csHTML,
anything you put in that code block at the top will be able to execute before the view does.
And this works in a hierarchy.
So if ViewStart.csHTML is in the root of the Views folder,
it applies to all the views that are inside of here.
But if I make a copy of this file and put it inside of Reviews,
let's open up this copy underscore ViewStart.csHTML
and change this over to Layout2.
Now I'll save everything and refresh the home page.
We have our header section back and this works normally.
But if I go to reviews, we'll get a runtime error because we've specified that the Views
and the Reviews folder should use a different layout file,
underscore Layout.csHTML and that doesn't exist.
So in order for this to work I don't have
to have underscore Layout.csHTML in the shared folder.
So let me delete this file.
First, let me make a copy of this.
And also I'll show you that you can overwrite this on a per view basis.
So if I open up our index view that's showing the latest reviews,
I can also specify the layout file here and let's just change it
to Layout3.csHTML so we can see a difference.
Save everything and refresh.
Now it's looking for Layout3.
I can also turn off a layout view here if I wanted to.
I could just say layout.
I don't want to use a layout page.
I'll set that equal to null.
And now it's working but we're also not using a layout page
so we do not have any style sheets applied and the view looks very plain and simple.
Let's go back to using the default layout view.
Now inside of a layout view, in addition to RenderBody
which is a required call somewhere inside of a layout view you must call RenderBody.
You can also call another method called RenderSection.
This is optional.
You can have one or more sections.
And what RenderSection will do is provide a content view like Index.csHTML,
the ability to plug in content into other sections of the page.
So this RenderSection is rendering a section called featured.
There's also another RenderSection down here at the bottom of the layout view
that will allow a content page to inject scripts at the bottom of the page.
We'll come back to that later when we talk about Ajax.
But right now let's talk about this RenderSection
which is currently not a required section
that means a content view can have this section that cannot.
If I switch this over to be a required section,
what will happen when we render this Reviews view is
that we get a runtime error saying you did not have this section called featured.
I want to change this back to being an optional section but we're also going to implement
that section inside of Index.csHTML.
Let's just take this bit of markup that we already have and put it inside of a section.
We can define these sections anywhere.
You just have to give them the name.
That name has to match what you specified in RenderSection.
And let's put that we are showing the latest X number of reviews inside
of the featured section and refresh.
And you can see that appears at the top of the view.
But inside of layout, if for some reason I wanted to show a featured content at the bottom
of the page, let's say in the footer, I could also work.
So let me move that section back up to the top.
And now that I'm looking at it, what would be really nice is that when I'm on the home page
of the application, I'd have a link here to go
to that ReviewsController instead of typing reviews into the URL.
That's easy enough.
This is the navigational menu that the layout page specifies.
Let me make a copy of that last action link and create a new action link.
We've looked at this before.
This is the text I want to display, Reviews.
This is the action that I want to reach from some controller, the Index action.
And this is the name of the controller that I want to reach, the ReviewsController.
And now if I save everything and refresh, we'll have a Reviews link
that will appear throughout the application.
I can click on it and we end up on the ReviewsController.