The action link helper that we just used is one
of many HTML helpers available inside of the view.
The purpose of an HTML helper is to make it easy to create small blocks of HTML.
There are helpers to create links like action link but there's also helpers to create inputs,
validation messages, labels and more.
Many of these helpers are quite intelligent.
For example, in these codes on the screen, we're calling HTML.EditorFor and passing
in an expression that references a property on the model, the FirstName property.
EditorFor can walk up to that property and examine its type,
determined that the FirstName property is a string and therefore what it needs
to do is emit an input type equals text.
If instead we were using EditorFor against the Boolean property,
then EditorFor could produce a checkbox input.
There's actually a number of other things that EditorFor will do.
We'll explore this as we move throughout the rest of the course.
But all of these methods like EditorFor, LabelFor, ValidationSummary,
they're available from an HTML property that a view inherits.
That's another reason we call them HTML helpers
and it's also the reason we access them using HTML dot.
Let's use a few of these in our application.
Inside of our Index view, lets' give ourselves the ability
to edit any particular restaurant review because the edit scenario is going
to involve a lot more HTML helpers than what we've seen so far.
So let me add a span inside of a div for each review,
a span that's going to be aligned to the right.
And inside of here we will use HTML.ActionLink to display a link that displays the text edit
and we'll go to the Edit action on this current controller.
I also need to pass along some information so that the Edit action knows
which review I'm trying to edit and I can do that by passing along the ID of the review.
So I just need to say item.Id.
The ID property then is wrapped up in an anonymous object.
And you can put as many additional values as you want inside that anonymous object,
that get passed along to the routing engine
and essentially say here's some additional information that needs to go in the URL.
The routing engine is going to look at ID and say, oh, I can see where I can put ID actually
into the URL, so we should come out with something like slash reviews, slash edit,
slash three to edit the review with an ID of three.
And let's test it out, I'll save the view, refresh the browser.
There's our Edit link.
It looks correct.
Slash review, slash edit, slash three.
And when I click on that, we already have an edit controller action
because when we scaffold it out this controller, we said that we wanted a controller
with the ability to update reviews.
But what we don't have yet is a view itself.
But that's okay because we also need to add a little bit more logic here into the edit action.
This is the edit action that responds to that Get request.
The ID that's in the URL will automatically be extracted
by the runtime and passed into our action.
All I need to do is go out to our data source and find that review that we want to edit.
So I can say that the review, it goes reviews give me the single review.
Or I'm given a review R dot ID equals that incoming ID.
So just a little link query to say give me single object out of this collection
that matches this criteria, its ID property has to match this incoming ID parameter
and that is the model for our view.
Now we actually need an edit views but we don't have this error screen over here.
I can right click inside the edit action say please add a view for me.
We do want it to be called the edit view, we do want to use Razor.
It's going to be strongly-typed against the RestaurantReview.
All of this is correct.
But I do want to scaffold out this time an edit view.
Now when I click Add, I'll have a brand new edit view.
And what I should be able to do now is just do a quick build
and refresh slash review slash edit slash three.
And now I have a form that will let me edit all these values.
So let's take a step back and see what some of these HTML helpers are doing.
And one easy way to do that is to go in and view the source for this
and compare it to what is inside of our view.
Let me scroll down a bit.
And now we can start to match some things up.
So HTML.BeginForm writes out an opening form tag.
Without passing any additional parameters into begin form, what it will do is emit
that form tag, it will set the action of that form tag to go to the same URL that we came
from slash Review slash Edit slash 3 but to do a post back when the user clicks on the button
to submit this form and save data.
Begin form is useful because you can pass in additional parameters
to change that URL, change the method.
It will take care of emitting the correct HTML.
A little further down we have a HTML.HiddenFor.
What this helper will do is it will emit an input type equals hidden into the form
so we're storing the ID value in the form.
We're just not giving the user the ability to edit that value, it's a hidden input.
And down a little bit further we have HTML.LabelFor.
Labels are great for accessibility.
And this is simply building a label attribute where the
for attribute is equal to the name of the property.
So the name is name-- or the name of the city, in that case will build label for city.
And then we have editor for HTML.EditorFor is literally saying I want an editor
for this property.
Now you go out and figure out what the best type of editor for.
Maybe that editor will be an input type equals text
or an input type equals number or a checkbox or radio button.
In fact if we scroll down a little bit further, we can see that the input
for a rating is type equals number.
That's a new input field for HTML 5 on browsers that are up-to-date with the standards,
they'll know that the user is supposed to input a number here not just some random string
like A B C. There's also a lot of data dash attributes in here
like data dash val, data dash val dash number.
Those are providing data for client side validation.
We'll talk about that later in this course.
But for now, I just want to point out that this is what HTML helpers are all about.
We could certainly for the rating come in and all by ourselves say
that we just want an input type equals number and set the value to at Model.Rating
but EditorFor will do that for us.
And also populate the ID and the name attributes so that the editor
of the input matches that property name of our model.
And if you remember back in our discussion in the last module, we talked about the way
that the MVC has a way of matching up things that we need by name.
So if we see that we need an ID parameter as a parameter to our action method, it will go out
and look for something called ID and it can look
in the routing data, it can look in the query string.
It can also look in these posted form values.
So if I need a rating for my model something that the user has typed into the screen
and then click save, the MVC framework can automatically find that rating and move it
into a property for me just based on a naming convention.
We'll see that here in just a second.
But let me close the source code view and implement what should happen
when the user clicks on the save button.
In that case that's going to be an HTTP post message.
This is also a topic we talked about in the last module.
That will end up not at this edit action because this responds to a get request.
It will end up at this edit action that explicitly advertises itself
as basically only replying to a post.
I'm going to change around the code that was given to us automatically just a little bit.
And the idea here is that I want to take values that the users typed in.
I want them-- and I want to move them into a review so I can save that.
First, let's grab the review that we need to edit.
And then to move the values in, I'm going to call a method called TryUpdateModel.
What TryUpdateModel will do is go through a process known as model binding.
In fact, model binding happens anytime you even have a parameter in an action method.
It's what ASP.NET MVC does when it goes out and it looks around in the request try
to find things to move into an object for you.
So when I have a parameter called ID on the edit action,
the model binder in ASP.NET MVC will find that ID, move it into that for me.
When I say TryUpdateModel on review, the model binder will go out and look at review,
see that it has a rating property, and then go out and try to find something called rating.
But fortunately, there should be a posted form input named rating.
The MVC runtime will find that and just move it into my review.
If anything fails, if any validation errors occur, TryUpdateModel will return false
and I don't want to save that review.
We'll talk more about validation later.
And if that happens, I can return the view with that same review to try
to let the user fix whatever problem they have.
But if TryUpdateModel works, this is the point where I would save that into the database.
We're not working with the database yet.
And for right now, what I will do is return a redirect action.
Let's go back to the index action.
I want to redirect here instead of just letting the users sit
on the saved values on that posted form field.
It's very common that after an HTTP post
where the user has saved something you redirect them back to a page
where they can view the changed results.
That way, they don't hit refresh on the result of this post operation
and accidentally submit something twice.
But with this logic in place, let's try to do a build and let me come out and do a get
on this page slash review slash edit slash 3 so we can start everything over.
So you can come up again with the house of Elliot let's bump the rating down to a 9
and click save and you can see we made that change.
Let's edit this again change this back to a 10, perhaps using alternate spelling for Gent
and click save, those change is also reflected here.
And one of the reasons this was so easy to build is because we're using TryUpdateModel
which just relies on the names of properties to match up data
with what needs to get pushed into the model.
And all of that matches up because our edit view is using things like HTML.EditorFor
which will automatically build the correct inputs with the right names and the IDs
and the validation and everything else associated with it.
There are many other HTML helpers that are available than what you see here,
you can see them in the IntelliSense window.
There's ways to build check boxes.
There's ways to display things, there's ways to generate names,
route links and validation messages.
You can also build your own custom HTML helpers.
And I would suggest that if you find yourself typing a lot of C sharp code into a Razor view
to build an HTML element, I would suggest you go out and look at how to build a custom helper.
They're very easy to build and then they're very easy to use and a custom helper can really help
to get logic out of your view and keep the view as simple as possible.
That's really the ultimate goal of the HTML helpers, keeps views simple.
( Pause )