Another type of view that you'll find useful
when building MVC applications is the partial view.
A partial view allows you to allow you to put HTML on C sharp code into a file
that you can reuse across multiple other views.
We'll see some used cases for partial views in this course but for now, let's just imagine
that the div we have here to display a review is something that we need
in several different places in the application.
We show the reviews in a couple different places and we'd like the display to be consistent
but we do not want to duplicate this code every time we display a review.
We want to reuse it that's why I'm going to select the code and cut it out of this view.
Then I'll come over to our views folder, the reviews folder in the views folder
and say add a new view and I'll call this underscore review.
Again the underscore is just a convention that means this is a special type of view
in this case it's a partial view.
It's still a Razor view.
It can still be strongly typed against the restaurant review
but this time I'll leave the Scaffold template empty
because I already have the mark up that I want to put in here.
And I will select the check box that says create as a partial view.
What that really means is that when Visual Studio creates this,
it won't automatically add a code block at the top of the view to set the page title
because we don't want to set the page title
from a partial view that's the responsibility of the content view.
This is just rendering a portion of the page.
And now I can click add and I will paste in the code that I cut out from the index view
and hit control K, control D to do some formatting.
In this case, it just bumps it up against the left margin and aligns some things.
But in the mean time you have some HTML or C sharp code
that doesn't quite fit right, it's not formatted properly.
If you hit control K, control D that will do some formatting for you.
There is one other change I have to make in this view.
It used to be inside of a foreach loop that had a local variable called item.
Now, the model for this view is actually going to be a single restaurant review.
So I need to change item to model.
And one quick and easy way to do that is with quick replace.
We'll just change item to model, replace all and now our view should be ready to go.
And you can see that the partial view is just another Razor view.
It has the same csHTML extension that can still be strongly typed.
It still has a model that it can work against.
It's just the intention is that we're going to reuse this from other views
in the way you render a partial view, is to use another HTML helper HTML.Partial.
When you call HTML partial, you give it the name or the view that you want
to render in this case, Review.csHTML.
And you don't need to specify the file extension when you ask the MVC runtime to render a partial
but I can pass in the model that it needs to render.
The model in this case is each individual review each item.
And with all this in place, I can just save everything and refresh the application.
The user won't see any visual difference in the page.
It looks exactly the same as it did before.
We've just made a structural change in how the page displays.
We've created this partial view and we might have done that because we want
to reuse that across several other views.
Another good reason to use a partial view is just to simplify a view.
Now the foreach statement is a lot easier to read because I can clearly see when it starts
and when it ends and I can see that all we really do
in here is render each review using a partial view.
I also want to point out that since we put underscore review in the reviews folder,
it's only available from other views that are in the same folder.
If instead, we had placed this view in the shared folder, it would be available anywhere
in the application from any view to say render partial this review.
I also want to show you another scenario where partial views can be useful.
So one way to render a partial is to use this HTML.PartialHelper.
Typically, this is the approach you take when you want to reuse a piece of the HTML
or you want to simplify a view because you have a really complex model.
But regardless of why you're using HTML.Partial, when you do use it the only data
or model information that you can pass to HTML.Partial is model information
that you already have available inside of your view.
So you can pass the model item or you can pass a subset of the model item
like here, we just passed a single review.
But you can also come across a situation where you want
to render something that is not part of your model.
This frequently comes up with the layout view.
Because the layout view is executing for every page in the application,
and so it's very difficult to tie it to any particular model, there's ways to do that
but it involves a lot of messy inheritance.
So the scenario I'm talking about is imagine in the layout view if we want the best review
in the database to always appear somewhere on the page.
If I went to do that there's no way for me to go into the layout view
and specify a model directive here that says this view will always have a restaurant review
as a model because this layout view is used again throughout the entire application.
It's used on pages that display restaurant reviews but it will also be used on pages
that display restaurants or allow a user to register and log in.
And all of those other scenarios, they do not involve restaurant reviews.
So I cannot strongly type this layout view to a particular model.
But there is another helper available that can allow me to solve that situation.
And it involves partial views quite frequently.
This other helper is called HTML.Action.
So imagine we do want to show the best review on every page in the application.
We'll show it down here just above the footer.
What I can do is invoke HTML.Action and what HTML.Action allows you to do is set
up a sub request inside of this primary MVC request.
So it's a subrequest that can go out and call another controller action
that builds its own model and dependent of what the main controller is doing
and render its own view, a partial view that will be inserted right here
where the call to HTML.Action is.
So let's say that we need to build an action called BestReview.
And this is always going to be on the Reviews controller.
Just like HTML.Action link, you can also pass in additional parameters here
that will get passed along to this other controller action,
but we don't need to pass any parameters.
And this is basically saying go out and call this action on the reviews controller
and whatever it omits, whatever outputs whatever the result is,
place it here where I have HTML.Action.
And I do want to point out that this is not a separate HTTP request.
This doesn't require the browser to come back to the server and call this other controller action
into controller action that's called from server code it's like a subrequest.
So let's go over to the ReviewsController we need to implement BestReview
and I'll just put it as the top action here.
This can still be an action that returns an action result.
Actually it's going to be returning a PartialViewResult and it's called BestReview.
We'll need to find the best review and I realized that all
of our reviews right now have a rating of 10, so we'd need to find a way
to reconcile a tie or let's say from R in reviews.
Now we orderby R dot rating in descending order.
Now, we have our reviews in sorted order and now we're going
to return not a view this time, but a PartialView.
And we could create a brand new PartialView for this action to render.
It could be called BestReview.
We could also render that other PartialView that we just created,
the one that is called underscore Review.csHTML.
Again, no extension needed here and we will pass in the first review that we picked up based
on putting the reviews in the sorted order.
This is by the way how you would overwrite what view and action is going to render,
you can always explicitly specify a view by name here without the file extension.
But I can do that for the IndexView too.
If I didn't want it to return the IndexView
for some reason I could always specify a view name by string here.
But now I should be able to do a bill and let's come out to the home page of the application.
And what we should see here at the bottom of the home page is there's our best review.
We should probably put a better title around it so we know why
that information is appearing here.
But that should now be on every page of the application, because it's in the lay out view.
And we did that by calling an action that got to build its own model, render its own view
so it's completely independent from everything else,
it didn't really complicate our layout view to do those.
But one thing to keep in mind when you do build an action like this BestReview,
as I said before, your public methods are available to the browser.
So if I come in to the browser and I go
to slash Reviews slash BestReview I will be able to get that result.
Because like all public methods on the controller, if the user enters the right URL
into the browser, they're going to be able to invoke the controller action.
But in this case, if you do not want that to happen, there's an attribute
that you can apply to this action.
It's called ChildActionOnly.
And if I do that and do a build it's no longer legal to call
that directly using an HTTP request.
You can only access this by calling HTML.Action as a child request,
so it would still work in the layout view.
I just can't call it directly.
And now you know a couple of different ways to use partial views.
There's HTML.Partial which allows you to simplify a view and reuse HTML.
And there's also HTML.Action which allows you to set up a completely independent subrequest
that builds its own model and renders its own PartialView.
( Pause )