In this module, we covered a number of different topics related
to building views in an MVC application.
We look at the Razor syntax, and learned about implicit
and explicit code expressions as well as code blocks.
We talked about HTML Helpers and I showed you how helpers
like EditorFor will help you build form inputs.
But I haven't told you the whole story there yet.
We'll see more when we start validating incoming data.
We did look at layout views and how they can define the UI structure for our application
and I demonstrated how Razor does HTML encoding for us
to help avoid cross-site scripting attacks.
Finally, I showed you a couple of scenarios where PartialViews can be your friend.
You can use partials to render a portion of your model in a reasonable way
and you can also use partials and child requests with HTML.Action
to delegate work to another controller.