Hi, this is Scott Allen, and welcome to my course on ASP.NET MVC 4.
In this course, we'll start building an application from scratch, and throughout the course we will see how
to build an entire application using the C# language
that stores data in a SQL Server database. Since this is a web application, we'll also be using JavaScript,
HTML, and CSS. But the primary focus is on ASP.NET MVC, so we will spend our time learning about the M and V
and C in MVC, that is models, views, and controllers. We'll see how controllers can respond to a user's
request, and how that controller can build a model, and how they can send the model to a view when we build
the UI for our web page. We'll also be using models to update data in the database, and that's the part of
the course where we can learn how to work with HTML forms and validate the data a user has entered.
By the end of the course, you'll be in a good position to work on your own ASP.NET MVC applications and build
a web application for your users. I do expect that you are already familiar with the C# language and know
some of the basics of a web application, like how to use HTML.
If not, we have plenty of courses on Pluralsight that cover everything from the HTTP protocol itself to using
JavaScript, CSS, and HTML together, as well as courses on the C# language.
I hope you enjoy the course.