The letter J in AJAX stands for JavaScript which means we'll need
to send JavaScript to the client.
And I think it will be good to look at what Script Libraries are already available
in the project and how to manage those scripts to get them to the client
which will demonstrate some new features in the framework.
So inside of the Scripts folder in Solution Explorer,
you can see the JavaScript files are available when you create a new project.
We'll start at the top with _references.js.
This file works with Visual Studio 2012 to give Studio a list of the files you commonly use
so that you can get better IntelliSense when writing JavaScript.
If we open up the file, we'll see it contains references inside of JavaScript comments.
These references look suspiciously like XML.
But these references are telling Visual Studio what files you commonly use.
We can see the list includes jquery, jquery-ui and more.
And now, Visual Studio will go out and find those files and parse them
and try to provide better IntelliSense for you.
It should know about method names and attributes of the objects
that you work with from these libraries.
If you were commonly working with additional libraries in the application,
you probably want to list those files here too.
Underneath of references is the jQuery library.
There's three versions of the core jQuery library file.
The first one has IntelliSense in the name.
You'll never use this file.
You'll never send it to the client.
This is just another aid for Visual Studio to generate intelligent prompts with IntelliSense.
When the references file says to reference jQuery,
Visual Studio will automatically find this file which has some additional comments inside
to make Visual Studio look smarter.
The jquery-1.7.1.js file, that's the core jQuery library that you can send to the client.
If you aren't familiar with the jQuery, then it is a JavaScript library
that gives us an API we can use on the client to select and manipulate DOM elements,
make asynchronous call to the server, and lots more.
jQuery supports all the modern browsers including Internet Explorer,
Chromes, Safari, Firefox, Opera.
And if you're new to jQuery, you'll see a few tips on this module.
This version of the jQuery file is very readable.
If you open it up, you can find lots of white space, well-formatted code, and comments.
The jQuery file with .min in the name is minified.
Minification is the process of going through a JavaScript file and making it small as possible
by removing unneeded white space, unneeded comments, and even shortening the names
of symbols and variables that are exposed to the outside world.
If you open that up, you'll see it's not very readable.
But it is smaller, and by making the file smaller, the browser will need less time
to download the file, which means, your page can load faster and users like fast pages.
However, we don't really need to touch this file because there's feature in ASP.NET MVC 4
that will automatically minify files for us
or pick up minified files as we'll see in just a bit.
In the Scripts folder, we also have jquery-ui which is a plug-in or extension for jQuery
that gives you UI widgets like dialog and accordion that you can use.
There's a minified and unminified version.
We also have jquery.validate, another plug-in for jQuery.
This one provides client side validation features.
The MVC framework actually relies on this library.
We also have knockout.js which you can use on the client to apply a model view--
view model design pattern in client script.
It provides features like declarative data by mean.
And then, there is modernizr, which as I mentioned early in the course,
is a library to detect and enable HTML5 features on a browser.
The files I skipped over all have unobtrusive in the mean, and these files are authored
by the MVC team and they serve as a bridge between ASP.NET MVC and jQuery.
In order for some MVC features to work like client side validation,
you need both the jQuery validation library and jQuery,
and the jquery.validate.unobtrusive script file because it takes metadata that's omitted
by HTML helpers like Editor 4 and feeds that data into jQuery validations
so it can apply the validation rules on the client.
We'll see that metadata in this module.
And now that we know what's here, let's look at how we send these script files
to the client in an efficient manner.