Libraries like jQuery and Modernizr are libraries that you typically use everywhere
in an application, which means you need a script reference on every page.
And as we've learned, it is the Layout views that are the place to go
when you have some common markup that you want on every page.
This application only has one Layout view.
It's in the Shared folder.
It's called _Layout.
And at the very top of the Layout view, you can see a call to Script.Render.
And this somehow involves Modernizr.
Before we talk about the details of Scripts.Render, let me just assure you,
this will put a script tag referencing the Modernizr JavaScript library into the top
of the page here, inside of the head tag.
It is important to include some JavaScript libraries at the top of a page.
This is true for Modernizr.
Modernizr needs to start executing before the rest of your HTML goes to the client.
As we talked about in the first module of the course, Modernizr will make sure older browser
like IE6 are prepared to work with a new HTML5 elements like nav
and section which appear in this page.
And to do this, Modernizr has to start executing before those elements appear.
Other libraries and scripts don't need to appear at the top of every page.
You can instead include them at the bottom of a page.
And if we come down to the bottom of the Layout view, we can see another call to Script.Render.
This one somehow involves jQuery.
When possible, you should add scripts to the bottom of the page
because it can make a page perform better, or at least,
it looks like the page is performing better because the browser doesn't have to block
as it downloads the script and executes the code inside.
Web browsers tend to bring everything else to a halt when they encounter a script tag.
But by placing scripts at the bottom, we get more content to the client
as the HTML images will start to display and then finally,
the browsers sees the scripts and loads them at the end.
And now, let's go to the question of what is Scripts.Render doing?
And for that matter, what is Styles.Render doing?
Because it turns out, these two calls are closely related.
They both rely on new features and ASP.NET that can bundle and minify files for you.
Scripts.Render can give you a minified job script bundle.
Style.Render can give you a minified bundle of style sheets.
What's a bundle, you might ask.
Well, another way to boost the performance of a webpage is to combine files together,
so a browser doesn't need to download as many resources.
For example, if you have three style sheets to include in a page,
you might want to bundle them together into a single style sheet
so the browser only downloads one file instead of three.
But, during development, it's often nice to have three separate files.
They're probably creative for different purposes and it's easy to find
and maintain the code when it's nicely separated.
That provides a bit of tension because we went three files
for development, but a single file for download.
And this is where the bundling feature in ASP.NET steps
in because it can dynamically bundle files together at runtime.
To see this, let's open up the Global.asax.cs file, look in our friend,
the application start event where we can see a call in here to BundleConfig.RegisterBundles.
Up at the cursor there, and strike the F12 key to open that file up.
And here we arrive inside of a class
that is building various style bundles and script bundles.
There are two parts to a bundle.
First, you give the bundle a virtual path to reach the bundle.
In other words, if I open up a browser and come to this URL,
I'll receive all the files that are included in the bundle.
This is also the path or the identifier you use when you reference a bundle and want
to render it using Scripts.Render or Styles.Render.
The files that are included in the bundle are listed with calls to include
and you might want to include one file.
You can certainly have a one file bundle.
But you can also include multiple files.
You can specify a full name here.
You can also specify a place holder for a version number and you can use wild cards.
For instance, the first script bundle here that is basically including jQuery is going
to have a placeholder for the version.
That means if I upgrade jQuery from -1.7.1 to -1.8.0,
I don't need to come in and change my C# code.
The script bundle will automatically pick up the latest version from the file system,
whatever is in my Scripts folder, and it's smart enough to distinguish
between IntelliSense files, minified files, and unminified files.
So even though we have three versions of that core jQuery library, the IntelliSense,
the minified and the regular file, it's only going to pick the one that it needs
and it won't include jQuery more than once.
You can also use wild cards.
So down here in the jQuery validation bundle, you can see a call to jquery.unobtrusive,
that means go out and find all the files that start with jquery.unobtrusive.
But again, it's going to be smart enough not to include both the minified
and the unminified file, it can distinguish between those two.
So the first bundle, the jQuery bundle, that's a bundle of one file.
And that's okay because in bundling will add some other features to this,
it can minify files that aren't minified.
In the jQuery validation bundle, that's going to include at least two files,
jquery.unobtrusive and jquery.validate.
Once you've created a bundle which includes all of the files that you need,
you render it in markup using Scripts.Render or Styles.Render as we saw on the Layout view.
And you can see, it is using that virtual path,
that identifier that you selected for the bundle.
And I call it a virtual path because there's not really a file at that location.
But the MVC runtime is smart enough to intercept that request and route it through the bundling
and minification pictures here which will served up the files you need.
So once you've created a bundle, you render Scripts.Render or Styles.Render.
And these methods will behave differently depending on your application configuration.
So for example, back in Bundle.Config, there was a StyleBundle to find
for all of the jQuery UI style sheets.
You can see those quite a few of them because they factor them out based on features.
If you wand to use just a dialog, then all you need
to do is include the core style sheet and the dialog style sheet.
But if you use everything, you'd want to include all these style sheets.
I'm going to take this bundle and render it from the Layout view
because eventually we will be using jQuery UI.
So I just need to add a call to Styles.Render and pass that path in.
And now, let's run the application.
And I'll do a View Source.
And you can see, with my single call to Styles.Render,
I omitted a link for each style sheet into the page, almost 12 links or exactly 12 links.
So it added a style sheet link for every file in the bundle.
You might think that's not much of a bundling feature if we have individual links,
or certainly not combining things into a single download.
But this is because we are running the application in debug mode.
And in debug mode, you'll find it easier to debug scripts and styles
when they are not bundled up into a single download.
However, if I come over into the Web.config file, we can change how we're running.
I just need to find the debug setting which is right here at the top.
We'll change it from true to false so that we're running in release mode.
And I'll run the application again, and do a View Source.
And now, you can see there is a single link tag admitted since we're in a release mode.
And if I were to take this URL and place it into the browser to download this directly,
it will all get back as a css file, let's open it in Notepad.
And that's all of the css from all 12 of those files combined into a single file.
It's also been minified, so it's been made as small as possible.
There's no white space or comments to make this a larger download.
This bundling and minification features then can really decrease the amount of time needed
to load a page, and they're easy to use.
We'll be using them in this application as we send more scripts to the client just
by defining the new bundles and using Scripts.Render
to put those scripts in the client.
( Pause )