Now that we know how to get scripts down to the client,
let's add some AJAXy features to the application.
We'll start with a homepage.
We currently have a search here which is working just fine,
but let's make things a little bit harder.
Instead of three restaurants, let's use 1,000 restaurants.
And the easiest way to do this is to see the database with a thousand restaurants.
I'll swing over into our Migrations folder and open up Configuration.cs.
Inside of here, you remember, is our Seed method.
And what I can do inside of here is just add a loop from 0 to less than 1,000.
And for each iteration of the loop, we'll just add another restaurant
that just has a name like 1, 2, 3, and 4.
All these restaurants are in no where USA.
Just having that code in place, if I open up the Package Manager Console,
I should be able to update the database which will execute that Seed method
and will have a lot more restaurant in the database.
Now, the Seed method is complete, so let's swing back into the application.
And now that we have all these restaurants, we're currently only taking the top ten.
It becomes much more important to be able to search.
We'll also need some paging, but we'll worry about that later.
Let's say I scroll halfway down the page and I search for restaurants.
Let's start with 77.
And the search still works, I can find restaurant 77 and 770.
But you'll notice what happens when I do the search, when I scrolled down into the page,
is I completely lose my scroll position.
And that's because we're doing a full request back
to the server withdrawing the entire page and it starts fresh.
It would be nice if I could search for restaurants and not lose my scroll position.
In other words, I just type in a search term, click Search,
and just this portion of the page refreshes.
You could think of this is a partial page update very similar
to what update panel could do in ASP.NET.
Let's add that feature, but first, I want to fix somethings up the way
that scripts are managed in this application right now.
What I want to do to simplify things is have a single script bundle that's rendered
at the bottom of every page from the Layout view.
And in order to do that, I'm going to need to fix up a few things that I've been scaffolded
into the data modification views like the view to edit a restaurant.
When we've been scaffolding up these views, we've been allowing the scaffolder
to include Scripts.Render at the bottom of this views or inside of the scripts section.
And it's rendering the scripts for everything that's needed for jQuery validation
and the clients side validation to work.
Basically, I want to take those scripts out of here.
If I just do a Search and Find in Files for section Scripts,
I'll find all the files where this is in place.
And what I'm going to do is coming to each one, and I'll leave the script section in place,
but I want to delete that Scripts.Render from each one.
And now that I've deleted eight instances of that script bundle,
let's close out all the documents that I opened, and come in to out App_Start folder.
It's inside of here where we will define a new bundle in BundleConfig.cs
that will take care of all our script needs.
I'll paste the code in here at the top of the class.
We're essentially going to create bundles under ~/bundles/otf or OdeToFood.
And we'll include jquery, jquery-ui and all of the scripts we need
for unobtrusive JavaScript and jQuery validation.
And now, I can come in to the Layout view.
And at the bottom of the page, instead of rendering just jQuery,
we will render that script bundle.
And now, the application should behave the same.
We're just going to have more scripts inside of every page.
It's going to simplify things for us in this application.
And now, we can work on this feature in the Index view for the HomeController.
Inside of here, let me comment out the simple form that we have in place
and replace it with the call to Ajax.BeginForm.
Ajax.BeginForm is very similar to Html.BeginForm.
It writes out to form tag and you can tell what controller and action and route values to use.
But Ajax.BeginForm will make an asynchronous request to the server.
Html.BeginForm makes a synchronous request to the server that withdraws the entire screen.
Ajax.BeginForm makes an async request and it can withdraw just a portion of the screen.
All you need to do is tell the helper what to update on the page, and you could do this
with the AjaxOptions object that we pass it.
We tell the helper to make a get request and whatever comes back should replace the content
in the page that's currently identified by this UpdateTargetId.
We don't have an HTML element by that name, so I need to add one.
This element will delimit essentially the area that we want updated.
So I want to update all of the restaurant information and all of that is now inside
of a div with an id of restaurantList.
And with just this code in place, let me press F5 to run this application with the debugger.
That will prompt me to change by Web.config back.
If you remember, we went into Web.config and set debug equals false.
This is going to set that back to true which makes things a little bit easier
to debug if something goes wrong.
I'll just click Okay and let it make that change.
And now, in the application, let's search for 23.
And you can see this kind of works.
Asynchronous form made a request back to the server, got back a response,
and then we're after that into the page where the restaurant list used to be.
So we now we have a page inside of a page that has a restaurant list
and I could continue doing that infinitely.
So the problem in here is that the client side stuff all worked, we need this server
to respond differently when we do a search.
We need it to return just updated restaurants that should be displayed on the page.
And that means this restaurantList needs to display in two ways.
First of all, it needs to display on the homepage
when the user first comes to the homepage.
We need the restaurant list there.
And then, when we do a search, we need the restaurant list
to display and just the restaurant list.
And since we're going to need to this in two places,
that means we'll be using a partial view.
Let me cut the restaurantList out of the Index view and come into the views
for the HomeController and add a view called _Restaurants.
This will be a Razor view.
It's going to be a partial view.
And I'll just click Add and paste in our HTML.
We can also make this strongly typed.
It's going to have the same model is the Index view, so I'll just copy the model directive
out of the Index view, paste it into _Restaurants, that's our partial view.
That's part of what we have to do.
Now, we can render this when someone renders the Index view, so that we get a full page
with the restaurants and the header and the login and everything.
So we'll render Restaurants and we'll send the model along to be rendered.
And now, it's really going to be up to the controller to decide how to render a response
to the indexed action because this is all happening through the index action,
the homepage, the search results.
Let's open up the HomeController and I'll show you how easy it is
to make this decision inside of the HomeController.
What I'll do is stop debugging, shift F5.
And then paste in a little bit of code that can determine if a request arriving
to the server is in an asynchronous request.
It does this behind the scenes by looking into the HTTP headers.
There'll be a special flag there that you can find
out easily just by asking Request.IsAjaxRequest.
So if it is an asynchronous request, we'll return just that partial view
with the restaurant information, otherwise, we'll return the full view.
Use the same model object for both views.
But now, if I run the application again, we should have the result we're looking for.
I'll scroll down the page just a little bit and search for 24.
And you can see that bottom portion of the screen just updates instantly.
We don't lose our scroll position.
In fact, it's sometimes hard to tell that the screen changed.
We might need to add a little animation or fade-in, fade-out effect,
just to draw the user's attention to the fact that the screen has in fact updated.