Now that we have this nice asynchronous search feature,
it would be nice if we could also help our users find a restaurant they are looking
for by providing some suggestions when they start typing in the search box.
In other words, if I type the letter S, I'd like to see a list of possible restaurants
that start with the letter S as I'm typing.
Fortunately, we have jQuery UI in the project
and jQuery UI includes an autocomplete widget that will help us do this.
The way autocomplete works is that when the user starts typing, we can configure autocomplete
to make a request to the server and find possible matches.
Of course, we'll be calling a controller action
and the controller action will need to return JSON.
That's one of the formats that autocomplete can work with.
And then, once it has the list of possible restaurants,
it will take care of the UI part and put that list on the screen.
Since we're going to need some JSON data, let's start with a controller.
And since we are on the Index view of the HomeController, I'll put this action
that autocomplete will call in the HomeController.
This action is called autocomplete, but you could call it quick search or restaurant search
or anything that you want because ultimately, we'll tell autocomplete what URL to call
and we'll have control over what action it we call.
But I do expect this action to receive a parameter called term.
How do I know that, because if you look on jQueryUI.com,
they have lots of wonderful examples and demonstrations of how these widgets work.
And the documentation for autocomplete says when the user is typing, it will send a request
to the server and include a parameter in the request called term
and that will represent what the user has typed so far.
So I know if it sends something named term, I can get that as an action parameter.
I just need to take that term and query the database with it.
We'll say please give us the restaurants where the name of the restaurant starts
with whatever term that autocomplete has given me.
We will limit the result set to the first ten restaurants that we find
and then we'll do a projection with the select operator.
We'll turn every restaurant into an object that has a label property
and that label property will be equal to the restaurant name.
Why am I creating something with a label property?
Because, again, the jQuery UI documentation for autocomplete says the JSON you return,
the object should have a label property, or a value property, or a label and a value
that will use any combination of that.
Just giving it a label will be enough to have it put something on the screen
and when the user selects it, it'll put it into the input box for us.
All I need to do is to put that into JSON format which as we saw early
in this course is very easy to do, just invoke the JSON method,
it will serialize my model into JSON format.
We're going to allow this to happen during a get request.
And I should be able to test up this controller action from the browser.
If I just do a build, I can come and go to that controller action from the browser
and see the JSON that it's going to produce.
We'll go to home, autocomplete and let's pass a search term of 1 along.
And I can see the browser is telling me that some JSON came back the server.
We'll open that up.
And there I can see my JSON array.
It looks like all the objects have label properties.
Looks like all the objects have the label property set correctly.
So I think this is going to work with autocomplete.
Now, we just need to implement the client side of this.
The way autocomplete works from the client site is you have to wire it up against the input
that needs the autocomplete behavior.
And the way I'll identify the inputs that need an autocomplete behavior is with, guess what,
a data dash attribute, data-otf-autocomplete.
And the value for this attribute will be the URL that autocomplete needs to talk to.
So again, I'm using the URL helper to generate a URL that will point
to the HomeController's autocomplete action with this
and that value will be embedded in the data dash attribute.
That's the only change I need to make in the view, everything else will be JavaScript.
What I need to do using jQuery is go out and find those inputs
that have that data dash attribute.
So again, I'll use a selector here.
Find me all the inputs that have data-otf-autocomplete.
And for each one, call this function createAutocomplete.
In this case, we're not really wiring up an event like we did with the form
where we wired up the submitted end.
In this case, we need to go up to each object and give it the autocomplete widget.
So createAutocomplete will be a function that we need to write.
And when jQuery invokes this function, it will pass along the input as the this parameter.
So for each input that it finds with that data dash attribute, it will invoke this function,
pass along that single input as the this reference.
This code is just wrapping that input in jQuery using the dollar sign function
so I can use the jQuery API against it.
And very similar to last time, I'll also create an options object.
Now, there's all sorts of options that you can specify for the autocomplete.
You can tell it the minimum number of characters that the user has
to type before it will send a request to the server.
You can tell it how many milliseconds it has to wait
until after the user has stopped typing before it sends off that request.
But the one option that you must specify is the source option
that tells the autocomplete widget where to get the data.
So in this case, we'll just take the URL that was embedded in that data dash attribute.
We'll pull it out using the attribute method of jQuery and put it
in the source property on the options object.
And then, all I need to do to wire up autocomplete is to walk up to the input,
invoke the autocomplete method and pass in that options object.
This is how a lot of jQuery plug-ins work.
They extend jQuery by adding additional methods
on the jQuery objects so you can just invoke them.
jQuery UI adds methods to jQuery like autocomplete and dialog and button and tabs
and accordion, all sorts of user interface type things.
And at this point, I think I have everything correct where if I run the application,
I should be able to see autocomplete work.
So let's type in the letter S and there we can see the two restaurants
that start with S. So this looks promising.
Let's type in the number 11.
There, I can see all sorts of restaurants that start with 11.
And after I select one from the list, if I click Search, then it appears.
So what I need to do is first type something, select it, it'll be placed into the input box
for me by jQuery autocomplete and then I need to do a Search.
So a lot of people look at that and say can't make it so that one someone selects one
of these items, it just automatically submits that search
for them so that the results are updated.
And the answer is of course we can.
Over here in the options that we passed to autocomplete, when it creates itself,
we can pass in an additional option which is the function to invoke when the select even occurs.
So when the user selects something, please call a function called submit autocomplete form.
That is another function that we'll have to write.
And once again, the this reference will be set up to point
to the DOM element that we're interacting with.
In this case, it's the input again.
And I'll wrap that DOM element with jQuery so that we can do some interesting things with it.
For instance, one of the things that we'll have to do is set its value
because even though jQuery autocomplete will automatically populate the input with the item
that the user has selected, sometimes
that doesn't happen before this select event is raised.
So you can get into submit autocomplete form and still have an old input value there,
not the new one that the user selected.
We'll circumvent that problem just by setting the input value ourselves.
So this is the jQuery API to set the value of an input.
We're going to set it to you ui.item.label.
UI is a parameter that autocomplete passes in.
This is something also that you'll find in the documentation.
That UI object will have all sorts o interesting information about the state of autocomplete
and the parameters of autocomplete including the label of the item that the user clicked on.
So once the input is set, we just need to submit the form.
But we have to find the form first.
Fortunately, that's pretty easy with jQuery too.
What I can do is say, dear input, go and look through the parents above you,
all the DOM elements above you, and find a form.
In fact, find the first form.
That's just in case you're inside of a form that's inside of a form.
That would seem a little bit weird, but we'll just take the first form that you find
as you look up through your ancestors.
And once I find the form, there's a jQuery API where I can tell the form to submit itself.
That will raise the submit event and that will ultimately come back
into our AJAX form submit function that we wrote earlier.
And now, if I save this script, the only change I made was in script, so I should just be able
to save the file, refresh the browser and see this new behavior.
Let's try looking for 11 and selecting something.
And there, I can see the form was automatically submitted for me.
Try it again with the letter S. That seems to work too, and 11 too, all this seem to work.
And the one thing that still bothers me is that it's hard to tell
when the bottom half of the screen is updated.
This is automatically updating for me now.
I almost don't notice it.
It would be nice if I could draw the user's attention
to the bottom half of the screen somehow.
This is another place where jQuery UI can help.
It includes a number of effects that you can apply to DOM elements.
Effects that make things pulsate or bounce or grow or shrink.
They're very easy to use.
Let me show you an example.
Up here, when we take some HTML back from the server and we replace what's in the page
for the restaurant list with that new data, we can make it highlight itself.
I'll place some code in here that will take the HTML that's coming from the server and wrap it
in jQuery so we can manipulate it with the jQuery UI.
And then, after we have replaced the restaurant list with this new HTML,
I'll call the jQuery UI Effect method and tell it to run the highlight effect.
This is where you can pass the parameter to tell it if it should explode or pulsate or highlight.
We'll choose highlight.
Just, again, save the script.
Let's refresh the page to get that new script in the browser.
And then I'll search for 11.
And there you can see, it's just a very brief flash.
Hopefully, you can see it in the video.
But it should be just enough to draw my attention to that area and reassure me that,
yes, the results here actually have changed for me automatically.
( Pause )