Finally, there's one more feature I'd like to add.
I'd like the ability to pageList lists of restaurants.
The last search we did was to search for restaurants that start with a 20.
And I can see 20 and 201, but it only goes to 208
and there is a restaurant 209 but I cannot see it here.
There's no indication that there's more results.
That's because we only take the first ten records from the database that we get.
So let's have paging.
To do the paging, I'm going to rely on a third party component and one of the best ways
to install a third party component is by right clicking on the References folder
and selecting Manage NuGet Packages.
NuGet is a package manager for .NET.
You can download software packages which might be JavaScript libraries or .NET assemblies
or something that has both of those and more.
Now, you don't have to find the project and download the zip
and extract the files and add them to your project.
All you need to do is come to that References and open up the NuGet Package manager.
From here, I can see a list of all the packages that are installed in my application.
That includes things like the EntityFramework and jQuery UI.
I can also go online and I want to search for paged list.
I'll search from the text box up here in the top right of the screen
and that will find me PagedList.Mvc and PagedList.
Two great projects by a fellow named Troy Goode.
I'm going to tell NuGet to install PagedList.Mvc.
NuGet understands package dependencies too and it can see that this package depends
on PagedList, so it downloads them both and adds them to my project.
I can click Close and come in to the assembly references and see PagedList and PagedList.Mvc.
Now, I can start making changes to the application.
We'll start with the HomeController.
The index action of the HomeController will no longer be able to just return just ten records.
Instead, we need to return the proper page of records.
And what the PagedList package will give me is, first of all, an extension method that I can use
in the query to get the proper page of results and also some HTML helpers that I can use
in a view to display a pager widget, something with more and next links and page numbers in it
that a user can click on to navigate around through a large result.
The first thing we need to use though is the Extension method in a query.
So let me add a using statement for PagedList.
And now, I can come down to the index action and instead of having that take operator in there,
we will end this query using a call ToPagedList.
ToPagedList, I need to pass it the page number that I want.
Where do I get that from?
We'll take it as a parameter, because when the user interacts with the pager that we're going
to produce, we'll make sure there's something in the request called page.
It might not always be there though, so we'll have a default of 1.
That way, if you come to this page and you don't specify what page number you want,
you get the first page of results.
And so, ToPagedList will get whatever page has been passed in.
And also, we need to specify the page size.
Let's just say ten restaurants per page is good.
And these are all the changes that we need to make to the controller.
Everything else is going to be in the UI.
The first change we'll make in the UI is to tell it about the new model type
because this is now a model that is of type IPagedList.
That's going to allow me to use the pager helpers to build a paging control.
Let's come in to the index action and instead of being a model that is IEnumerable
of RestaurantListViewModel, it's now going to be a model of IPagedLisr of Restaurant View Model.
Right now, I have a red squiggly here because razor doesn't understand what an IPagedLIst is.
I could add a using statement in here to tell it what namespace that is in,
or I can just add that as a default namespace for my entire application.
In fact, I could add OdeToFood.Models also as a default namespace.
This just cleans up the code and makes it a little easier to work with.
So the way that you do this is by opening up the Web.config file that is in the Views folder.
Not the Web.config file that is in the root of the application, but the Web.config file that's
in the Views folder because it is this web config that controls the razor configuration.
This is the list of default namespaces that razor uses.
I want to add three additional namespaces, PagedList,
PagedList.Mvc, and also my OdeToFood.Models.
Now, quite often, when you change this section of Web.config, Visual Studio
and that razor parser, they do not pickup the changes here until you restart Visual Studio.
And because this always happens to me, I'm just going to go ahead and I've maid these changes
and save everything and close Visual Studio.
We will reopen it right away.
And hopefully, all the red squigglies are gone from Index.cshtml.
And they are, so we're in good shape.
Now, from the Index view, we're also rendering a partial view with the same model.
I need to come into this partial view and also change the model directive there to let me open
up _restaurants and we'll change this from in IEnumerable to also be an IPagedList.
And now, we can get rid of the OdeToFood.Models namespace qualifier too.
It is inside of here, in fact, inside of our restaurant list too and I will place a pager,
a call to Html.PagedListPager that's provided by PagedList.Mvc.
This will build the pager for me.
All I need to do is give it the model.
It will figure out how many total things are in there and also a lambda expression
that given a page will be able to return a URL to go to that page.
The PagedListPager will pass me the page.
I'll use Url.Action to generate the URL
to the HomeController Index action passing page along in the request.
And we know now, that will get into the action and into that to PagedList call.
There's all sorts of options that you can specify for the PagedList pager.
I'm going to select MinimalWithItemCountText.
That will just give me previous and next links and the total number of items that are
in my model that you can play around with here with the different options.
You can have individual page numbers.
You can do all sorts of crazy things with the PagedList pager
and make it work the way you want it to work.
But this should be enough that if I run the application, we should have a pager
on the screen now that tells me how many restaurants are in the database.
And indeed, there's the pager with the next link and it tells me I'm seeing ten restaurants
out a possible 1,003, that's the rate number.
So this seems to be working.
And I can click on Next to go to the next list of results.
So this is all very good, but there are two problems.
One is that the pager, it's not aesthetically pleasing at the moment.
That's an easy fix.
And also, you'll notice that we're redrawing the entire page when I click on the Next link.
We're going off and just redrawing the whole page.
I'd like that to be able to redraw just this portion of the page just like we do
when we do a search on this page.
So let's fix the easy one first and that is to improve the user interface here.
One of the files that the PagedList package will install
into my application is a PagedList.css file.
So a style sheet to make that pager look a little bit better.
I just need to make sure those styles are included with my styles, or put them in a bundle
to download with my style sheet bundles and that's the path I'll take.
This is the bundle that includes my site.css.
I'll also just include PagedList.css along with that.
And just doing a build and refreshing the application,
we should see a better implementation of the pager.
And indeed, that has helped quite a bit.
Now, I have the Previous and Next links, and those still work.
Now, let's try to make this asynchronous which will be a little bit more challenging.
What I need to do, just like how previously we intercepted this form submission,
when I click on this, we catch that event and send off the request ourselves
and redraw the screen, now, I have to intercept click events on these anchor tags that are here.
Intercept those requests, go off and get the page data myself and redraw the screen.
To intercept those requests, of course, we'll still be using jQuery.
So let's go back to our script file, but we'll do this a little bit differently.
What I'm going to do is not go out and look for those anchor tags and wear out Dot Click event.
That would be easy enough to do with jQuery.
I'm not going to do that because we destroy those anchor tags every time we repaint
the screen.
We go off and get a fresh batch of HTML and then we put that HTML in the page
and destroy the anchor tags that were there and replace them with new ones.
I'd have to rewire the event every time we redrew the screen like that.
Instead, what I'm going to do is walk up to something called main-content.
main-content is in the Layout view.
You can see it right here.
A section with a class of main-content.
I'm going to wire up a click even on this section because it contains all
of the HTML that our view renders.
And this section isn't destroyed.
It's always going to be on the page.
So this syntax is saying go out and find the element or elements with the class
of main-content and wire up the Click even.
This is using the On method with jQuery.
What this allows you to do is wire up an event on a DOM element that's higher up in the tree
and then specify how to filter those events.
This is saying, yes, I want click events, but I only want click events that originated
from an anchor tag that was inside of an element with a class of pagedList.
This way, I don't pickup just any anchor tag that might be on the page.
I'm picking up just the anchor tags that are inside of this div with a class of pagedList.
Now, we're intercepting those events.
We can call a method called getPage.
getPage is a function that we'll write.
And inside of getPage, this reference will point to the anchor tag that the user clicked on.
We'll get a reference to that and wrap it with jQuery
so that we can extract some values from it.
We will extract values like the Href attribute that's on that anchor tag
where it's pointing to, because that contains the information that we need to use
to get to the correct page number.
It will be something like /home/index query string page equals 5.
That's the Href value that we need.
We'll take that value.
Put it into a URL property on this options object.
Just like we did earlier with a form, we're going to build an options object
that tells jQuery how to contact the server.
This is the URL we want to go to.
This is the type of request that we want to make and get request.
And the rest of the code would look like this.
Given that options object that we just built, go out and do $.ajax
and make a request to get request to that URL.
And when it's done and you have the new data, call this function.
We'll go out and find the target, the thing that we need to update which will be restaurant list,
but I'm trying to rate this code in a generic fashion so it could be used anywhere
with any page list in the application.
All you need to specify after the user has clicked on one of the pager links,
what DOM element that you want to update.
I put that here in a data dash attribute inside of the div with a class of pagedList.
So we're just looking for this value to extract restaurant list.
And once we have extracted restaurant list, we'll go out and select that element with jQuery
and replace it with the fresh data from the server.
Let's cross our fingers and run the application and see if we can get this to work.
I'll scroll down a bit.
That's always a good test to see if you're doing a partial page refresh,
or refreshing the whole screen.
And it looks like this is not working.
I'm able to go to every page just by clicking Next,
and we're not refreshing the entire screen.
Does it work with the search?
Let's search for 20 again.
And there's my 20 results.
If I go to Next, that seems to be broken and that's because when we go off
to fetch the next page of result in here, we're not taking into account the search term
that user has entered on the page.
All we're passing along is the page number that we got out of the Href for the anchor tag.
But this is actually a very easy problem to solve.
What I can do inside of our AjaxOptions is say please add some additional data to this request.
Essentially, go out and get the form that's on this page and serialize it
and send those values along in the request too.
And now, if I save the script, and let's do a hard refresh in Internet Explore.
Now, let me search for 20 and page through the results,
and there's only two pages of results and that looks good.
Now, I may have a list of restaurants on the homepage that can search through
and page through, and it all happens asynchronously
to provide a nice slick user interface.
( Pause )