Thus far in the application we've been accessing the data base and using different queries
to show and search for restaurants on the home page of the application.
I think the next step would be to add the ability to create update,
edit and delete restaurants but I don't think we want this functionality on the home page,
so let's create a new section of the application to do this.
We need a restaurant area that will let us manage restaurants and what I'll do is come
into the layout view of the application
and let's replace the link that's currently pointing towards reviews and instead is going
to say Restaurant is going to go to the index action of the restaurant controller
which means we need a restaurant controller, we don't have a restaurant controller as yet.
So I'm going to right click the controllers folder,
say add a new controller this will be the RestaurantController and I'm going
to select a new template, I'm going to select the template MVC controller
with read/write actions and views using Entity Framework.
Essentially, the visual studio can create your controller and all the views that you need
if you tell-- first of all the model class which in this case will be restaurant,
I can just type the first few words to this and find it in the drop down list
and the data context class which in our case is going to be OdeToFoodDb
and now I'll let visual studio work its magic by just clicking ad and it will go
out it will create that controller, populate all the actions with all the necessary code
to save things and query things from the data base,
also give me all of the views that I need in my views folder.
And when it's done it will open up all these new files in the editor.
So now I can see that I have a restaurant controller.
Let's build the application and try it out.
The build was successful now if I refresh the home page we should have a restaurant link
and if I click that I'll go to the restaurant controller.
And there we can still see all of our restaurants now we're back
in the pre-generated view that shows the restaurants in a table but I should now be able
to read a new restaurant just by typing in a name and I'll give this restaurant a City
and click create, and we now have a new restaurant in the data base.
Let's see if we can edit this because it's actually Yellow Brick Bank Restaurant
and that seems to work.
Can we delete the restaurant?
Yes we can delete the restaurant too.
This was all thanks to the scaffolding that I selected when I created this controller,
it gave me a controller that instantiated an OdeToFoodDb, give me an index action
that will show all the restaurants.
If we go down here to the bottom it also provided the dispose method
to make sure things were cleaned up.
And in between were a number of actions like delete and edit that will save
and create and delete restaurants.
The idea again behind scaffolding is that it gives you a good starting point.
You cannot necessarily write an entire application just by scaffolding everything out.
There's very few applications that are that simple but it does give you a code base
to start working with and shows you some of the basic MVC patterns that we usually follow.
You can certainly go in and change the controller code, you can go in
and change the view code but I'm not going to drill into each of these methods just now
because what's ultimately going to happen is we're going to impellent many
of the same methods in another controller, the reviews controller
so that we can create and edit reviews.
But I will take a minute just to walk you
through one controller action the details action.
The details action is what is invoked when I click on the details link,
it just shows all the details oft the restaurant, not the prettiest UI
so certainly it's something that you'll look at changing but the way the controller works is
to accept an incoming ID parameter that's the restaurant that we have to look up
and then using the restaurants DbSet
on my OdeToFoodDb it will invoke the find method passing in that ID.
Find is one of those convenient methods that the Entity Framework provides when it's EPI,
it's basically saying I'll go out and find something by it's primary key value all you have
to do is give me the primary key value, if it does find that object,
great, and return to a restaurant.
No link queries or link operators or lambda expressions here required.
If it doesn't find that restaurant it will return null,
so one of the things we could do here is check for null, if we didn't find the null
or return HttpNotFound which is another method that will produce a result,
that essentially return to 404 to the browser.
If we were to come in to this application in look for slash restaurant slash 22
where there shouldn't be a restaurant with a 22 in here, so we get the 404 error message
which may or may not be what you want.
If it is uncommon that a user should click a link
for a restaurant it doesn't exist anymore then you might just go ahead and return a 404
but for some reason there's a lot of links out there and you delete a lot of restaurants,
you might consider returning some sort of custom view.
So I could write a view called NotFound.chhtml put into the reviews folder
and basically put a little message there that says, "Sorry, we couldn't find that restaurant"
and maybe provide a link that you can click on to go back and search for other restaurants,
but for now just for turning a NotFound the area is fine, if we do find the restaurant
and of course we'll pass that into the view and it will display
as much restaurant information as possible.
But one thing the details are missing is a list of any reviews that the restaurant might have.
That would be easy enough to add to this details view, I could certainly come down here somewhere
and have a for each statement and look through Model.Reviews and print out some information
about each review or list how many reviews it has or its average rating.
But I thought we could do something that would be a little bit of the beat and path.
I'd like to be able to click on a link here that says reviews and go to the reviews
for the restaurant and then have the ability to add reviews to that restaurant
or edit the existing reviews for that restaurant.
This will be a little bit off the beat and path because the built in scaffolding cannot create
that for me, it can be close but what we'll do is write most of it from scratch
so that we can actually see how some
of these data modification actions need to be implemented.
And along the way we'll be talking about model binding, model validation and learn some more
about how to work with the MVC framework.