Let's implement a listing of reviews for each restaurant.
Since we're going to not use this details view anymore I'm going to delete
that from my views folder and I'll also delete the details action for my restaurant controller.
And since we don't have a details action I need
to change the index view that's displaying all the restaurant to not have a link to details,
instead we will say here's where you can go to see the reviews for this restaurant
and that will go to the index action on the reviews controller.
And now there's a little set of bug here in the way that I've invoked to action link
because I've picked the wrong overload.
I expect that ID equals item.ID will go as the route values parameter.
Because it did before I just added one more thing here, the name of the controller to call,
why wouldn't it go to route values.
And just because of the way that the action link overloads
or design you'll notice I'm not passing this as route values,
I'm passing this as htmlAttributes.
And the string reviews is being passed as route values and I see this happen all the time I want
to be able to show you how to spot this particular bug.
If I save this view and refresh the browser and I hover over one of the reviews links that's
about to appear I'll see in the little chrome pop window that previous the url
that I do not have an ID in the url, instead I have restaurant query string length equal seven.
Anytime you see length equal seven you probably picked the wrong over load
of action link unless you really did mean to pass length in the query string.
The only thing I need to do to fix this is to pass an additional parameter
so that reviews becomes the controller name, ID equals item.ID goes to route values
and this last parameter goes to htmlAttributes.
htmlAttributes by the way, that's a way to add additional attributes
to that anchor tag that is being produced.
So if you wanted to give that anchor tag a special class
or title attribute you could specify another anonymously typed object here something
like new title equals foo and that will be emitted into the html.
The passing null here will suffice if I don't want to set any htmlAttributes
that should also fix the link if I come back out here and refresh the view.
Now, I can see that this looks like what I need, slash review slash index slash one or slash two,
so the ID is now in the url, very good.
But if I click that link we'll have an exception because we comment it
out our reviews controller in an earlier module.
What I want to do now is select everything with control A uncomment with control KU
and delete code that we don't need anymore, for instance we don't need this in memory data.
Really, the only thing we need is we'll just start back with the index view that's right here
at the very top of the controller.
And in fact we don't need this best review anymore.
We deleted that from the layout action in the previous module.
What we do need is a data source.
So let me go ahead and add an OdeToFoodDb private variable and instantiate
up here when the controller is created.
Now, we'll also go ahead and override dispose.
You can just type override, have this lists pop up.
Pick the method that you want to override and then type code into it.
This looks good.
And now, what we'll do is change the index action around.
So, the index action will receive an Id parameter.
And what can be a little bit confusing here is
that this Id parameter is not the Id for overview.
Typically, when you're working with an Id inside of the controller it's an Id for the entity
that that controller is centered around.
Instead this is an ID that represents a restaurant Id.
That's a little bit confusing.
I could in the index view say instead
of Id equals item.Id I could say restaurant Id equals item.Id
and pass restaurant Id along in the query string.
Remember the routing engine doesn't know anything about restaurant Id in the URL
so we'd have to go in the query string.
I could add a new route if I wanted a restaurant Id to appear in the URL.
But I want to show you another option.
I'm just trying to change the name of this from Id to restaurant Id and instead
of changing the routes or changing where this parameter is passed,
I'm putting it into the query string, I'm just going to alias.
I can do that with the bind attribute.
But bind allows you to do is tell the MVC Model Binder that when it goes to look
for the restaurant Id parameter value look for something called Id
which is not very obvious syntax I know,
but that's essentially what this attribute is going to do.
When it looks for restaurant Id it will look for with the name of Id.
And now I can paste on some code that will go out and find
that restaurant by its restaurant Id.
If it's not equal to null we will render a view with that restaurant.
Otherwise we'll return a four for error.
And at this point we don't have any views for the reviews controller.
So, we're going to need to add a view.
I'll add an index view.
It's going to use razor.
I wanted to be strongly typed against a restaurant review.
Even though we're passing in a restaurant I'm going to strongly type it to restaurant review
because I want the scaffolding to create as much of the HTML forming as possible.
We're going to need to go in and fix this up because we're actually passing
in a restaurant not a restaurant review.
But that's okay.
This is going to help me.
When I click add I'm going to do a couple things.
First of all let me copy this model directive because it's going to come in useful here just
in a minute and change the model to say, no, you don't need a restaurant review.
What you'll be receiving is a restaurant.
And that means I could change this H2 tag to say something like reviews for at Model.Name
and that will give me the restaurant name.
And now let me take that model directive actually and paste it right here
and take all the rest of those code out because this code
that the scaffolding generated is here towards iterating
through a collection of reviews and writing them out.
But the model for this view is a restaurant.
What I want to do is create a partial view that will take care of rendering this table for me
and the model for that partial view will be an IEnumerable of restaurant review.
Inside of the reviews folder I'll create a new partial view.
Let's call it Reviews.
Using a Razor I strongly type to restaurant review
and we'll create it as a partial view of course.
I'll click Add.
Actually, delete the model directive that's here and paste this in.
This gives me everything that I need.
Our model is going to be IEnumerable of restaurant review.
I wanted to create a table of these reviews.
I don't necessarily want it to display the restaurant Id because that's meaningless
to an end user so let's delete that column.
I'll also delete that down here where it's displaying the value
and I think we'll just go with an edit link.
So, delete the details and the delete link and save everything.
Let me do a build and see if this works.
Oh, it won't work yet because back in the index view we need to render that partial.
I'll do that ahead of the create link.
So, html.partial, please render the reviews view for me and pass in Model.Reviews.
I'll take the reviews that are associated with this restaurant and pass it in to
that partial view as the strongly type model.
It will take care or rendering the table for me.
And now, let me do another build just to make sure everything is out there.
And let's refresh this page.
And let me go to the reviews for this first restaurant that I know there is a review
in there because we see that the database with a review.
But when I click that link I'll get a very strange air.
This is something that you could spend a long time debugging
if you don't know what's going on.
Because the error is a little bit misleading it's telling you that you passed
in a restaurant to this partial view.
But the partial view needs an IEnumerable of Restaurant Review.
And then you'll go back and look at your code, and you'll say,
but I'm not passing a restaurant to this partial view.
I'm passing in at Model.Reviews which should be a collection of restaurant review.
What is debug?
What's broken about the runtime here?
But the problem is not that you're passing the wrong thing.
The problem is that these reviews property is going to be null by default.
And this is something that you run into with the entity framework.
There's several different ways to solve this problem.
So, just to make it clear let me open up the Restaurant class and tell you
that in the controller when we do Restaurants.Find
in passing an Id what the entity framework will do is happily load
up these properties, Id, Name, City and Country.
It won't touch reviews because that's information that's in a different table.
There's a one to many relationship between restaurant and reviews.
And the entity framework just doesn't load up this associated child collections automatically.
At least not in this scenario the way I have things to find here.
There's at least six different ways to solve this problem.
I'll show you the easiest one which is just to add the virtual keyword here.
Now, what the entity framework will do when you spell virtual correctly is that it will
at runtime create a little wrapper for this restaurant class
and intercept recalls to the reviews property.
So that when you go to get to the reviews
for a restaurant it will make sure that it loads them up for you.
And that requires a second query to the database.
In other words Db.Restaurants.Find will just pull in the restaurant information.
Later in the view when we say Model.Reviews behind the scenes the entity framework will
issue a second query to pull in those reviews.
And you might say, but that's data access from a view
and I'll say that's fine because it's implicit.
I'm not writing explicit code data access code to load something.
It's just happening behind the scenes for me.
But some people will worry that there are two queries instead
of one to get all this information.
And for now, I'll just point you to some documentation that if you read
through it will explain how to eagerly load related information at the time you do a query.
I can get you down to just a single query to pull in a restaurant and a bunch of reviews.
As I said there's a number of different ways to solve this.
But just having the virtual keyword there is one of the easiest solutions
if you're not too worried about performance.
So, with the virtual keyword in place on a Restaurant Reviews, now I've done a build.
Let me go in and refresh this.
And this area should go away.
So a very non intuitive error what is going now because we have some reviews here
and it should also work when there are on reviews
because behind the scenes the entity framework is making sure it gives you some collection even
if it's an empty collection.
Now, again, our display isn't the prettiest display in the world.
It would be nice not to have ReviewerName, all this one word.
We'll come back and fix that later when we start looking
at some annotations that you can add to a model.
For right now I want to focus on creating a new review.