Let's turn our attention to creating a review.
When I click on this Created New link to create a review I'm going to need
to know the restaurant to associate the review with.
So, in the index action I will add a parameter here
that will tell the routing engine, please pass along.
A parameter called RestaurantId set it to the Restaurants Id property.
And I didn't pick the correct overload of action link here.
I can see that's going into route values.
So the routing engine will say, restaurant Id, I don't see that in the URL.
So, I'll place it in the query string.
This then should give us the proper link.
Now, what I need in the reviews controller is an action
that will respond to a Get request for create.
This is a very simple action.
It just needs to return a view that contains everything the user needs
to type in to create a review.
An early response to a get request and even though the restaurant Id will be
in the query string and I can take it
as a parameter here I don't actually use it in this create action.
But I'm going to leave the parameter there just so we know that it's available
in the query string and in the future if we create perhaps some sort of view model
that will provide some defaults for some of the RestaurantReview fields.
We can always populate it with that restaurant ID.
But really, this is all we need in the Create Action for this simple scenario.
I do need to create view so I will add a view called Create using Razor,
strongly typed against the RestaurantReview
and this time I will select the Create Scaffold template and we'll get a view
that is strongly typed to RestaurantReview.
It's using the BeginForm helper that will post back this form when the user clicks Save.
It'll post back to the same URL it came from.
So if we are on /Reviews/Create?restaurantId=3, we'll post back to that same location.
We'll still have a restaurant ID in the query string
and here's a little trick about BeginForm.
What Html.BeginForm will do is return an object that implements iDisposable and that means
that we can use it with a C# using statement.
Typically, iDisposable objects are objects that hold on to precious resources
like database connections and you want to dispose them, and an easy way to do that is
to wrap something that's iDisposable with a using statement and create a code block.
At the bottom of the code block, the C# compiler will emit the proper code
to automatically call Dispose on that object.
In this case, BeginForm isn't really hanging on to any precious connections
but when you call Dispose on that object, that's when it will emit the closing form tag.
So that's just some information on how BeginForm works
and why we're placing it inside of a using statement.
Inside of the form, we'll have some validation messages.
We'll see those in this module.
We also have some literal text that we could make a little bit prettier instead
of RestaurantReview all one word, I could give this a legend of New Review.
Then we have labels and editors for everything the user needs to fill in, the rating, the body,
the Reviewer Name and oops, here's restaurant ID.
So sometimes the scaffolding is a little eager and emits things
that you don't necessarily want these or to edit.
We're going to delete that.
Sometimes it is not so eager and it doesn't emit things that you want it to,
but in this case we just had to delete something.
That should be enough so that if I do a build and make sure everything is saved,
if I refresh this page, to get the new Create New link that has a restaurant ID in it.
I should be able to click this and here we're on a page where I can enter a rating,
I can enter a body, and I could enter a Reviewer Name and click Create.
That'll do a post back.
So we need a controller action on the Reviews controller
that will respond to that post request.
That action will look like this.
We respond to a post request and we take a RestaurantReview as a parameter.
That's where the model binder in MVC will jump in and say, "Oh, you need a RestaurantReview."
I'll instantiate an instance of that type and then look through all the properties to see
if I can match them up with something in the request and it will find a rating,
it will find a body, it will push those values into it.
It will also find the restaurant ID so it will populate the restaurant ID property of a Review.
So it's associated with the proper restaurant and then inside of that Create Action,
the first thing you typically do is check to see if ModelState is valid
and if this flag is valid, returns false,
that means something went wrong with the model binding.
Something that was required isn't there.
Something is too long or something was too short.
It runs through all the validation rules associated with an entity
and tells you if everything worked or not.
We'll add some additional validation rules in this module but for now,
just know that if that returns false, what we want to do is not save the thing
in the database, something was invalid, instead, we'll return the Create View again
and let the user try to fix any problems that might have occurred.
Those Html.validation message for helpers will show validation messages to the user.
We'll see that here in just a second.
But if ModelState is valid, that means everything was proper.
So we will tell the Entity Framework to please add this review to its reviews collection
and then the Entity Framework doesn't actually save anything
to the database until you call SaveChanges.
At that point, it will issue Insert or Update or Delete Statements or all three,
depending on how many objects you changed to reconcile the changes that you made
in memory with what's in the database.
In this case, it should just issue a single Insert statement to insert a new review
into the Reviews Table and if that works, we will redirect the user back to the index action.
We don't want to let them sit there on the Create View that was the result of a post
because they might hit Refresh and create another review accidentally
or redirect them back to another page where they can see that review.
And now I should have everything that I need if I do a Build where I can come to this page
and click Create and there I can see my new review in the list.
Let's try it with a different restaurant.
Let's see if we can add a review for a restaurant that doesn't have any reviews yet.
And that seems to work.
And now before we start talking about validation and how to add additional validation rules,
let's finish off the edit scenario.