For editing a review, we already have a link specified here that will take us
to an edit action and pass along the ID of the review to edit.
All we need to do to respond politely to that request is
to implement an Edit Action that responds to an HttpGet.
All we need to do here is take that ID parameter, lookup a review using
that primary key and then return a view that will allow the user to edit that.
We need the view so I will right click and add a view called Edit using Razor,
strongly type to a RestaurantReview.
This time the Scaffold template will be Edit.
This is going to look very similar to the Create View.
It still has a BeginForm.
It still has validation summaries.
It still has a legend that we don't quite like so we can say Edit Review.
It does have something a little bit different here.
It has a hidden input for the model.
That hidden input will allow us to track the ID of the review that's being edited
and it's hidden because the user doesn't need to see it.
We just need to preserve that piece of state between the requests,
and then we have the labels and the editors for Rating, Body, Reviewer Name
and ah, here again is restaurant ID.
This time I'm going to delete it again but we also need to keep track of this restaurant ID
because when we update this review, we're going to need
to properly populate the restaurant ID field.
What I can do is just add another Html.HiddenFor that says given a model called Model,
please give me a hidden input for restaurant ID.
There are some other approaches that we could use for this but this makes it easy
and now when the user clicks on the Submit button,
we will have to respond to that post request.
So back in the Reviews Controller, I'll implement an edit action that responds
to a post that's very similar to create but it has one little difference.
It's still going to take a RestaurantReview.
The MVC model binder is still going to populate that object
with things that it finds in the request.
So again, we don't have to look in the query strings or post of form values ourselves.
The model binder will take care of all that for us.
We'll still check if ModelState is valid.
Return to Edit View if ModelState is not valid because that will allow the user
to fix any problems that they have but if it is valid, we're going to come in
and use a slightly different API and I do need to bring in a namespace here,
System.Data, for this to be legal C# code.
But now that it's legal, I can tell you about this entry API on the db context.
The entry API is a way to tell the Entity Framework, "Here is a review that I want you
to start tracking so you can make changes in the database
for this review but it's not a new review.
I don't want it inserted into the database.
Instead, this is a review that's already in the database.
I just want you to take ownership of this object and treat it as if it had some new data inside."
That's the purpose of EntityState.Modified.
Now, when I call SavesChanges, you will update that record
in the database, the record that has the same ID.
In the Create Action, we add a review and EF will insert the record.
In the Edit Action, we attach an existing review with that entry, set the state to modified
and EF will update the record, and once that is successful, again, we'll redirect the user back
to the index action where they should be able to see the effect of their edit.
So after a build, let me come in and edit this review and because I'm really excited
about this restaurant, I will add extra exclamation points and click Save
and I can see that the edit worked.
And we're not going to go into validation just yet.
Before we do that, I want to tell you about some serious security implications of model binding,
some things that you need to know about.