You do need to be careful with model binding in MVC.
The model binder has a brute force algorithm that will try to move anything and everything
into your model that it can possibly move.
This means you might values you didn't expect in a model which can lead
to security related problems you might not have thought about.
Let's pretend that once a review is created, no one should be allowed
to edit the Reviewer Name of a review.
If you didn't watch this video, you would think that would be very easy.
All I need to do is take Reviewer Name out of my form.
If there's no more editor for Reviewer Name and I don't see it on the form,
how can I possibly change the Reviewer Name?
Well unfortunately, there's all sorts of tools out there that you can use to modify data
in a request or just create a request with arbitrary data and send it off to a server.
People use these tools all the time to break into servers
and send people information they didn't expect.
In fact, we don't really need a fancy tool here, all I need to do to get something
into reviewer name is to add a parameter to the query string.
I'll add reviewer name equals hack.
We usually get request for this form and now has that value in the query string and I don't need
to save anything here, all I want to do is get that reviewer name in there.
If I click save, we now have a new reviewer name.
And the problem here is that the model binder didn't know about my forum, about my view code,
it didn't know that I didn't want a reviewer name to be edited.
All it knows is that the restaurant review has a reviewer name property
and that the request had a reviewer name value so it moved the value into the property.
This problem is often referred to by one of two names.
Some people call it over posting that is we created more values than you expected
in the request but it also goes by the name mass assignment
because the model binder just assigns all the values it can
without regard to how you wrote your view code.
If someone knows the right syntax, they can move anything into your model.
There's a number of different solutions to this problem.
I'll show you one quick and easy solution probably not the best solution but if you want
to see more alternatives, you can read the post on my blog
where I cover this topic in more detail.
For now, let me show you one quick easy solution which is to use that bind attribute again.
We use this before when we aliased a parameter name.
This time, I'll show you some of the other things that you can pass in the bind,
they include a list of things to exclude and a list of things to include.
You typically pick one or the other.
Exclude is a black list.
I can say please exclude the following fields, reviewer name.
And if I had additional field here, I could just separate them by commas
but that's the one thing I want to be excluded when you do the model binding.
You can also use include and that's a white list,
I just list all the things that you do want to be bound.
But exclude works for me well here because I only need to exclude one thing.
Another common approach to this problem is to define a view model.
This time, an input view model and the view model would only have the properties you expect
to receive from the user, nothing else.
You'll use the view model as the parameter to your action and then you'll need
to copy the values into a real entity to update the database.
But by only having the values you expect from the user in the view model,
you can be sure you don't pick up anything unexpected from one of your shadier customers.
Also, related to security, make sure to watch the security module and learn
about cross site request forgeries.
Cross site request forgeries are a dangerous settle attack you should worry
about when posting form data and we'll look at the attack
and how to avoid a cross site request forgery in the security module later in the course.