Currently, when we edit a review, we could run into a couple problems.
There's nothing that constrains the rating to any sort of scale so if someone wanted
to save a rating of 1000 into the database, we would let them.
There's also nothing that requires them to enter a body or restricts them from entering a body
with 10,000 exclamation points in it.
These are all types of validations that we can do very easily with the MVC framework.
Before we look at them, let me just add a couple of things back into the project.
Let's remove the bind attribute for right now, I actually want people
to be able to edit the reviewer name.
I'll hit control Z in the edit view to bring back the editor for the reviewer name.
And now, let's go over and look at restaurant review and apply some data annotations.
So, one annotation that you can apply is the range annotation.
I can say that this rating has to be between one and ten and now, when we do model binding
in ASP.NET MVC, the model binder after it moves property values into this properties,
it also exercises any validation logic that is applied through this attributes.
So it defines that the rating is 100, it will tell you that the model state is not valid
and then you can let the user try this again.
There's also a required attribute although putting this
on an integer property is a little bit redundant because to the model binder,
an integer property is required by default because integers and C sharp are value types.
That means they cannot be null.
And when the model binder comes across a value type like int or date time, long and decimal,
it automatically requires a value to be present in the request for that.
We can also come in and tell the body-- tell the model binder that the body should be required
and we can also give it a maximum string length, let's say 1,024 characters.
In addition to this attributes, there's also attributes
to apply a regular expression validation, there's attributes to compare two properties
and there's an attribute to do a remote validation.
Actually, call back to the server and check your property value
as the user is typing into a forum.
You can read all about these validation annotations on MSDN and MVC documentation.
So just having this attributes in place and doing a build,
we'll make something different happen in my application
and that something different might not be something that you expect right away
but that something different is this.
The entity framework is always checking the model that is in effect against the model
that you use to create the database including any migrations
that have been put into the database.
And at this point in time, it is detected that there is something different about the model
and if you think about it, some
of these attributes really do influence the database schema.
For instance, saying that Body is required is like saying I need a not null column.
Previously, this was a null column, you can insert null values into it.
Specifying a string length gives this a definite string length.
Previously, it was nvarchar max, now it has a maximum length of 1,024 characters.
If I want it to get pass this error, there's a couple different ways to do it.
There is a way to just tell the entity framework trust me, I know what I'm doing,
just work with me and move ahead.
Or, you can actually apply the migrations to get the database schema and sync with what is
in your C sharp code and that's what we'll do.
Remember, we have automatic migrations enabled so what I am able to do is just come in
and say let's update the database and I'll throw in the Verbose flag.
If I do this, it's going to fail the first time because migrations is smart enough to realize
that we're taking one column, the body column or choose to be nvarchar max
and we're making it smaller that could result in data loss.
But here, I can say basically, I know what I'm doing and I want to force this through and now,
we can see things like alter table RestaurantReviews, alter the column body
to make it nvarchar 1024, not null.
And then we rerun the seed method, that mens all my data should still be in here.
We didn't loose anything.
And now, after I do a build one more time just to be safe,
I should be able to refresh the home page and we'll have a working application again.
So let's go into restaurants and look at one that has reviews
and see if we can edit this review and put the value of 1,000 in for the rating.
No, as soon as I tab off of that, it will give me a message
that the field rating must be between one and ten.
Notice, I didn't even click the Save button and that's because one of the nice things
that the editor for HTML helper will do for you is emit some Metadata into the input tag
that client-side JavaScript can pick up
and exercise the validation logic for you on the client-side.
So before the user even tries to submit these to the server,
we can tell them that they've done something wrong.
Same thing should happen here with Great, if I blank that out and try to click Save this time,
now, it can come back and tell me the body field is required.
That request actually didn't go to the server.
That was triggered on the client side by JavaScript.
Some of these validations require a little more
than just filling something in and tabbing out of the input.
But as soon as I start typing in here again, the validation message goes away.
And as a user, I feel happy and I can also fix the rating here.
And just to be clear, these validations are run on a client side,
they're also run on the server side so even if the user has JavaScript disabled for some reason
and a bad value comes into your server, the model binder will run the same validation rules
after it's done its model binding for this restaurant review.
And if any one of those rules failed, it will set model state is valid equals False.
And then when you re-render the view, things like the validation message four will pick
up those error messages and display them in the view.
In addition to data annotations for validation,
there's also a data annotations that can influence the display.
So if you remember, we had HTML helpers like display for and display name
for that we would use to write out things like the reviewer name here.
And the problem is that reviewer name as all one word isn't very pretty.
That's being written out by LabelFor ReviewerName.
So let me introduce you to just a couple of the display annotations here with the reviewer name.
One of the things we could use here is the display annotation
and one of the parameters we can pass for the display annotation is the name
that should be used when this is shown in the UI.
So I could just say this is perhaps user name as two words.
There's also a display format attribute.
With this attribute, you can specify things like the data format string
that should be applied that's quite useful when you want
to format numbers and dates for display.
For this one, what I could do is say that the NullDisplayText perhaps is anonymous.
We don't know who the user is and it always helps when I spell that correctly.
And now, let me do a build and come back out and refresh this page.
And we can see that Reviewer Name has changed to User Name.
And if I blank out the User Name to get rid of this ugly value that some malicious user put
in my database, I can see that User Name displays as anonymous when it has no value.
When I go into Edit it, I see the real value that's there which is empty,
it's just when we use the display for helper,
it's going to use that null value display text in place of a null string.
Again, there's many more Display attributes they can use, if you just want to poke around inside
of the System.ComponentModel.DataAnnotations name space,
I think you'll find a number of useful attributes in there.