I'm sure you can think of many validation scenarios that are not covered
by the validation attributes provided with the framework.
This is when you can implement custom validation logic.
And there's a couple different approaches you can take
that will plug right into the framework.
One popular approach is to write a custom validation attribute.
Use this approach when you have validation logic that you want to apply to multiple models.
An example might look like this.
I'm going to temporarily paste some code inside of here,
that's not something we're going to keep in the project.
So I'm just going to keep it in the same file as a Restaurant Review
and we'll remove it after I explain what it is.
This is a maxWords attribute.
What I can do with this is restrict the number of words
that a user can enter into a string property.
It does this just by using a simple check and looking at the number of space characters.
So it's not an advanced validation.
I'm just really showing you how to go about implementing this approach.
And before I explain what it does, let me just show you how you could use it.
Let's say that we wanted to restrict Reviewer Name to be a single word.
And I could say, maxWords and you need to pass in a parameter
which is the maximum number of words.
So let's say just a single word for Reviewer Name.
And now, if I do a build and come out into the application,
I'm going to try to edit this User Name and put in Scott Allen
and click Save, User Name has too many words.
But if I go with just Scott, everything is fine.
So my validation attribute is working.
Let me remove it from here and I'll show you what it does.
First you derive from a base class ValidationAttribute.
The MVC runtime and the model binder, they respect ValidationAttibute.
So that automatically plugs you into the framework.
And when you derive from ValidationAttribute, you can override a method is valid.
When the model binders performing validation on your model, it will pass in the value
of the property where you place this attribute.
So here, it would pass in the Reviewer Name when it's validating a Restaurant Review.
And then it's up to me to inspect that value and see if it meets the proper criteria.
We're just doing a String.Split to create an array and it's going to split
up that string wherever it sees a space character then look at the Length
and see if that is created with maxWords.
So again, a very simple brute force validation.
I'm sure you can think of all sorts of edge cases where this would fail
but this is really more just about showing you how to implement custom validation logic.
You could have anything inside of here.
If the model passes validation, you can just return ValidationResult.Success.
But if there is a problem, you want to return a new ValidationResult
and associate an errorMessage with it.
And the error message you can create using another method that you inherit
from the base class FormatErrorMessage, we actually set the error to display string to use
for this attribute and the constructor.
And then back in is valid.
We'll build that string using Display Name.
And that's what ultimately produce the string, User Name has too many words.
It also allows other people to set a custom error message if they want.
You can do this actually on any attribute even the built in attributes.
Anyone of these attributes, I could walk up to them and say, errorMessage equals
and have a custom error message here that will display when the user is outside of that range.
And I could do that for maxWords too just because we're using FormatErrorString
and deriving from a validation attribute base class.
Now, this type of validation only happens on the server-side.
You can implement custom JavaScript code to plug in to the client-side validation framework.
You'll find many examples of this on the web, just remember you don't need
to duplicate all the validation logic on the client.
Some validations are difficult on the client.
If you at least have the required and length attributes and simple text like that,
you can give quick feedback for common errors that's going to help your users out quite a bit.
In addition to this validation attribute approach,
you can also have a model object implement and IValidatable Object Interface.
This is a good approach to use if you want to do a deep inspection of a model
because what I can do with this interface is use control period to tell Visual Studio that I want
to implement this interface and it will give me that validate method.
That's the method that you implement to provide the custom validation logic.
And it's inside of here where you have access to the entire model.
When you write a validation attribute, you only have easy access to a single property,
that's the property value where the attribute I was used and that's the property value
that the model binder will pass in to you.
You can get to other properties on the model but it's a bit messy.
With Validate, I'm inside my model object so it would be really easy for me
to exercise validation logic that looks at multiple properties, for instance,
I could say something like, if Rating is less than two and ReviewerName ToLower,
startsWith Scott and maybe we just have a trouble maker
on the site with the User Name of Scott.
And it gives everyone a bad and low rating.
We just want to prevent him from entering messages.
And what I could do here is use yield return
and create a new ValidationResult with an error message.
And otherwise, if everything succeeds, I don't need to yield return anything here,
that'll essentially produce an empty IEnumerable
and the MVC runtime will know there's no problems.
And now, if I build the application again and we come into edit a review and I have a User Name
of Scott and I tried to put in a Rating of one.
I'll save the error message.
Notice that this error message appears above any properties that's
because we didn't associate this validation error
with a specific property like User Name or Rating.
And in that case, it just gets associated with the model
and it will display in the Validation Summary.
If I open up the Edit view for a Review real quick, that error message is appearing here
in the Validation Summary which by default only shows errors that aren't associated
with a specific field in the model.
That's what the true parameter is telling the Validation Summary to do.
If you change that value over a false value, the Validation Summary will display all errors
on the models for all properties and also the model of all errors.