Hi, this is Scott Allen and this is the first module in the course design
to demonstrate everything you need to build applications with ASP.NET MVC.
This course is primarily aimed at developers who are new to ASP.NET MVC,
but even if you've been working with the framework I hope to show you a few tricks.
We'll be starting at the very beginning in this first module.
I'll first show you how to install all the tools that you need.
We'll be using Visual Studio express 2012 for the web which is a free tool
for building web applications, but you can use other editions
of Visual Studio 2012 if you want to follow along.
By the end of this first module, you'll see how to create and run your first application
and also have an understanding of the design goals of the MVC framework.
So, let's get started.