Now, it's just a few minutes later and the Web Platform Installer has completed.
It didn't require any reboot on this machine which is always nice.
So, we're ready to use Visual Studio for the first time.
But before we do, let's just a take a step back and talk
about the tools we're going to use in this course.
What we've done so far is set up the Web Platform Installer
and you can launch this tool again at any time if you want to install more software.
But we've already installed the three essential tools that we need to move forward.
The first is Visual Studio.
Visual Studio is where we will write task and debug our code.
It includes editors, debuggers and shortcuts for all the technologies that we need
to bring together in a web application.
It can handle C sharp code.
It can also handle JavaScript HTML and CSS.
We've also installed SQL server.
Later in this course, we'll see how to persist
and query data that's stored in a SQL server database.
And finally we've installed IIS Express.
IIS Express is a light weight web server we can use during development
and it doesn't require any special privileges to run.
As a web server, this is the component that will respond to HTTP request that come
in from a web browser and it responds by executing the logic
that we build inside of our MVC application.
We won't interact with IIS Express on a regular basis.
It just pretty much sits behind the scenes and faithfully hosts and executes our application.
The first step in using all these tools is to just launch Visual Studio.