Here inside the Visual Studio you'll have a window with the title Solution Explorer.
It is the Solution Explorer window that allows you to get to all of your files, C sharp files,
JavaScript files, CSS files, icons, images and everything that goes into your application.
When we created this application using the internet project template,
Visual Studio went ahead and populated our application with all
of the folders and files that you see here.
That's why we already have a running application with contact in about links working.
Three of these folders have a special significance, the controllers,
the models and the views folders.
Let's talk about those names for a minute.
The ASP.NET MVC framework derives its name from the model view controller design pattern.
This design pattern has been present in software applications for several decades at this point
and it's a design pattern to follow when you want to separate the responsibilities
of the components in your user interface layer.
The C and MVC is for controller.
A controller is a software component that will be the target for some external stimulus.
In the case of a web application that external stimulus is usually an incoming HTTP request.
So, when someone launches a web browser and points it to the slash home slash
about location of my application.
That incoming request needs to go to a controller that is in my application.
When the controller receives the request, it's responsible for building a model that M in MVC.
It's the model that contains all the information that you need to present to the user
to satisfy that incoming request.
In the case, of slash home slash about, the model might just be some information
about the website or about the company or the people behind the website.
Another example would be a controller for handling request to view recipes.
You might have a recipe controller that builds a list of the most popular recipes.
That list would be the model.
The controller then selects a view to display the model.
Views in the MVC design pattern are very simple objects.
Think of them as templates.
They take pieces of data from the model and they place them into a proper location on the page.
If the model was a list of recipes, then the controller might select a view that will take
that list and display the recipes inside an HTML table.
That end result is that you isolate the behaviors in your UI into one
of these three categories, model, view or controller.
A view would never need to know how to call into the data access layer
because the model already contains all the data it needs.
Meanwhile, a controller would never need to know about where to place an error message
or how to color it because that's the responsibility of the view.
That isolation that you achieve with the MVC pattern makes it easy to maintain
and change your application moving forward because the code inside of each
of these pieces is very focused and easier to understand.
You can make a change in the controller about where to get your list of recipes
or how to calculate what the best recipes are and that shouldn't impact the view
which is only worried about displaying the recipes.
I do want to point out that the MVC design pattern doesn't dictate what type
of data access you use.
You can use web services, relational databases, file system, document databases,
any form of storage behind the scenes.
And it also doesn't dictate what your business objects or domain layer should look like.
In fact, the MVC design pattern doesn't care if your application has layers or not.
It's simply a design pattern for building a user interface and nothing more.
So the MVC framework is designed to help you follow this MVC design pattern
by giving you tools and classes to build models, views and controllers.
The MVC framework also has some additional goals.
One of these goals is to embrace the web and to be able to work very closely
with web technologies like JavaScript, HTML and CSS.
There is no large obstructions here that try to shield you from knowing things
like what HTTP verb is being used to place a request.
We'll learn about those things in this course.
There is also nothing that makes it harder for you to work with the designer
who can help you style and make your site look good using CSS.
Another goal for MVC is to run on top of the core ASP.NET run time.
The ASP.NET run time is been around for over ten years now.
And it's proven itself to be secure and stable and optimized for performance.
If you're already familiar with ASP.NET and you know how to work with HTTP modules and handlers
and caching and diagnostics, then you'll feel right at home in the MVC environment.
A third goal for the framework is to be extensible.
We'll look at many extensibility points as we work through this course.
If you do not like how the MVC framework behaves in some certain area, chances are,
all you need to do is plug in the right component
to make it behave a little bit differently.
And finally the last goal of the MVC framework is to be testable.
We will look at unit testing and tester and development techniques in this course
and we'll see that MVC framework went to a lot of trouble to try and obstruct the ways of some
of the thornier issues in testing user interface-oriented code.
But right now what I want to do is return the Visual Studio and make some
of these concepts a little more concrete.