Let's look at the details of what happens when we click on the about link in our application.
The browser is going to send off a request to slash home slash about
and that request will reach our development web server here on the local host
which is this machine and that request will be received by IIS Express.
IIS Express is running and it's in the background.
You can see it if you go to the system tray area of the task bar.
Sometimes it hides itself here because it's shy.
But if you click on the little arrow, you can see that the icon looks
like stacked blue pizza boxes and I can right click it to see more details
like show me all the applications that you're currently running.
I can see it's running my OdeToFood application and it's running it on port 56470.
That's just a temporary port used for development.
ISS express is going to take that request and deliver it to my MVC application.
Inside of every MVC application, there is a routing engine which takes request and tries
to deliver them to the proper component.
We'll look at the routing API in the next module, but for now you're just going to have
to trust me when I tell you that the request ultimately ends up inside
of a class that's inside of the controllers folder.
In fact, it ends up in a class called home controller because by default a request
for slash home something will come to the home controller and a request for slash home slash
about will end up inside of this about method inside of the home controller.
So you can see there is a naming convention in play here.
Where if you just name things correctly, request will find their way to the proper place
and this isn't the only scenario where naming conventions play a role in MVC.
The about method doesn't have much work to do
and by the way we may call this an action in ASP.NET MVC.
So the public method inside of a controller are actions.
This action doesn't have much work to do.
It's not even really building a model.
But let me put a break point here by clicking out to the left
of the editor window and getting that little red dot.
Now, we can run it with the debugger
and see execution actually pause here when I click on the about link.
The debuggers are a great way to step through your code
and see what it's doing and inspecting variable values.
Let me click on about and you can see we hit this breakpoint.
And now I can press F10 to step through code one line at a time.
I can hover over things to view their values and so forth.
The line of code we're on now is about to return a view.
A view is one type of action result that you can return from an action
that tells the MVC framework what to do next.
Maybe you want to redirect the user or maybe you want to return some data
in a format for JavaScript to consume it.
Returning a view is telling the MVC framework that the next thing you want
to do is render a view, but what view will the MVC framework render?
Well there is also a naming convention in play here too.
The MVC framework is going to look inside of the views folder of this application.
Notice there is a folder called home that matches the controller I'm in,
that home controller without the controller pat of it.
But these are the views for the home controller and if I expand that,
I can see there is a view called about, that matches the action that I'm inside of.
The about action of the home controller and if I open this, what we'll see is the information
that is pretty much what we'll see if I hit F5 to continue and let this view render.
This about view has a dot CSHTML extension that is just the default extension for Razor views.
Notice that that view that appears on the left hand side doesn't include everything
that you see in the browser.
It doesn't include the text, your logo here or the register link or the log
on link or home about and contact.
It really just includes the content that is specific to this about action.
All these other pieces including the copyright at the bottom, those are things that we need
to appear on every page in this application.
So, they have been factored out of the individual views like about dot CSHTML.
We'll see how to build what's known as a lay out view that contain all that common mark up.
For now, what I want to focus on is just how do I deliver additional information
from the controller to this view and then have it displayed on this page.
So, let me stop debugging and come back into the home controller
and we'll make some changes here inside of about.
There is a couple of different ways to get information to the view.
One approach is to use the approach that we see here in the about action and that's simply
to put information inside of the ViewBag.
ViewBag is a dynamically typed object in C sharp.
That means you can add any sort of property to the ViewBag and it will be available inside
of the view to pull out and retrieve and display.
That's currently what's happening with this message property.
So it could also say something like ViewBag.Location equals Maryland
and the United States of America and do a build
and that value will be available inside of ViewBag also.
If I want to display that, I could come into about dot CSHTML
and let's remove what is currently inside of here and come up.
We're already displaying ViewBag.Message inside of an h2 tag so let me just have a div
that says location is at ViewBag.Location.
The amp sign is a way to tell the razor view engine here is a C sharp expression.
I want you to evaluate it and take the result and write it into the response right here
where I'm placing this particular expression.
So by having that in place there and saving the view, I should be able to come back
out to the browser and refresh and see that we now have location mailed in the USA.
So this is one approach that a controller can use to pass along information to a view
but let's look at a different approach,
an approach using what we call a strongly typed model.
Every MVC project will start with a models folder inside.
You can use this folder when you create new models for your application.
Although in reality, models can live anywhere even in a different project
that you reference from this project.
But we use the models folder for now.
All I need to do is right click this.
I want to add a new class.
I'll call this the about model.
And we'll keep things very simple.
This is a class, I'm just going to give it two properties.
I'll add them using a code snippet in Visual Studio so I can just type P-R-O-P
and hit tab twice that will expand out to a property.
I'll give the first property a type of string.
We will call this property name and I'll give us another property.
This one also type string will include the location.
And let's say that this about model represents everything that we want to show
when the user visits the about page.
So what I'll need to do is come into the HomeController and instead of using the ViewBag,
I'll declare a new instance of our about model.
The about model isn't a different name space that I'm currently in.
So for this to be legal C sharp code, I need to include the name space
that this is defined in which is OdeToFood.Models.
An easy way to do that is just to use this drop down menu here that's sometimes hard
to get a hold of, and click on this to add the using for OdeToFood.Models.
A quick way to do this is when your cursor is on that unexpected identifier.
Just hold down the control key and hit period.
That will drop down the menu then select it using enter.
That adds the using statement for me and we now have legal C sharp code.
Now, usually when you build a model, you need to do some sort
of data access or some calculations.
But right now, we'll just counter up something.
We'll save the data access stuff for later.
I'll give this a name, you can use your name and I will say
that my location is still Maryland in the United States.
And now that the model is complete, I can tell the MVC framework
that when it renders this view, you use this model.
So pass this model along to the view.
The next step would then be to modify the view to use this new model.
So let me come into the About.cshtml view.
The first thing I'll do up here at the top is tell the view about this model.
So I'm going to use what's known as a directive which is at model and that's a lower case M,
very important that you use the lower case M here,
tell it that the model it should expect will be an instance of about model.
And again in order for the name space to work, I'll have to hit control period and drop down
and say that this isn't OdeToFood.Models.AboutModel,
in this case it doesn't add a using statement,
just adds the pooling name space qualified type name which is just fun.
And now instead of going to ViewBag which we never knew quite what is in ViewBag.
There could be a message property, there might not be a message property.
Instead of using ViewBag, I will use the model property of this view.
The model property knows what we're passing in as a model
and quite often you can get IntelliSense, let me do a quick build
by doing shift control B making sure the project builds,
and then maybe when I hit period, I can see the IntelliSense.
I can see there is a name, that's what we'll put out here.
And I can see there is a location.
So, let me switch the server to the model.location just to save everything,
do another build, amount and refresh.
And we're now building this view using a strongly typed model.
And this is a very common approach to MVC development.
So, let me just reiterate what we did here.
This model property with the capital M at Model that will represent the model object
that I passed in to this view from the controller action.
And in fact, I told Razor that it should be expecting a model of type about model
and now visual studio and Razor and everyone in the world knows
that the object it should be receiving is an object of that type
that it should have name and location properties.
And what we've seen so far is really the essence of MVC, I have a request arrive
for slash home slash about that will be delivered by the framework to this
about action on my home controller.
I build a model, pass it to the default view.
When that view renders, it picks apart that model and puts all the pieces
in the right location for-- to display correctly to the user.
So, I can see this working, but how can I be a little more assured
that this will always work for me?
That's where unit testing come into play.
So, let's look at unit testing with ASP.NET MVC next.