As I mentioned previously, one of the goals of the MVC framework is to be testable.
Specifically, your controller should be testable.
I should be able to exercise the logic inside of the controller action from a unit test
and be able to write assert to make sure that the logic is behaving correctly
and I should be able to do that without involving a web server or HTTP messages,
or my network card or other things that make testing complicated.
Fortunately, when I created this application, we told Visual Studio
to create a unit test project for us.
And if I look in the solution explorer window,
I'll see there are actually two projects in my application solution.
The first one is OdeToFood that's the web application
and the second one is OdeToFood.test.
This is my testing project.
Inside of the testing project are some test the Visual Studio added
when I created this application, these aren't the most fantastic tests in the world,
but they do demonstrate how to implement unit test.
This is a new feature for Visual Studio 2012 by the way.
In previous versions of Visual Studio the free express edition did not include a unit testing
tool, but it 2012 we have the framework known as MS test.
So, let me open up the one set of test that it's inside of here the home controllers test.
And you can see that tests are identified by attributes.
With MS test you need an attribute on every class that contains a test,
that's the test class attribute that you see.
This attribute helps the test runner which we'll use in just a bit
to find all the test inside of this project.
And then every individual tests inside of a test class has a test method attribute.
What a test runner is going to do is once it finds your test,
it will instantiate every test class
and then invoke every method that's a test method inside of that class.
It will then check to see if each of those test passes or fails.
You can tell the test runner when something fails.
Inside of every unit test, you typically have three steps.
Each step can have one or more lines of code.
The first step in the arrange step.
This is where you create objects that you want to test.
In this index test, we're looking at the arrange act just consisting
of just instantiating the home controller.
That's the object that we want to test.
Thanks to the testability of ASP.NET that we see we can instantiate our controllers from anywhere
and not have them fail just because they aren't processing a real HTTP request.
After the arrange step comes the act step.
This is where you set things in motion.
You usually invoke a method or set a property, do something to the object that you want to test
and have it produce a result which you'll capture and examine
in the third step which is the assert step.
This is where you rate an assertion that should prove whether or not something work correctly.
In this test we're just asserting that the home controller produced a result
or the result .ViewBag.Message was equal to some specific string that's here.
The test is just making sure
that ViewBag.Message property is set the way it expects it.
As I said, this isn't the greatest in the world.
There is no real logic or need to test it that exact string as a match,
but it does demonstrate how to use the test framework and to test API
and you can see the arrange act assert steps that are common to almost every unit test.
The assert API by the way includes a number of different assertions you can write.
This assert is the R equal assert.
It's to make sure that two objects are equal.
But you can also assert that something is true or something is false or something is not null.
There are many different types of assert.
If the assertion fails, the test will fail.
To see what test are passing and what test are failing.
I just need to get the test runner going.
I can do that by going to the test menu and saying run all the tests,
the shortcut key there is control R followed by an A and when I do
that I'll see the test explorer appear, test that have a green icon next
to them are passing test that's good.
Test that have a red icon next to them are failing test that would be bad.
Let's see if we can get a failing test, right now we only have three tests
and they are all passing but I can break something easily.
I'll come over into the home controller and remove this bit of code
that is passing the model in to build the view result.
That means my view will not receive a model object and if I run the application when it's
in this state, and go to that about action, we'll get a runtime error because the view needs
that model when we don't pass a model
in to build the view result we'll get a null model property and when we try to--
dereference that by doing model.name we'll get the object reference not set
to an instance of an object exception.
I could avoid this with a unit test, a unit test that makes sure that the about action
of the home controller sets a model object and that the model object is of the right type
and having a unit test in place for that will mean I can see
that it's failing before it ever try to push this somewhere where someone will see it,
I'll catch this error before the application ever runs.
Let's try to do that.
If I come over into the home controller test, I can see there already is an about test here.
But the about test is just making sure that the about action is producing a result,
any result and that the result is not null.
And so, the change I made in the home controller will still not break this test.
Let's run all the test again.
All the test are still passing.
I need to do a little more in this test.
I need to really assert that result.model is not null.
That's the important part that the view needs.
We need a result but that result also needs a model associated with it.
So with that change in the test and we run all the test again, now we have a failing test.
If I click on the failing test, I'll get down here in the bottom of the test explorer window,
a StackTrace I can click on the top link here, it will take me right to the line of code
that failed, in this case it failed because result.model is null
and the assertion is making sure that it's not null and to fix that, I just need to go back
to the controller and put the code back in place so I actually pass a model along,
now I can hit control RA to run all the test again.
And we should come out with three passing tests.
So this is all the time we have to talk about testing right now but we'll return
to this topic later in the course.
This is just a quick demonstration that was intended to show you how easy it can be
to test the logic in your presentation layer, specifically the logic
that you have inside of your controllers.
Controllers are relatively plain C sharp classes.
We can instantiate them without having a web server
or a web browser or an HTTP request running.
And compared to the view, it's the controllers that are doing all the hard work.
Views are just simple in the MVC design pattern we use them just as templates
to control the placement of data to most of the unit testing effort in an MVC application,
it was against the controllers and the models.