So far, we've started to see how views, models and controllers work together
and we've also seen how you see this to write unit test for an MVC application.
But I also mentioned earlier that another goal of the MVC framework is to embrace the web
and that means being able to use standard web technologies like HTML 5, JavaScript, and CSS 3.
We've already seen a bit about how to work with HTML.
We know the razor views that are in our views folder emit this HTML and we've already seen
that the project does set up to use HTML 5.
But there's a couple of other folders we haven't looked at yet,
the scripts folder and the content folder.
Inside of the scripts folder you'll find JavaScript files.
The JavaScript files here include the popular jQuery library as well
as some other jQuery plug ins we'll be using later in this course,
plugins like jQuery validation and jQuery UI.
And the content you will find the CSS style sheet for this site.
This file site dot CSS is the file that's responsible for all the color
and font choices that you see in the application.
Let me make some basic changes to the body style here and see how that's reflected
in the application instead of a white background color, let's go with 3, 3, 3, and instead this
or that color let's change that over to white.
So essentially we're flipping the background and foreground colors.
And now once I save that file and refresh this page, you can see that influence is how
at least that top of the page displays.
But let me make a few more tweaks to that file and come right back.
Now I finished making a few tweaks to my CSS file.
And I've and added an image to the project.
And this is what the applications looks like now.
It's still not the prettiest application in the world but this is what we're going to be working
on throughout the rest of the course.
And hopefully we'll be adding features and making look it better.
If you are interested in looking at the source code for this project,
just go to odetofoodmvc4.codeplex.com.
From here you can come into the source code tab.
And from in the source code section you can download the latest source code.
You can also click this History link and go back and see what the code look
like at specific point in time like this point in time with the first video is nearly over.