In this first module I've demonstrated how to use the Web Platform Installer
to create a development environment or you can build ASP.NET MVC Web Applications.
With just a few clicks we were able to install Visual Studio, SQL Server and the MVC Framework.
We still how to create a new MVC application and we talked
about the Model, View, Controller design pattern.
In the rest of this course we will be again drilling
into specific areas of the MVC Framework.
And see how to build Controllers, how to build Models, send story information in SQL Server.
We'll take a very close look at Razor and also how to use jQuery plugins
to add Ajax features to our application.
We'll be writing more unit test and then
in the end we'll deploy our application live to the internet.
Thanks to Microsoft Windows Azure websites.
So don't go away, we're only getting started with this excitement.