Configuration files and .NET are XML files that control everything
about the environment your code will execute inside of.
For web applications, this includes the authentication settings as we saw
in the security module of this course, but config files also control the compilation
of use, database connection strings, cryptography settings,
custom errors settings, and much, much more.
The configuration system in .NET is also extensible,
so if you want to build your own custom configuration section,
all you need to do is write some classes to support that.
I'm not going to show you that specific scenario in this module,
but I will demonstrate an easy way for you to store custom settings in a configuration file.
Inside of Visual Studio I'm going to open up the web.config file that's in the root
of this project; the one we've been using repeatedly throughout this course.
This is where we specify the connection string for the database that we want to use.
We've also looked at the globalization settings in here, we've created some cash profiles,
we've configured custom errors, and we've looked at authentication.
So there are various components of ASP.NET and ASP.NET MVC, and also of the webserver itself
that look in this configuration file for settings.
And so, the obvious question might be what if I want
to keep my own settings inside of web.config?
One of the easiest things to do if you just have a simple value that you want to store is
to add it to the app settings section.
Right here I can add a new setting with a key of mail server and give it a value.
And now, I want to be able to retrieve that value inside of my MVC application; let's say,
somewhere inside of the home controller.
Let's just read that value out, and put it into a view.
The easiest way to do that would be to just put it into viewbag.
And the way I can read that setting is to use configuration manager that's
in a namespace system.configuration.
Configuration manager will give me access to connection strings, to app settings;
really to anything that's in a config file.
But here I'm explicitly asking for the mail server app setting.
We'll grab that value.
We'll put it in viewbag, and in the index view that that action renders.
Let's delete some of the culture globalization stuff that we were fiddling with
and instead write out viewbag.mailserver to see if we've retrieved this correctly.
I'll do a build and refresh the homepage of the application,
and there you can see we get out mail.server.com.
So that worked.
And configuration manager makes it very easy to grab app settings,
and really any setting that's in a web.config file.
And this is the place where you want to put things
that you don't necessarily want to hardcode.
So connection strings, server names, file share names; all of those types
of things can go into your configuration file.
That way, you can change them just by changing the config file and you don't have
to recompile and redeploy all your binaries.
( Silence )