Configuration files for .NET are hierarchical, meaning the configuration
for your application is controlled not only by the web.config in your project,
but also by configuration files at a higher level.
When you're running the MVC application, the configuration starts
with a machine level configuration file.
That file controls basic settings for all .NET applications that run on the same computer;
desktop applications, windows services, and even web applications -- everything.
We'll take a look at where this file lives and what's inside in just a minute.
There's also a machine level web.config file.
We looked at that when we were poking around in the health monitoring settings.
It puts in place all the default settings for every ASP.NET application on the machine.
And before we get to the web.config that's in our application,
we might also have a parent web.config file that we inherit settings from, and that would happen
if our application is deployed underneath another ASP.NET web application.
These configuration settings then are inherited downwards in the configuration in effect
for your application is a combination of all the configuration files.
Inside my web.config file I can generally override any settings that might be in place
from the machine level config or the machine level web.config file,
although administrators do have the option of locking down settings
and preventing me from changing a value.
Let's take a look at what these configuration files look like.
Using Windows Explorer, let's find the machine level configuration file.
I need to look on the C drive under windows, under Microsoft.net, framework.
And as I mentioned in an earlier module, even though we're running .NET 4.5 we need
to look in the version 4 config folder.
It's inside of here where we will find the machine level web.config.
I can open that up.
It's about the most boring configuration file you'll ever see.
Most of it is just sections describing the types to use
for other configuration sections when they're loaded.
But there are some things in here, and there are some things
in here that actually apply to ASP.NET.
For instance, all the way at the bottom,
here's the default membership provider that's configured for all ASP.NET applications.
It's the ASPNET sql membership provider, but we're not using this in our application.
We have changed the setting in our web.config -- overridden it.
Down here at the bottom -- remember we added our own membership section
that is using the simple membership provider.
So that's an example of changing the defaults that are specified at a higher level.
We can also find the root level web.config file here.
This is the file that would apply to all ASP.NET web applications
that are running version 4 or version 4.5 of .NET.
It's inside of here where you can find things like the default authorization rule;
will allow all users, even anonymous users into every site unless you tell us otherwise.
It's inside of this file where you can also find the default health monitoring rules --
we looked at those previously -- the default HTTP handlers;
that is like a file with and ASHX extension.
What is the handler for that?
What class does the .NET runtime need to instantiate to handle that request?
And we can also see inside of here some default modules.
Modules provide services like implementing our forms authentication,
doing checks against the cookie that arrives to see if the user has been authenticated.
Also, the routing engine is an HTTP module.
It runs in the ASP.NET pipeline and gets to look at every request.
That's what an HTTP module can do.
So many settings in this root level web.config file, but eventually the settings inside
of our own web.config file get to take effect.
And these can override the settings like for membership.
And we can even inside of our own application have web.config files
that override settings for a specific directory.
For instance, there's a web.config file in the views folder.
This is the web.config file that controls razor configuration.
These are the namespaces that are in effect when a razor template is parts and compiled.
We added a few custom namespaces here during the course.
And there's other interesting things in here too.
Like if I scroll down here a little bit,
there is an HTTP handler registered essentially saying, if a request arrives here looking
for any type of file using any type of HTTP verb -- doesn't matter if it's a get or a post --
the component that will handle that is the HTTP not found handler.
The HTTP not found handler essentially returns a 404 error to the client.
Why are we doing that inside of the views folder?
We're doing that because if someone launches a browser and request and file that is
in this views folder directly -- like if they typed
in localhost/views/home/index.cshtml, we want to return a 404 error.
A user shouldn't be able to go directly to a view using a browser.
They should go through a controller.
It's the controller that gets to select a view.
Therefore, we'll just return a 404 if anyone requests a file inside of here directly.
And this file is here by default when you start a new MVC application.
( Silence )