Now that we understand a little bit about ASP.NET configuration,
let's see how to deploy an application and how to change configurations on a deployed website.
First, understand that when you build an MVC application, you're producing a .DLL file
with the application logic inside.
That's going to sit in the bin directory of your project.
DLL's don't execute by themselves.
They need some sort of host process to load them into memory.
And for websites that host processes, also then responsible
for delivering HTTP requests to the logic inside the DLL.
We've been using IIS Express as the host for our application so far.
IIS Express makes things very easy for development because it runs with our identity,
and we can start and stop the webserver whenever we need to.
But if you're deploying an application for real on the internet or intranet,
chances are you'll be using the full version of internet information services.
You can install IIS on nearly any version of Windows, but it is off by default
on nearly all versions of Windows.
So you might need to go into Windows features
or use the web platform installer to get IIS onto a machine.
Let me show you how that works.
What I want to do now is transform my development environment
into a server type environment by installing IIS.
And one of the easiest ways to do that is to use the web platform installer.
You might remember that we used this in the introduction
to this course to install Visual Studio.
Now, I'm going to launch it, and install IIS as well as a few other tools.
So up here in the top right where I can search, I'm going to search for IIS and ASP.NET.
That should find me this entry; IIS with ASP.NET 4.5.
Let's add that.
I also want to be able to manage IIS.
So let me search for IIS, and select the IIS management console.
And I'm also going to install sql server --
a sql server express edition because even though we already have local DB installed,
it turns out that using local DB from IIS is a bit of a pain.
It can be done, but it requires a lot of configuration and it's configuration
that you'd never have to do, because when you really do deploy to production,
chances are you'll have a real instance of sql server and a real license,
and everything will be set up for you.
I'm just going to install sql server express just to get this running under IIS,
and let you see what it would look like.
I'm also going to install sql management tools because chances are we're going to have to log
into that database and tweak some permissions.
So I will install the sql server management studio.
Four components to install just click the install button.
I will need to fill out some information about the SA password.
SA stands for system administrator.
That's the all-powerful account inside of sql server.
I'm just giving it an initial password.
I can click continue and accept, and we'll come back after all
of this has finished downloading and installing.
Now the web platform installer has finished.
I should be able to exit out.
And I should be able to open up internet explorer and go to local host.
And I can see that IIS 8 is running on this machine.
That's a good sign.
This is exactly where we want to deploy our application.
So if I come to local host I won't see the IIS banner page.
I'll instead see Ode To Food.
Let's check to make sure the other components installed too.
I'm going to go and search for sql management studio, and once this has initialized I will try
to connect to the sql express instance.
There's two ways to get to a local sql express instance.
You can specify a server name/sqlexpress.
You can also use a period here to specify that you want to go
to the local sql express instance.
I should be able to click connect.
And that looks good, there's no databases there yet.
That's where we're going to put our Ode To Food database.
You can also use this management tool by the way, to connect to local DB.
A connection string is just like you see in your web.config file.
It's local DB inside a parenthesis, slash V11.0.
And when I connect to that I can see our Ode To Food DB as well
as some other temporary databases that Visual Studio has created for things
like storing the unit test results.
And finally, there was one more tool that we installed.
That was the IIS management console.
It wants me to launch the web platform installer.
We don't need to do that right now.
I just want to see that IIS is running on this machine.
Inside of this manager you can go through and modify any of the settings for this server.
A lot of this just maps down to the same XML files
that we've been looking at -- configuration files.
Inside of a server I can see two nodes: there's application pools.
An application pool is a process that a web application will run inside of.
We'll be using the default application pool.
I can already see there's one application running there.
That's the website that we went to that just has the IIS banner.
If you go into the task manager for Windows --
and in Windows 8 the task manager is a little bit fancier
than the previous versions of Windows.
So let me go to more details, and go to the details tab.
Inside of here I should be able to find a W3WP.EXE.
That's a world wide web worker process .EXE.
That will be the process that will host our MVC application default app pool.
And also, inside the manager if I drill into sites I can see there's one site in here now.
It's the default website.
That's where we will deploy our application.
You can have additional websites, and you can have web applications listed under that website.
We want to deploy our application to the root of this website.
So that's what we'll get ready to do next.
( Silence )