There's just a couple housekeeping tasks that I want to take care
of to get my application ready for deployment.
These mostly revolve around the database.
The first thing I'd like to do is re-do our database migrations.
We've been a little loose with our migrations.
We've been running with automatic migrations enabled, which means,
we don't get explicit migration scripts; or migration files in the migrations folder.
Instead when we go to the package manager and go to update database,
it just makes whatever changes in the database that it sees fit to do.
Whatever is needed to sink up the schema with our models.
But for my first deployment, I'd like to baseline the database and get us into a state
where we will not be using automatic migrations anymore.
We'll be a little more careful because after we deploy, we'll get live data in the database.
We need to start taking care of things, and making sure we're managing the schema properly.
At least that's how I feel.
I essentially want to restart the migrations.
There's nothing in the database that I need right now.
All the data comes from our seed method down here, which while I'm in here,
I'm also going to remove the 1000 restaurants that we create just to test paging and sorting
because I don't want to deploy those either.
And I will also delete our initial database migration script.
I'm just going to recreate this from scratch using a brand new database.
And the definition of the schema will be based on what is in our model classes right now;
what's a restaurant, what's a review.
And the best way to do this with entity framework migrations is to come in
and also delete your database, so it doesn't see anything there and knows
that you want to start from scratch.
And I can do this through the sql server management studio just by highlighting Ode
To Food and right-clicking and saying delete; or hitting the delete key.
I'm going to tell sql management studio to close any existing connections
to make sure we can drop this database.
And it looks like it's gone.
And now reopen the package manager console, and let's create our initial migration.
Remember, we're not using automatic migrations anymore.
We won't be able to just say update database and have it create a database for us.
We need to have a migration script there first.
So add migration, initial create.
And I need to make sure that this executes us under the right project;
not OdeToFood.test, but OdeToFood.
That's where my entity framework DB context class is.
And now we will have an initial create that includes everything that we've been using,
the user profile class, restaurants, restaurant reviews.
And this is the point where I would also go through this file
and make sure all the column sizes are reasonable.
Make sure indexes are applied.
But for this application we can forge ahead.
Now, the other thing I'm going to want to do with this application is that it when deploys,
I want it to run the migrations automatically.
There's a way to do that through configuration, but we're actually going to do it through code.
And the other thing I want to do before I forget is make sure
that web security does not get initialized more than once
because if you call initialized database more than once,
this line of code will throw an exception and stop everything.
It's very easy to check if web security is initialized.
If web security initialized -- and put a not in front of here --
so if it's not initialized, we will initialize the database.
And the reason I'm putting that check there is because now we're going
to be running migrations when the web application runs.
So this initialized database connection can run when the web application is running.
And we have another call to initialize the database connection here during
application start.
I'm also going to put a guard around this.
Although I'm fairly certain it's always going to run before we reach this point because I want
to run the migrations before we get into this point in application start.
I'm still going to put that check there just to make sure it doesn't throw and exception.
And it is during the application start event when I want to run the migrations,
and I can do that using a class called DB migrator.
It is in the system.data.entity.migrations namespace.
So I'm just going to bring that in.
And we give it our configuration class that is in our project in a migrations folder.
So also bring that namespace in.
And then just tell it to update.
That will run any schema changes that need applied.
That will run the seed method to make sure the database is populated.
And the reason I'm doing this in code instead of in my web.config file, which is possible is
because I want to make very sure about when these migrations run.
I want them to run at this point before web security tries to initialize the database.
If you're not using forms authentication or if you are using forms authentication,
but not using web security, you wouldn't have to use this approach.
You could just put some configuration in place that would run the migrations automatically.
And the tools as we'll see in just a bit, will automatically add that configuration for us.
I'll point that out when we get to it.
But for now, I think we've reached the point where we are ready to deploy.