When you're ready to deploy an application, you can right click
on your web project and select publish.
Visual Studio will figure out all of the files that need to be deployed to a web server,
collect them all together, and push them there.
All you need to do is tell it how to do that.
The first thing you do is select a publishing profile.
I'll create a new profile.
I'll give it the name release because this will be my release mode build that I want to publish.
And on the next screen, I can select a publish method.
There's several different methods here.
If you need to FTP the files to the server, Visual Studio can do that.
If you need to just push something onto a file system, you already know the directory
where the webserver will serve this application from; you can also do that.
You can select web deploy, and just enter in a server name and the site that you want
and it will contact the server and push your files over.
You can do this with shared hosting providers on the internet.
You can also do it on intranet servers if you're deploying with inside your company.
The one catch to web deploy here is I would want to push to local host.
And the problem is that in order to do this, I need to be an administrator.
So I could re-launch Visual Studio using renams
( assumed spelling )
administrator and then right click and publish and be successful,
but I'm going to show you a different approach.
We're going to build a web deploy package.
A web deploy package is ultimately just a zip file, and you can take the zip file and put it
on a USB key or email it to a administrator at your company, and they will be able
to take the web deploy package and copy it to a server, and install it for you.
In this case, we'll be doing the installing.
Let me create a package -- let me create a directory under dev.
We'll call it Ode To Food release.
And I need to include .zip in the name so release.zip.
And actually, let me put the zip file inside of a folder called release.
And then I pick the site where I want this to be deployed.
So it could be something like default website/OdeToFood, but I actually want this
in the root directory of the website.
So if someone just goes to local host, they will see this application running.
So the site I wanted to deploy it to on this IIS server is default website.
And that's actually just a parameter that you can change when you deploy it.
But now, if I click next, the next screen will go through what sort
of configuration do I want it to build in; release or to bug.
We will deploy in release mode and I can also pick a connection string
to use for default connection.
Remember, right now default connection is the connection string that's
in the web.config that's pointing to local DB.
When I deploy this to IIS, I want it to point to that sql express instance that I just installed.
So I will say that the default connection should actually point here.
The server name will be dot/sqlexpress.
I will use Windows authentication to connect.
We'll see how that creates a slight hiccup, but we'll work around that,
and the database that we will use; I will call it OTF production just
to make this dramatically different.
And select okay.
We can say yes, go ahead create this database for me.
And when this application is deployed, that connection string will be substituted
into the default connection, and replace whatever we are using there for development.
And then this checkbox here, execute first code migrations.
That's where I was telling you if you select this checkbox, Visual Studio will also add a bit
of configuration to your web.config file that will automatically run
into the framework code first migrations.
But we're actually going to explicitly run the migrations in our code,
so I'm going to leave that unselected.
Then there's a preview screen, which will tell you, you are about to create release.zip.
And let me just click publish.
All the files will be packaged up together.
And what I can do now is open up a command prompt; make sure I right click it and say run
as administrator because I will need administrator privileges
to actually get this installed into IIS.
And then come into that directory where I placed the zip file,
and inside of here I'll find the zip file.
I'll also find a command script that I can run that will do the installation for me.
And if I run it without any parameters, it will pop up a little help and notepad
that will tell me there's two ways to run this.
You can pass the /T to test the deployment and simulate what would happen,
and it will show you any errors that might occur.
Or, you can do a /Y to just go ahead and do the full deployment.
You can also point it to a remote computer, pass in a username and password;
all sorts of additional flags you could use.
Let's see what happens if we run this with a /T.
I don't see any error messages, so this just might go through if I run it with a /Y.
And now, if I come back into internet explorer, where we used to see an IIS 8 banner page,
if I refresh, we'll see our application trying to make a connection
to the database, but it can't quite get there.
It doesn't have permission to do it.
And this is because the IIS worker process that we looked at earlier W3WP.EXE runs
under an identity known as IIS app pool default app pool.
And this user account doesn't have any permissions
in the database or on the server at all.
When we're using local DB for development, we're administrators for local DB
and IIS express is running under our identity, so we can do anything with local DB.
But to get this application running with a production database,
I need to give some permissions to that default app pool account.
So I'll open up sql server management studio, and under security there will be logins.
What I want to do is create a new login for that account.
So the account is IIS app pools/default app pool.
And I'll come over into user mapping, and say please give this login the ability to get
into OTF production as a user, and give this login the ability to read data,
to write data, and to execute DDL.
Essentially execute things like create table.
The entity framework migrations will need to modify the schema.
We'll need to be DDL admin here.
And now click okay.
And now come back and refresh the browser and our application is now running under IIS 8.
We have our database in place; we have our C data in the database.
I should be able to log in, create restaurants, create reviews, and use all the features
that we've built into this application.