Now once you've completed all this work and you're done with the single deployment,
subsequent deployments are much smoother.
For instance, I'm looking at the home page.
I'm seeing it's displaying mail.server.com on the home page.
I don't necessarily want that there.
That was just an experiment we were doing to make sure
that we could read the configuration file that was in the home index view.
Let me open up and remove that, save the view, come back out to the project, and say publish.
It has already selected by release package that we created earlier.
So let me go ahead and click publish.
That will rebuild the zip file.
I can come out here to the command line, re-execute to the deploy.
Notice that it's smart enough to understand what's
on the server; what's new, what's changed.
It only copied over the files that needed change.
And now if I refresh the application, then that text is gone and we just made a small tweak
to the deployed version of the application.
And let's just see what's happening behind the scenes.
If I open up the IIS manager, I'll be able to come into the default website,
and switch over into content view.
That actually shows me the files that are sitting out here.
It does need to be refreshed.
And now I can see my views folder, my scripts folder,
my content folder with site.css inside of it.
You might be wondering what happened to the controllers folder.
This all looks like exactly like it did in my solution except there's some things missing.
Well the controllers folder is all C sharp code.
Visual Studio compiles all that code into a DLL.
Remember I said that when you build a web application you produce a DLL,
and that goes into this bin folder.
Here we can see OdeToFood.DLL that will have all the controller code compiled inside
of that assembly.
We also have a lot of other assemblies.
These are all things that we reference and that we need to run.
Assemblies like DotNetOpenAuth, which as I described
in the security module is what helps users log in using OpenAuth and OpenId.
And when a request arise or the default website -- aka local host --
IIS will spin up that W3WP.EXE process, load our assemblies into it,
and start sending us requests to process.
That's when MVC takes over, calls into our controller, which renders a view.
That's how the application all works.