Now that we've deployed to IIS on a local server,
let's deploy to IIS running in the cloud with Windows Azure.
To get started, I'll to go the Windows Azure website; WindowsAzure.com.
And if you haven't heard of Azure, it is Microsoft's Cloud platform
where you can host websites, databases and virtual machines.
You can run Windows or Linux, and you can start small and scale up really big just
by adding more resources for Microsoft's global data centers.
If I want to put a new website into Azure, I would first log into the Azure portal.
This is currently in preview, but by the time you watch this video it might be live.
I'll first need to sign in with my live ID.
( Silence )
And the first screen that is about to come up will be a screen
where I can see everything I have deployed in Azure under this account.
It's my portal where I can add new databases, new websites,
new virtual machines, new media services.
It's also where I can manage my existing services, and where I can create new services,
which is what I'll want to do when this is finished loading.
We want to add a new website and give the website a database for storage.
And you can see I have a few things out there already; couple websites, couple databases,
a virtual machine, a storage account.
But I want to create a new website with a database to host Ode To Food.
First I'll need to give my website a URL.
What will happen is that my website will be OdeToFood.AzureWebsites.net.
I can also get a DNS and point this to my website in Azure,
so it could just be OdeToFood.com; but we'll leave it as AzureWebsites.net for right now.
I get to pick a region for the data center.
I'll pick the eastern United States.
I want to create a new sequel database.
My connection string name -- let's call it OdeToFoodDB.
And in the next step I'll need to specify my database settings.
This is the name that I want to use.
The server will be a sql server that I already have in Azure; I just need to log in properly.
And I can show you what the advanced database settings look like.
This is where I can select my addition wherever business The maximum database size one gigabyte
will be good enough to start, and my collation.
And with all that in place I can select okay,
and Azure will go off and start creating this website.
As soon as it's done creating that I'll have a website on the internet that I can go to.
It'll have just the blank Azure template.
And what we'll need to do is publish our website now, and set it to local IIS to this website.
There are a number of publishing options available with Azure websites.
You can see them in the list here.
You can use GIT, you can use TFS, you can use Visual Studio or WebMatrix.
We're going to be using Visual Studio; it's very simple.
First I'll go to this website.
This brings up the dashboard where I can look at things like how much CPU has been used
by the website over the last 24 hours or over the last week.
But it's also where I can download a publishing profile.
Remember when we were publishing to IIS we created a publishing profile.
This is going to download one for me that I could just plug into Visual Studio,
and it will have all the settings that it needs to upload my website here.
And we just downloaded it into my downloads folder.
And now, let me go into Visual Studio, and let's publish this website again.
I'm going to go to the profile tab, because I want to import this new profile.
And there it is; the publish settings file.
If you open that up, it's just a big scary amount of XML inside, but it has everything
that I need to get this to the right server.
So it already includes the URL, the site name, the user name, passwords.
All you need to do is -- I can validate the connection; make sure this is going to work.
And that looks good.
So let's go to the next phase where you can see we're going
to again deploy a release mode build.
It is already understood that my default connections string will probably want
to point to that sql server in the cloud.
It will have populated the server name and the user name
and the password, and everything I need.
We're not going to run the entity code first migrations.
We're taking explicit control of our migrations in the code.
I'll just go to next.
This allows me to preview what it is going to push out.
But I'm feeling lucky, so I'm just going to click publish.
Since this is going over the internet, it might take a little bit of time.
The first time you need to publish it needs to push out a lot of assemblies,
a lot of data going over the network.
We'll come back in a second when it's finished pushing everything up into the cloud.
And the publishing operation has just succeeded.
I should now be able to go back into the browser.
Let's refresh this website.
And I'm now running on AzureWebsites.net, very simple to deploy.
All my functionality should be there.
The database is working.
We see the database.
That means I should be able to log into this application.
( Silence )
That was successful.
I should also be able to go and create new restaurant at this point.
And since I just launched, I don't expect a lot of traffic.
The wonderful thing about ager is that this is now in someone else's data center.
They make sure the electricity stays on.
They're making sure they take backups at all the right time.
And as this grows in popularity, I can come in and scale this thing out.
I can reserve my own machine, crank up the number of instances,
so I have more instances available to serve up all the requests that are coming in.
And of course, you'll pay for the resources that you use, but hopefully you'll be making money
from all of the customers that come to the website,
and that will pay for everything that you need in Azure.
( Silence )