This concludes this module on configuration and deployment where we looked
at all the configuration files that are in effect when running a web application,
and we also deployed to IIS both locally and in Windows Azure.
This also concludes my ASP.NET MVC 4 course.
We've seen how to work with routing, controllers, and razor views.
We added javascript and used jQuery and jQuery UI to add Ajax features to the application.
And we also saw how to work with foreign authentication and the membership provider
that comes with our MVC application.
I hope you enjoyed this course and were able to use the videos
to either jumpstart your MVC development or solidify your existing knowledge
of the framework, just a reminder that all the code
that we've been working on is published on codeplex.
If you look at the history of the check-ins you'll see I did one check-in for each module.
So if you want to go back in time to a specific point and work along
with the video, you should be able to do that.
And now that we are finished I'd just like to say thanks for listening,
and good luck with your software development endeavors.