Hi! This is Scott Allen and this module of the course is devoted to Data.
In this first Data module, we want to start using a real database with our application.
So the focus of the first module is to bring SQL Server into the picture.
In the next Data module, we'll look at other data-related features
in the MVC framework, features like model validation.
What I'll demonstrate in this first module is how to use a technology known
as the Entity Framework and combine the Entity Framework
with the plain simple C Sharp class definitions we've been working with to build an application
that uses SQL Server to persist data.
We will see how to query data using link in the Entity Framework,
and also use the Entity Framework Migrations
to manage our database schema from C Sharp and Visual Studio.