The first stop we'll take in this module is to get up and running with the Entity Framework.
The Entity Framework is a part of the .NET framework and you'll already have a reference
to the Entity Framework in the new MVC internet application.
The Entity Framework or EF as I sometimes call it for short,
allows me to access a relational database using strongly typed C Sharp code,
or Visual Basic code, or really any .NET language.
When I'm working with classes to talk to the Entity Framework, I don't have to worry
about SQL connections, SQL commands, SQL parameters, SQL data readers,
none of the low level abstractions you might have programmed with in the past with .NET.
And if you don't know them, that's good for you because you won't have to learn them.
With the Entity Framework, I work with my C Sharp code and I can issue queries
to the database using a language feature called Language Integrated Query also known as LINQ
and this is a feature that's in both the C Sharp and Visual Basic languages.
There's a few different ways to get started with the Entity Framework.
One approach is called the Schema First approach.
In this approach, you open up a graphical designer in Visual Studio,
you point it to an existing database, and it can import the database schema
and generate all the classes you need to query and update that database.
Another approach is a Model First approach, this is where I use the same graphical designer
in Visual Studio to draw a conceptual model for my applications, so what classes do I want.
And then I have the Entity Framework generate both my class definitions
and my database schema.
Finally, there's a Code First approach you can take with EF.
In this approach, I just write C Sharp classes and the Entity Framework
and use those class definitions to create a database for me.
And it will do that either using conventions like naming conventions,
very similar to the naming conventions we've seen with the MVC framework and that is
where things just magically work if they had the right name.
I can also provide explicit mappings or change the mappings if I don't like any
of these conventions or defaults that the Entity Framework uses.
In this module, we're going to use a Code First approach,
so we won't see a visual design surface or any XML configuration files.
I hope that makes you happy.
And when I say that the Entity Framework supports relational databases,
then the Entity Framework supports quite a few.
You can point the Entity Framework towards a full-blown SQL Server installation
on a remote server that has hundreds of gigabytes of RAM and network storage.
Or you can point it to SQL Server Compact edition which is running in process
and accessing a database file on the local file system.
You can also use it with usher in the clown (phonetic),
you can use it with Oracle, you can use it with DB2.
But my code really doesn't have to know what's on the back end.
The Entity Framework knows how to work with all these different databases.
I can build an application without worrying so much about the database details.
In this module, we'll be working with SQL Server,
specifically the local DB version of SQL Server.