So far in the application, we've been using some in-memory data and this Restaurant Review class
to get some things done and experiment with razor and controllers.
But this restaurant review really combines a restaurant, the restaurant name and a review
which is the rating, I really need to separate those out
and form a relationship if we're going to move forward.
So there should be a restaurant class which I can create right now.
And that restaurant class will have multiple reviews associated with it.
We'll give a couple of properties to the restaurant,
there's going to be a primary key fields so we'll give it an ID property.
We'll give it a name.
We'll also store the city that the restaurant is in and the country.
And then every restaurant can have some associated reviews.
We'll put that in ICollection, a collection of restaurant reviews.
And this seems like a good definition for a restaurant.
Let's go over into the review class and change some things around.
A restaurant review will still have an ID, the name, city and country,
that's really restaurant information.
We don't need that.
We'll have the rating.
Perhaps we want the body of the review, so if a person wants to type out some text,
what they really thought about the restaurant, they can put that in here.
And although it's not entirely necessary,
it does make some scenarios easier if I add a restaurant ID field.
And this restaurant ID will point back to the restaurant that this review is associated with.
And now restaurant review and restaurant are my two entities, these are going to be objects
that I expect to instantiate and save in a database and retrieve from a database.
But right now, I'm leaving their definition in the models folder.
But if you continue down this path on larger applications,
the model's folder becomes way too big.
There's too many classes inside of it.
You might consider having a separate folder or even a separate project
where you define entities like this.
But this is good enough for our purposes to get started with.
Now let me also add a class that will use the Entity Framework
to persist and retrieve this data.
We'll call it OdeToFoodDb.
OdeToFoodDb needs to derive from an Entity Framework class known as the DbContext.
To use DbContext, I'll need to bring the System.Data.Entity name space
and the scope, so I'll add that using.
And then a DbContext, you can have properties of type DbSet that represent the entities
that you want to query and persist.
So we'll have a DbSet of restaurant called Restaurants.
And walking up to that DbSet and asking
for all the restaurants would essentially do a select star
from a restaurant table in SQL Server.
We'll have Restaurants and we'll have a DbSet of RestaurantReview.
RestaurantReviews is not something that I absolutely must have,
I can always get to reviews through a restaurant but I'm going to add it as a DbSet here.
Again, it makes some things easier.
To see how easy this is to use, let's say that we want the home page of the application now
to display a list of restaurants that we have in the database.
So let me swing over into the home controller and we're going to change
around the index action and also the view for this controller.
We don't really want to show the controller and the action and the ID anymore,
instead, we want to show restaurants.
So here I can instantiate OdeToFoodDb and I'll also point
out the sense this is a disposable resource, I should override dispose.
And if this is not null, tell it to dispose itself.
To dispose API and .NET is just a way to clean up resources that might be open.
Anything that implements the IDisposable interface or has a dispose method,
you should call it as soon as possible
to make sure everything is cleaned up as early as possible.
But with this bit of code in place, let's come into the home index action
and say that our model is equal to db.Restaurants.ToList.
What the Entity Framework will do when I execute that line of code is go into SQL Server,
find where it stored all the restaurants, retrieve all of them and put them into a list.
Eventually, if this application grows, we will need to provide some search facilities,
we'll need to provide some paging facilities but this should be enough to build a screen
that has a list of all our restaurants.
And now let's swing over into the index action for the home controller.
And let's clean some things up.
Let's get rid of the feature section and also the information about what we suggest
because we really just want to show restaurants on this page.
And because this view is already created, I'll add a model directive here manually to say
that this is strongly typed against IEnumerable of restaurant.
And I need to fully name space qualify that as OdeToFood.Models.Restaurant.
Again, just control period will give you that drop down menu
and you can have Visual Studio add that for you.
And now let's write those restaurants out.
So for each item in my model or each item as a restaurant, let's write out a div.
It has an h4 inside with the restaurant name.
And we can also write out the city and the country.
And then perhaps just put in a little horizontal line
to distinguish one restaurant from the other.
Now at this point, we don't have any data in a database because we don't even have a database
but we're very close to doing that.
Just by having a DbContext derived class, if I instantiate this class and ask it for data,
it will go out and see if a database exist.
And if that database doesn't exist, it will be created for me.
So I should be able to do a build.
And, of course, we'll have some compiler areas because we already had some code inside
of the reviews controller that was depending on a different definition of restaurant review.
So for right now, I'm going to hit Control A to highlight all the code inside
of our reviews controller and then hit Control K, control C to just comment it out.
We'll come back to the reviews controller later and rebuild it
so that it actually displays reviews that are associated with our restaurant instead
of using this in-memory data that we had here before.
There's another change that I want to make because that's commented out.
We're also going to have to change the layout view because if you remember,
caught into the reviews controller to list the best review but we don't really need that.
I'm going to delete that bit of code from the layout view.
And since the definition of our restaurant review has changed so dramatically,
I'm going to go ahead into the Reviews' views folder
and just delete our existing views from inside of here.
And this is all okay.
We're just taking in an iterative approach here to building an application
and learning MVC at the same time.
But I should have done enough now to be able to do a build and run the application.
And on the home page, it will try to list our restaurants
but of course we have no restaurants.
But the question here is, we didn't get an error so the Entity Framework talked
to some database, where is that database?
And to answer that question, let's go to view Database Explorer and add a connection.
This is going to be a SQL Server connection.
And I'm going to specify LocalDB v11.0 as the server I want to connect to.
This is a special connection string for SQL Server 2012 Express, the LocalDB edition.
So if you haven't heard of SQL Server LocalDB, it's a new edition
of SQL Server that's primarily targeted towards developers.
The big difference between this and SQL Server Express which you might have used
in the past during development is that LocalDB runs
with your identity and it doesn't run as a service.
It's launched on-demand when you need to get to it.
Other than that, it's very much like SQL Server.
And now let's pull down this drop down list to see what databases are available there.
And I can see that one of the databases is OdeToFood.Models.OdeToFoodDb.
I know this is the database that the Entity Framework just created because the name
of that database exactly matches the name of the OdeToFoodDb class that we created.
So by default, when you instantiate one of these and try to query data,
if the Entity Framework doesn't find a database and you have no other configuration in place
that tells the Entity Framework where to go, it will just look at LocalDB and create a database
that has the same name as your DBContext class.
And if we come in here, indeed we can see Restaurants.
We can see the RestaurantReviews.
We can see that RestaurantReviews have a primary key.
That's the ID column.
We can see that Restaurants also have an ID column.
And just to prove that this is working, if I go in and I say, show table data,
what I should be able to do here is add some new restaurant into the database manually.
Save that in the database.
And if I come up to the home page of the application again and refresh,
that restaurant is displaying on the home page.
So we are querying SQL Server and we've created our first database.
All this was taken care of by the Entity Framework just using the definitions
of our C Sharp classes, Restaurant and RestaurantReview.