You might be wondering if it's possible to influence
where the Entity Framework creates database and also
if you can influence how the Entity Framework creates a database.
Can you change the names of tables and add indexes and things like that?
Let's look at the first question, the where question.
You can configure your data context with a specific database connection string.
The way you do this is to call into the base class constructor.
And the syntax for that in C Sharp is to use the keyword base.
And right here, I could pass a connection string.
Explicitly specify the server, the database, and the credentials.
But we generally don't hard code connection strings into an application because when we want
to point the application to a different database that means we have
to change the code and recompile.
And since we usually write applications that used different databases, at least,
there's one database during development and one for deployment, and perhaps one for testing.
Well, it's a good idea not to hard code connection stings.
Instead, with ASP.NET, we can store connection strings in our web.config file.
I'm going to open up the web.config file that's in the root of this application.
And we can see there already is a connection string here in place
for us, it's called default connection.
The project template put this in place when we created this new application.
And we can change this connection string to point anywhere.
I'm just going to tweak it a little bit.
I still want it to point to LocalDB but I want the initial catalog not
to have the word ASP.NET and all this other stuff in it.
I just want it to be OdeToFoodDb Integrated Security equals SSPI.
That basically means connect with the process credentials, which is fine.
We do want it to attach to a file that's in the DataDirectory.
And again, I'm going to call this OdeToFoodDb.mdf
so it's very easy to identify there.
And now, if I want the Entity Framework to use this connection string, what I do when I call
into the base class constructor is say, name equals, and the name of my connection string.
And that tells it to go out into the web.config and use whatever that connection string value is
when it connects to the database.
Now, I never need to recompile the application when I want to point somewhere else,
I just need to go into the config file and I should be able to run the application again.
And we should be back to a blank page, there it is,
because we're now pointing to a new database.
It doesn't have that restaurant in there that I added manually.
But I should still be able to use the Database Explorer to poke around in that database.
In fact, default connection is already here in my data connections.
It just detected that when I loaded this project.
And there's Restaurants and RestaurantReviews.
I could add data in there manually again.
And also, I should be able to see this database now if I come
into the Solution Explorer and look in the App Data folder.
What I'll have to do is allow Solution Explorer to show all files with this toolbar button.
And there I can see OdeToFoodDb.mdf.
There are some other databases here that I should clean out
but we'll worry about that later.
Let's go back to our second question at the beginning which is,
how can I influence how the Entity Framework creates my schema?
And can I have it initially populates some data for me into that database?
And the answer to both of these questions is yes.
All we need to do is use Entity Framework Migrations.
Migrations are a feature of the Entity Framework that allow you to configure database schemas
with C Sharp code, seed your databases with C Sharp code and Migrations can then track changes
that you're making in your entity classes.
Those classes like Restaurant and RestaurantReview.
And it can keep the database schema in sync with the changes that you make in your C Sharp code.
The way to get started with Migrations is to open up the Package Manager Console.
There's two ways to do this.
You can go to the View menu and go to Other Windows and find the Package Manager Console
or you can use this Quick Launch toolbox that's up here in the upper right of Visual Studio
and just type, Package or Package Manager Console, it'll find all the commands
in the menus everywhere throughout Visual Studio really quickly
and then you can just click on it.
The Package Manager Console will open up here inside of Visual Studio as another window.
It's essentially a PowerShell command line.
If you know how to write scripts in PowerShell then you can use any PowerShell command in here
that you want and list directories and manage services.
Inside of here if you want to get what directory you're in, you can type GET-D and then hit tab.
You can see it has some tab completion.
Let's try and Get-Date instead, that executes, that's a PowerShell command.
But we're here actually for Migrations.
And what I want to do is enable Migration.
So, enable dash with an M, it knows I want Enable Migrations.
And I'm going to have to specify a ContextTypeName.
This is the name of my DBContext that I want to enable Migrations for.
In this case, just typing in OdeToFoodDb is sufficient.
And now when I press enter, this is going to kick off some logic that is part
of the Code First Migrations of the Entity Framework that goes out and pokes
around the environment and looks like at my classes, looks at any existing database,
and it will add a new folder with a new file into my solution.
The new folder is called Migrations.
And inside of Migrations, right now there's two files, Configuration.cs
and basically a schema change script that's written in C Sharp.
Let's talk about configuration first.
The configuration class is really about controlling Code First Migrations.
How do you want it to perform?
When should it run?
The one setting in here that is most notable is the Automatic Migrations Enabled setting.
By default, it will be false.
And that means, basically, that the Entity Framework won't make any changes
in your database unless you explicitly tell the Entity Framework
that you want it to make changes.
I'm going to set this to true because quite often,
when you are initially starting a project, you just want to be able to make changes
in your C Sharp code wherever those classes are and just have the database be ready
for you in the application to run.
If you're working in a more controlled environment
and the product is a little more mature, you might want to set this to false
and be very explicit about when changes in the database happen.
But I'll show the impact of setting this to true a little bit later.
The second nice part of the configuration class is the seed method.
This is basically where you can tell the Entity Framework
to populate the database with some initial data.
And now, every time that it goes to update the database, it's going to invoke the seed method.
And this gives you the opportunity to populate those tables
that always need data, things like lookup data.
You need a list of countries.
You need a list of postal codes, all of those types of things can go
into seed, and that's usually static data.
But I'm going to do something a little bit different because we do not have a screen
yet that will allow us to create a restaurant or a review, I'm going to paste in some code
that will create restaurants for us.
I'm pasting it in so you don't have to watch my typing skills, I know it's painful.
I do need to bring in some name spaces, OdeTofood.models and system.collection.generic.
But now that this code is legal, let me explain a little about what it does.
This is walking up to the RestaurantsDb set on our OdeToFoodDb context and it's saying add
or update the following restaurants.
So literally go into the database and see if any of these restaurants exist
by name, it's looking them up by name.
So what we'll see if there's a Sabatino's in the Restaurants table.
And if there is, it will update that record with the information I have here.
If that name doesn't exist in the Restaurants table,
it will add this new restaurant as a row into that table.
It will do that for all three of these, in fact,
it's even going to add a review for this last restaurant here.
And now, every time I update the database, the seed method will run.
And when I'm talking about updates, I'm talking about Migration updates.
You typically run a database update when you want to migrate the schema.
And that's why it's important that we're not just doing an add
because we might update this database multiple times.
As we're making schema changes, we're doing an add or update
so this information isn't duplicated inside of here.
So how do you update the database?
There's a couple of different ways to do it.
You can configure the application to automatically apply updates,
that's going to be very useful much later in the course when we deploy this
and it will just create a database for us in the Cloud.
We can also do it explicitly through the Package Manager Console.
It's a command update-database which I'm going to run
with the flag-verbose, so update database-verbose.
Verbose isn't going to add much information to this update
because we don't have any other changes to do.
And the two important pieces of output here are number one,
there were no pending code-based Migrations which is good.
That means essentially nothing in our C Sharp class has changed
so it didn't have to change the database.
But it did run the seed method that would that put that information into the database.
I'd be able to see that if I went into the Database Explorer.
I should also be able to see it if I just refresh the application.
And there you can see, I pulled those records out of the database.
So they are always there.
And every time I do the update database, it will check to make sure that they're there
and update them if they already are.
The other piece of output about no pending code-based Migrations, again,
that's because the Entity Framework didn't detect any changes.
But the other thing I can do when I run update database is have the database synchronize
with my model.
So for instance, if at this point,
I realize that a review should really also include the name of the person
that was reviewing this, I would probably come into this class and give this a new property,
let's call it ReviewerName and do a Build.
And at this point, if I come back to the Package Manager Console, I could do one of two things.
I could tell the Entity Framework that I explicitly need a Migration script to move
from the database schema as it currently exists into a new database schema
that can store ReviewerName or I can just tell it to update the database and let it figure
that out without being very explicit about it.
I'd only be able to do that because Automatic Migrations are enabled.
So what I will want to do is just to update the database.
But before I do that, let me show you what a Migration script would look like.
Because when we enabled Migrations in this project,
the Entity Framework created both the configuration.csfile
but also this, and this will create .CS file.
And if we look in here, it's essentially a schema change in C Sharp code.
In order to initially create the database,
what we need to do is create a table called Restaurants, give it the following columns, ID,
name, city, and country, and set the ID to be primary key.
By the way, ID is also an identity column.
That means in SQL Server, you'll have
that value automatically populated when you insert a new row.
We also need to create a table called RestaurantReviews with the following columns.
It has a primary key.
It also has foreign key that references another table.
And we want to apply an index to RestaurantId because it will probably be important
to query the reviews given a specific Restaurant ID
so we can find all the reviews for a given Restaurant.
I'll just quickly point out that there's many other commands that you can run in here.
For instance, if you just need it to execute some row of SQL during a Migration,
maybe to update some data, you could put an update statement in here,
execute it through that SQL method.
And when you update the database,
when the Entity Framework applies the script, that statement will execute.
So these Migrations, I keep calling them scripts even though they're not really SQL scripts,
they're C Sharp code.
But you can generate SQL scripts from them.
The Entity Framework keeps track of which ones have been applied to a database,
which new ones need to be applied, and then what order they need to be applied.
It takes care of all that for you to a table that's hidden inside
of database called underscore Migration History.
It will be a system table in your database.
But at this point, what has happened is that we have changed the definition of review.
We really need to update the database to get that in sync.
So let me run Update-Database-Verbose again and you'll see in the output
that the Entity Framework automatically applied an alter table RestaurantReviews
to add ReviewerName to the table.
So that's what I could've generated as an explicit Migration
that would come out in the C Sharp code style.
But since I have the Automatic Migrations enabled,
I just let the Entity Framework take care of that.
And if I wanted to actually have a name in there for this particular review,
I could always say ReviewerName equal Scott.
Run update database again and it will run that seed method,
that value Scott should be put into the database.
And now, one more thing to know about, you might have noticed that when we added ReviewerName,
it was added as in nvarchar(max) field.
That may not be what you want.
You might want to restrict that field to a specific lane.
But I'm going to defer that discussion till the next module when we start talking
about data annotations because we can change that through a data annotation.
In fact, we can change nearly everything that the Entity Framework is doing to the database
in some fashion either through attributes or through some explicit code.
But for our application, we're just going to move ahead.
We've seen just enough to know how to use Entity Framework,
how to use Entity Framework Migrations.
And we have an application that's up and running that's displaying restaurants
that are coming from a table in SQL Server.