We now have a working database in our project and we will be using LINQ statements
to query the data in that database.
LINQ stands for Language Integrated Query.
And I want you to know about two different styles of queries that you can write with LINQ.
The first style looks almost like a query you would write
with structured query language against SQL Server.
One difference you'll notice that might jump out immediately though is that select appears
at the end of the statement, unlike in Structured Query Language
where you begin the query with a select.
These LINQ queries are going to be strongly typed.
That is the Compiler and Visual Studio, they know about the types
of objects you're querying against.
So if you change something in a class, you can end up with compiler areas in your queries
because the compiler will know exactly what is inside of those objects.
This particular query is what we call the Comprehension Query Syntax.
It starts with a from keyword to specify where the data is coming from
and it introduces a range variable.
In this case, the name of the range variable is r. You can use that throughout the rest
of the query when you want to do filtering, grouping, joining, and projecting.
There are keywords in C Sharp to let you do the filtering, grouping, joining, and projecting.
Keywords like where, and orderby, and select.
That's just a subset of the available keywords.
In this example, we're taking our restaurants,
filtering out so we only have the restaurants that have a country of USA.
We're going to order them by their names and that's an ascending order by default
and then select the entire Restaurant.
We're not doing a projection into some smaller set of data.
The job of the Entity Framework then is to take this query and translate it
into an efficient query for the database, then execute that query
and bring you back objects, actual restaurant objects.
But you can also express this query a second way.
This query is using extension method and lambda expressions.
The first part of this query would produce the exact same results as the query above.
We want restaurants whose country is equal to a specific value,
and we want them ordered by name.
But when you use this syntax, there are some additional operators that you can use.
For instance, Skip and Take.
They're quite commonly used when you want to do paging operations.
I want to skip the first ten results because they're on the first page.
I want to take the next ten results because I'm going
to display the second page of results to users.
There's no C Sharp keywords to express those operators
so you'll always see those invoked as extension methods.
There are dozens of LINQ operators available.
If you want to explore the syntax and the possibilities,
then you can look for 101 LINQ Samples on MSDN.
These samples are available on both C Sharp and Visual Basic.
You can also download a free utility called LINQPad.
It comes with hundreds of samples and you can write LINQ queries
in an interactive manner and try them out immediately.
Also, if you're a Pluralsight subscriber, I have a few courses devoted to LINQ.
Well let's try out a few different queries inside of our application.
Inside the application, we're displaying a list of restaurants now on the home page
but they're obviously not in alphabetical order.
So let's try to fix that by changing the query
around in the index action of the HomeController.
I'm going to switch over to using the comprehension query syntax for a bit
and say from r, where r is my range variable, it represents a restaurant
because I'm going to say from r in db.restaurants.
Let's OrderBy r. Name.
By default, this will be ascending, you can explicitly specify that using the keyword.
You could also specify descending but we'll stick with ascending for right now
and just select the entire restaurant.
Just by putting that change in the code, if I refresh, we should now be getting Great Lakes
on top of the list which we do, so that's good.
But we could do some more fancier ordering.
Let me try to arrange these windows so we can see everything.
And now let's say that we want to display the restaurants but perhaps we want
to display the most popular restaurants at the top.
And perhaps one way to measure the popularity of a restaurant is
to see how many times it's been reviewed.
So we'll order by r.Reviews.Count descending, so the one with the most review should be here
at the top and that's going to be our restaurant in Sweden, if I refresh.
And now that appears to work too.
And behind the scenes, the Entity Framework is taking this query and translating it
into a query for SQL Server then it executes that query and brings back a result set
from SQL Server but transforms that result set into real objects,
into real restaurants that I can use in C Sharp code.
And you can see the query we have now is a bit of a mix.
It is in the comprehension query syntax but there's a little bit of extension method
in here too because we need to count the reviews.
And there's no keyword in C Sharp to say count.
Now maybe someone discovers that the restaurants coming to the top are restaurants
that have a lot of reviews but they're all negative reviews.
So what we'd really like to do is order by the average review and find
out what the best restaurants are.
So there I could say r.Reviews, please give me an average, compute an average.
And for the average extension method to work, I need to pass in a lambda expression
that tells the Entity Framework which property I want to average.
So given a review, please average Review.rating,
and we'll still specify this in descending order.
And if I do a build and refresh, you can see now we have a relatively complicated query going on,
still going to produce the same result though
because we only have one restaurant with reviews in the database.
And actually this query is quite mild in complexity compared to some
of the LINQ queries I've worked with in the past.
But let me show you one more thing.
Suppose that in addition to displaying the restaurant name, city and country,
we also want to display how many reviews that we have for that restaurant.
There's a couple different ways to do that but I want to show you one of the most performant way
and also a popular approach to this.
And that is if the view needs to know all this information including the number of reviews
and perhaps the model that we build for should include the number of reviews.
So I'm going to do a projection and not just hand back a list of restaurants to view,
it could use that list of restaurants to compute the number of reviews for each restaurant.
But I'm going to do a transformation.
Let's say give me a new object that includes r.Id, r.Name, r.City, r.Country,
and also a new property NumberOfReviews equals r.Reviews.Count
and just put my missing comma in here.
This is creating a new anonymous type that has properties named ID, Name, City and Country.
The C Sharp compiler will just give it those property names
if you don't specify something equals.
And we're also adding in this NumberOfReviews equals r.Reviews.Count.
I could take this and still pass it to my View.
But being an anonymously typed object, we have the problem
that we don't know its name, it's anonymous.
What would I put as a strongly typed model directive here?
Well, what I could do instead is create a new model.
I'll call it a View Model because it's dedicated to this View.
So, let's create a class called RestaurantListViewModel and I'm going
to give it those properties that we need.
I'll just paste in that code to give it the properties that I need: ID,
Name, City, Country, CountOfReviews.
And now, I'll use this class when I'm building a model.
Select new RestaurantListViewModel, ID equals r.Id, Name equals r.Name, City equals r.City,
Country equals r.Country and CountOfReviews will be equal to r.Reviews.Count.
So this is an entity that I've created, something that I'll add as a DbSet
to my DbContext to save in the database.
It's what I call a View Model, it's something that is going to carry the information along
that the View needs to display and respond to this request.
So let me take this class and we will open up the Index View for the HomeController
and we'll change the model from being Restaurant to being a RestaurantListViewModel.
And now one of the pieces of information that we can add here would include item.CountOfReviews.
Let me save everything and do a Build and refresh our home page,
and now we're getting a little more insight into each restaurant,
a little more information out here.
View models, by the way, are a topic that we will return to talk about again.
They're quite useful because, very often, a page that you need
to display requires more information that one of your entities can have.
So you need to aggregate some information from a couple different places,
a couple different sources, wrap it all up into one object to hand over to the view
so it can do its job very efficiently.
And it's very easy to build a View Model.
You can do a projection with the select operator.
You can use a framework like AutoMapper.
AutoMapper is very good at copying data from one object into another object.
But what I want to focus on is just to show you that in addition
to using this pretty comprehension query syntax,
it's entirely legal and we can see it works well.
We could rate the same query using extension methods.
So I could say model equals db.Restaurants.
and let's do the OrderBy.
Now I need to pass a lambda expression to specify how to OrderBy.
So I'll say given a restaurant r, r goes to r.Reviews.average,
I need another lambda expression here that says given a review called review,
make you sure you average review.rating.
And in this case, to make this descending, what I should really invoke is not OrderBy,
I should invoke OrderByDescending into different extension method,
different LINQ operator that's available.
And now we just need to select.
I could say select, given a restaurant r, r goes to and let me try to save myself some typing,
I'm going to take this bit of code, new RestaurantListViewModel and try to paste it
into my Select statement here and highlight this, Control K, Control U to uncomment
and then close things off with a parenthesis and semicolon.
Control K, Control D to do some formatting which didn't really work in this case.
Sometimes it's not quite smart enough to know how you wanted something formatted.
I'll just select everything, tab this over.
But that is the equivalent query in the comprehension syntax.
There is no reason to choose these based on performance.
It's really which syntax do you like better and what operators do you need
because again some operators like Take and Skip,
you can only invoke them using this extension method syntax.
So I could say just give me the first ten restaurants that are in the database.
And if I do a Build right now and refresh, we should get the same result
because we have the exact same query that we had before.
And now, the one scenario we haven't looked at quite yet is filtering.
Let's look at that next.