Let's adds some filtering to our query with a where clause.
But instead of using a where operator, in a hard coded value like I did in the slide
that introduced you to LINQ, let me add a parameter because a user might come
to the home page searching for a specific restaurant.
So we will allow them to enter a searchTerm and I'll provide a default value of this for null,
which is slightly redundant because if the MVC runtime doesn't find a searchTerm
in the request, it will pass along a null for the string parameter.
But there is a unit testing project in this solution that is invoking the index action
and the unit test and it's not passing any parameters.
So I'm just going to provide a default value here
so that the compiler will be happy with that unit test.
And now we can use that with a Where operator.
I can say Where, given a restaurant r, r goes to and then we can check a searchTerm equals null.
If searchTerm equals null, everything will be true, we want all the restaurants,
we're not searching for any specific restaurant or r.Name starts
with whatever searchTerm was entered.
And now if I do a Build and refresh the Home application, we'll have the same result so far
because we didn't enter a searchTerm but I just want to verify
that it still works and it looks like it does.
And now I can come up here and say searchTerm equals S, and now we just get the restaurants
that starts with an S. So that looks good but of course the user might not know
to enter something in the query string.
How can we provide a bit of a user interface that allows them to do some filtering?
That will require a modification to the index view.
So lets' come in here and up above the list of cities, let's add a form.
Now, I could add this form using HTML.begin form but there's no real special parameters
that I need this form to have, so I'm just going to type in a form tag.
I do want to change one thing about the default though, the default method.
I want that to issue a get request but I don't need to specify a parameter for action.
If there's no action there, it's just going to go back to the URL it came from which is perfect
because we can show the index view, the user can type something in, hit the submit button
and will go right back to where we came from which is the index action of the HomeController.
I'll explain why I used the get method in just a second.
But let's have an input type equals submit, value equals Search By Name.
That will be the button that the user clicks when they want to do the search
and then we'll have an input type equals search and that is
where they can type in to perform the search.
And, of course, we'll have to give this a name
and remember ASP.NET MVC matches things up in the request by name.
Because we have a searchTerm parameter on the index action, I would want the name of this
to match, so the name of this should be searchTerm.
So let's save everything.
Do a build just to be safe and refresh the application to see what this looks like.
And it's not the optimum user interface but it should be functional.
If I go in and type a G and click Search
By Name then you'll notice we get the right result, we get Great Lake.
You can see in the query string, we have searchTerm equals G. And the reason that is
in the query string is because our form method equals get.
When you click on a submit button for a form that does a get request,
it has to wrap up all these input values and put them in the query string.
If instead we had used post and done a submit, all these values would be inside
that it should be message body, you wouldn't see them in the query string.
It's nice to use a get request here because by putting these things in the query string,
someone can copy this and paste it into an e-mail or they can bookmark it,
and they can always come back to this page and see all of the restaurants that start with a G
or an S or whatever they're looking for.
You do have to be careful about when you use get because you wouldn't want to use a get request
for a form that is submitting information to the server to save in the database,
so something that is processing a credit card or creating a restaurant
or editing a review, those are all post operations.
Post operations are write operations.
A search is a read operation.
It's perfectly safe to issue a get request or a search request.