In this module, we took our first steps with the Entity Framework.
We let it take our C Sharp classes and not only save objects in the database
but we also let it create the database for us.
This was all done using the DbSet and DbContext classes of the Entity Framework.
We also used EF Migrations to seed the database
with some initial restaurants and manage the schema.
Finally, I showed you a few different LINQ queries to give you an idea of what is possible
when querying a database with the Entity Framework.
In the next module, we're going to build on what we learned here to look at editing
and inserting data along with all the features you need in those scenarios,
features like validation and from the error messages.