Hi, this is Scott Allen and this module looks at test-driven development
and unit testing with the "ASP.NET MVC Framework".
In this module, I want to show you how to use test-driven development
to drive the design of a feature.
We'll look at the TDD cycle, which is red, green, re-factor.
First, you write a failing test which gives you a red result in the "Test Runner".
Then you make the test pass, which gives you a green result.
And then you re-factor the code to improve the design.
I'm also going to demonstrate how to unit test controllers, and how to build test doubles
to control the environment the controller executes inside of when we test them.
( Silence )