To give you some idea of the test-driven development flow, we're going to step away
from the web project for a bit and focus on the test project.
If you remember, in the first module of this course when we created the application,
we also created a unit testing project.
We can run tests inside of this project using the "Test Menu"
or by using the "Control-R A" shortcut key.
"Visual Studio" will find all of the test classes inside this project
and run the test methods.
We currently have a failing test, and if you look at the problem here by clicking
on the test, and down here at the bottom of the test explorer,
it will show you the exception that happened.
You'll see there was an exception because the "Home Controller" tries to talk to the database,
but it doesn't find the connection string that it's looking for,
and this test is envoking the "Home Controller Index Action".
We have that connection string defined in the web application,
so the web application works just fine when we view the app with a browser,
but the tests are failing because we haven't configured this properly yet.
We're going to defer this problem and come back later.
And I'll show you a couple approaches you can use for testing controllers that need data.
For right now, I just want to focus on what it would look like to try test-driven development.
I encourage you to try test-driven development, and write unit tests
because I personally have found them
to be the most beneficial practice I have ever followed in my career.
And the one secret to this is that tests are just as much about design
as they are about insuring quality.
Let me show you what I mean.
To get ready to implement this feature,
I've already added a "Features" folder into my "Unit Tests" project.
All I need to do is right-click this and say "Add a Unit Test".
It's called "Unit Test One.cs".
We can change the name later.
For now, I'm going to paste in some comments that I jotted down as I was talking
to the business people about this feature.
It turns out that they want to try at least two different approaches
and see which one works the best.
One approach to calculating the overall rating for a restaurant would be
to just take the simple average of the rating property for the last N number of reviews
where N is something an administrator can configure,
so it might be the last 10 reviews or the last 100 reviews.
Another approach would be to compute a weighted mean
where the most recent reviews are more heavily weighted.
That would benefit a restaurant that is improving
after a bad start and getting better reviews.
It might also benefit a customer who is thinking about going to a restaurant that used
to have great quality, but is now on the decline.
I like starting with some comments inside of my test file,
just so I can refer to them and think about them.
They usually describe the business scenario that I'm trying to solve.
I don't use the TDD approach for all of the code I write, but this represents the type
of scenario where I probably would use TDD.
I'm not sure how to design this feature, and test-driven development is a great design tool.
I can delete the comments when I'm done, but for right now it provides me something concrete
that I can look at and remember the goal, and I can start thinking about a solution and thinking
about how I'd implement this feature.
"Visual Studio" has already given me a test class.
It has a method inside of it, "Test Method One".
The first thing you might try to do is give this class and method a more descriptive name,
but don't get too caught up on naming right away.
My idea is that I want to use "Visual Studio" like I used
to use a whiteboard before I started test-driven development.
Someone would give me a software requirement, and I'd go to the whiteboard and start trying
to diagram out some classes and methods that I think I would need.
I'm going to do that in "Visual Studio" instead because "Visual Studio" gives me a compiler,
and I can use tests to validate that the code works.
And since I'm not sure what direction I'm going just yet,
there's no need to spend time thinking of names.
Once I've figured that out, we can rename things later.
I do know I'm going to be working with some data, some restaurant data,
and we already have that restaurant class defined.
I just need to pull in the name space "Ode to Food.models",
and my restaurant will have some reviews associated with it, and I need to bring
in the name space for "List of T", which is "system.collections.generic".
And once I have that, I'm ready to add some reviews to this restaurant.
I'll just add a single review, and I think the only thing that we're going to care
about for the purposes of these tests is that a review has a rating.
In this case, we'll just have a single review, keep things very simple; the rating is a four.
That's the data I want to evaluate.
And now I can start thinking about the API that I want to use to compute the restaurant rating.
This would be the point where I could experiment with different class names and method names
until I found something that looks like it might work.
And let's say I reach the point where I've decided
that I think a restaurant rater might work,
so I will create a restaurant rater and pass the data into it.
And, of course, this code doesn't compile, but I don't expect it to yet.
Remember, this is just a whiteboard.
In fact, one of the first steps that you'll take many times
with test-driven development is writing some code that doesn't even compile yet.
The goal is to go and do the simplest possible thing to get it
to compile once you're relatively happy with the names and the design.
Next, I might say that this rater -- I can tell it to compute a rating given some number
that it will use to determine how many reviews to use, so let's say 10 reviews,
and it will give me back some sort of result.
Again, this is the time where I am exploring how I want to invoke these API's,
and what these API's should look like.
What parameters do I want to pass?
What do I want to name things?
And forging ahead with what I have so far, I'm thinking that if I tell this
to compute the result for a restaurant with a single review,
and we're doing just the simple averaging for right now, I should be able to write an assert
at this point, and assert that four would be the "result.rating".
At this point, if I tried to do a build or run the test, it's going to fail miserably
because we don't compile, but I can use "Visual Studio" to help me create the classes.
Just put the cursor on "Restaurant Rater", open the drop-down list with "Control-Period",
and let's generate a class from "Restaurant Rater"
that will create a new ".cs" file in this project.
Ultimately, it's going to need to be in the "Ode to Food" project because it's going
to be business logic that we need to exercise from the web application,
but leaving it in here is fine for right now.
I haven't solidified anything yet; things might change.
At some point, the design will start to firm up and I can move these ".cs" files
into the right project, and then adjust the name spaces accordingly.
My next compiler error is that the "Restaurant Rater" needs a constructor
that takes some restaurant information.
Again, I can generate this from "Visual Studio", just "Control-Period",
and select the entry "Generate Constructor Stub".
That should be there now.
It's going to need a method called "Compute Rating".
I will also generate that.
And let's look at what we've developed so far in side of "Restaurant Rater".
We have a "Public Constructor" that takes a restaurant that seems good.
Let's get rid of the spurious name space here by deleting that and bringing in a using statement
for "Ode to Food.models", and then I can delete that here also,
just trying to clean up the code already.
I should really wait until I have a passing test, and then come in and do changes like this.
That would be the re-factoring step.
This "Compute Rating" method, I believe, will ultimately return some sort of rating result.
Let's create that, generate a class for "Rating Result".
So it's not going to return "Object"; it's going to return a rating result,
and we don't need this exception here.
What I could do, the simplest possible thing to make this work,
would be to just return a new rating result, not even do any calculations just yet.
And are we ready to build?
Not quite yet.
It looks like my "Rating Result" needs a rating property,
and my "Compute Rating" method needs to be public.
So let's come in and change this.
This is a public method, and "Rating Result" will ultimately be a public class,
and it's going to have a "Property of Type Integer" that is the rating.
I know this is an integer because the business specifically asked me
to make ratings an integer value so we don't have ratings like seven point six six six
that scare users; that would just be a seven or an eight.
And at this point, I think, I can do a build.
Build succeeded.
I'll run all the tests with "Control-R A", and of course, our new test method fails.
We told it that it should be expecting a four result; the actual result it got back
from "Result.rating" was a zero because we haven't done any calculations.
And this is the first step in TDD.
I've designed some classes, designed some methods.
I now have a failing test.
My next goal is to do the simplest possible thing that will make that test pass,
and the absolute simplest possible thing would be to say --
let's say that the result equals a new rating result, "'Result.rating' equals four".
"Return Result", run the tests, now "Test Method One" passes.
And you might look at that and say, "It's completely ridiculous.
You're hard-coding computations just to make the test pass."
However, stick with me on this.
One of the tenets of doing test-driven development is to do the simplest possible thing
to make a test pass, and then you just keep adding tests that will test more conditions.
You're going to have to come in and change this "Compute Rating" code
so it actually behaves correctly.
But along the way, as you're making these changes, you're going to be writing tests
that validate scenarios that are going to prove very valuable later on.
They're going to make sure that you're making the right changes, that as you're adding things
and adding features and reconstructing the code,
that you're not breaking anything that used to work.
That's one of the real values of having tests.
And once you have a passing test, one of the first things you'll want to do is come in
and re-factor, clean code up, make sure things are named properly.
I don't really like the "To-Do" statement here.
In fact, I don't really like having a data field in here when this is really a restaurant.
And I can use "Visual Studio", "Control-Period", to say,
"Rename data to restaurant everywhere," And that fixes things up for me.
I also want this to be called "Restaurant".
Same trick here, "Control-Period", it will rename the local use
of that restaurant variable, also, this "P parameter", no idea what that means,
so let's just change it right away to "Number of Reviews".
That's what it's supposed to be, ultimately.
And now I'll hit "Control-R", "Control-A" again.
Test method is still passing.
My changes haven't broken anything.
Those are very simple changes, but you can imagine, as things build up in complexity,
you change things in one place it breaks something somewhere else.
That's a sign that the tests are helping you, and also that you might have a design issue.
Maybe something is too coupled to another class.
But now that we've seen a basic test in action, I'm going to accelerate things a bit,
and work through the rest of the design and implementation of this feature.
( Silence )