I've added a second test to the "Test Fixture".
This one passes in two "Restaurant Reviews" to the "Restaurant Rater".
Since the code is starting to take some form, I've also given the tests some names,
"Computes Result for One Review", and "Computes Results for Two Reviews".
I've also changed the implementation inside of the "Restaurant Rater".
The simplest possible thing I've found to work is a very simple link statement.
It averages the reviews.
The good news is both of the tests now pass and I'm in a re-factoring stage.
I think the "Restaurant Rater" is in good shape so far.
It's actually the tests that are bothering me.
One thing you'll learn about unit testing in general is that the tests are just
as important as the application code.
And it bothers me that I have so much setup work inside of each test to make a restaurant
and make the reviews for that restaurant, so in this re-factoring phase,
I'm going to re-factor the tests to make the setup a little bit easier.
( Silence )
What I've done to re-factor the tests is to add a method, a private method,
named "Build Restaurants and Reviews".
This is not a test method that the "Test Runner" will invoke to see if something passes or fails.
It doesn't have a "Test Method Attribute".
This is a helper method I can use for my other tests, to keep them simple.
When you look at a test, it's a little easier to see that "Arrange, Act,
Assert" pattern that we talked about in the introduction to this course.
This new method takes a variable number of integer parameters, and uses some link operators
to transform the integers into a list of reviews.
Those reviews are attached to the restaurant.
We just return the "Restaurant" then.
I can use this method in my tests by either creating an array of integers and passing them
into this method, as we did here with the values four and eight, or I can use the params ability
of "C Sharp" to just pass them in one by one.
And now I'm feeling a bit better about these tests.
They look a little bit cleaner, and both the tests are still passing, which is good.
For the next step, I might want to start to test boundary conditions.
What happens when we rate a restaurant with zero reviews,
or if we rate a restaurant that has a negative review?
Should we throw exceptions?
How do we deal with odd numbers?
Those would all be good tests to write, but I'm sure I can come up with an implementation
to satisfy all those odd scenarios.
They don't feel like they'd be high risk or difficult to implement.
And at this early point, I'm really trying to focus on design issues first because, remember,
TDD is primarily about design, and if I look at these requirements again,
they say we have to support at least two different types of averaging.
There's the simple average and the weighted average, and the business people also hinted
that there might be more in the future.
They want to try, and experiment, and find out what will work the best.
I want to see what happens if I introduce the second form of averaging,
and see how it impacts my design.
( Silence )
I have now added a new test, the "Test the Weighted Average of Two Reviews".
Remember, the requirements also said I need to weight the most recent reviews twice
as heavily as the oldest reviews.
And we haven't worked with review dates.
We haven't sorted anything yet, but in the future, again, I know I can write some tests
to make sure that the reviews are properly sorted before I compute the rating.
I can do that later.
Sorting is another implementation detail I know I can figure out,
and I'm not finished writing tests yet but I am still focused on design.
In this weighting test, the rating for a restaurant with review ratings of three
and nine is five because the value three is more heavily weighted than the value nine.
It comes before the value nine in order.
I've put together a quick and dirty implementation that will pass the test, and,
of course, I did this after I watched the test fail.
And this is what the implementation looks like.
I'm not in the re-factoring phase again.
I just want to show you some of the things
that tests will make you think about, for instance, rounding.
Right now, I'm truncating the average rating,
so the link statement computes the average rating and casts the result to an int.
The weighted average also performs division
between two integer values, which will result in truncation.
So the question is, is truncating the right behavior?
This is one of those scenarios that tests will make you think about, and many times you'll need
to go back to the business people and ask for clarification.
All I know so far is that they told me that the rating should be a whole number like six
or seven so I need to clarify the exact behavior.
Do I need to round?
Do I need to truncate?
Once I have an answer, I can write the tests that make sure that the rounding
or the truncating happens correctly.
But for right now, I still want to think about high level design issues,
and come back to handling simple averages versus weighted averages.
One thing that bothers me about this "Restaurant Rater" right now is how it is responsible
for computing a simple rating, which I would probably rename if it was going
to stay here, and computing a weighted rate.
But I know, based on my notes, that this is an area where I can anticipate change.
The business is going to want to add new algorithms, and change algorithms all the time
in search for something that works the best.
If we had to go into the "Restaurant Rater" and add a new method every time the business came
up with a new algorithm, I think that would make things difficult to change.
I want to make things easy to change, make them as easy as possible.
Let me do a bit more re-factoring, and I'll see if I can make it easy
to change algorithms while still having my tests pass.
It's wonderful having these passing tests now because I can rip code apart,
rebuild everything, and my tests will tell me if I did anything wrong.
( Silence )
I've done a bit more re-factoring, and I've decided that the
"Restaurant Rater" should not be responsible for computing the actual result.
You'll notice the class is much smaller now.
Instead of computing the result directly, the rater is going to rely on an algorithm
that is passed in and abstracted behind an interface definition.
The interface definition is "I-Rating algorithm", and it looks like this.
Any object that implements this interface you can call
"Compute on" and pass in a list of reviews.
It will then return the proper new rating result.
I've made two concrete implementations of this interface.
They're both in the same file.
That's something that I'd want to change later on, move these classes
to their own files perhaps, but we can worry about that later.
The first implementation performs a "Simple Averaging of Reviews".
The second implementation performs a "Weighted Averaging of the Reviews".
You might have noticed that the code inside the algorithms is the same code I had before inside
of the "Restaurant Rater" itself, so I just moved code around.
I took code out of the "Restaurant Rater" and pasted it into these algorithm classes.
Is that good?
I think so, because it's assigning specific responsibilities to different classes now.
I now have algorithms that are dedicated to and focused on computing a rating result,
and I have a "Restaurant Rater" that is now going to be focused on coordinating all
of the pieces together needed to produce that result.
And now when a client needs to determine a rating, like if we looked inside
of our tests now, we don't need to figure out which method to call on the "Restaurant Rater".
We always call "Compute Result", but we pass
in the algorithm that's required to perform the computation.
This is the Strategy Design pattern for you pattern fans out there.
What's important about this pattern is how I can now introduce new algorithms
without changing any of the code inside the "Restaurant Rater" or inside
of any of the existing algorithms.
I've made the system much easier to extend, and we should be able to keep
up with all the changes that the business wants to introduce in this area as they experiment
with different ways to rate restaurants.
All I need to do is write a class that implements "I-Rating algorithm".
The good news is, after I've ripped all this code apart, all of the tests still pass,
so I know I haven't broken anything.
And you might be wondering, if all I did was move code around,
then why couldn't I just call this algorithm directly instead
of going through this rater class?
If I'm a client, like our unit tests are clients for this code,
why do I instantiate a "Restaurant Rater" and call "Compute Rate"?
Why don't I just instantiate an algorithm and call "Compute Rate"?
And the answer is that we haven't given the "Restaurant Rater" all
of the responsibilities it needs to take care of just yet.
Let me write another test and come right back.
I've written a new test, this one to make sure that the
"Restaurant Rater" only uses the top N number of reviews in the calculation.
To test this scenario, I've built a restaurant with six reviews, one, one, one followed by 10,
10, 10, and I expect if I tell the rater to only use the first three reviews,
it should produce an average of one.
If I run the tests with this new test in place, I'll discover that this test fails
because I haven't implemented the logic for this to work yet.
Let me go into the "Restaurant Rater", and get a list of filtered reviews.
And I think what I can do is just take "Restaurant.reviews", and take the first number
of reviews to use, and that should satisfy the logic.
This should make the test pass, but let me do a "Filtered Reviews.to List", run the test again,
and I can see that that test now passes.
And now you can see that the "Restaurant Rater" is going to have a purpose in life.
It's going to massage the data, and set everything
up properly so the algorithm can work.
It's still the algorithm that does the computations and leaves us open
to extending the software with new algorithms.
And at this point, I'm sure we could think of many more tests to write.
We could write tests that check for rounding errors and truncating errors,
tests for restaurants with no reviews,
tests to make sure the reviews are sorted properly, and the list goes on.
I'm not going to write those tests for you in this video.
I'll leave that as an exercise for you.
Instead, we're going to move on and look at more MVC-specific issues around unit testing.
But the goal of this was that I hope I've shown you some of the benefits
of test-first development and how to apply TDD.
It has a real learning curve.
You need to keep trying, and then learning, and then trying again.
You might think this example was too simplistic, but I assure you that after many years
of doing this if you can make your code easy to test, like in this example,
and there's always a way to make code easier to test, then you're going to have success,
not only with test-driven development but also
in writing maintainable code and building software.
( Silence )