When you are unit testing an "ASP.NET MVC" application,
you'll probably want to unit test your controllers.
And one of the first decisions you'll need to make is if you want to isolate your controllers
from infrastructure-related services that they use, like web services or mail servers, or,
in the case of our application, a database.
There are two ways we could go.
We could write unit tests that hit the controllers,
and the controllers go against the database.
This is perfectly reasonable for some people.
Other people think it is an atrocity.
I just want to let you know there is some debate on this topic.
The problem with writing unit tests against your controllers when your controllers need
to access a database is that the unit tests can run a little bit slower,
and in unit testing you generally want the test to run as fast as possible.
But there's actually a bigger problem, and that's usually setup.
Because you are writing tests, you want the controllers to behave predictably,
and that means you need predictable data.
So you need to make sure the database is set up, it has the right data in it,
there's nothing new there that could break a test.
In the long run, this can actually end up being a lot of work.
I would suggest if you go down this path,
you might look at an embedded database like "Sequel Server Compact".
With the "Entity Framework", you can point the connection string to a Sequel compact database,
and it can be a little bit easier to work with compared to a real Sequel server.
But "Sequel Compact" doesn't support all the queries, and features that regular
"Sequel Server" supports, so you can still run into a little trouble,
in which case you might stick with a real Sequel server, but your tests are going to be slower.
I want to show you how to isolate your controllers
from the database using a simple approach, the simplest approach I can come up with.
Right now, a test for the home controller is failing
because the entity framework is running inside,
and it's looking for a database connection string.
It's the index test, and the exception that's being thrown is
"no connection string named default connection can be found in the application config file."
If I want this test to pass, I can set up a real database for my unit test to use,
or I can remove the database from the application when it's under test.
And removing the database usually involves some sort of interface definition.
Let me show you how this works.
First, we'll have an interface "IO Defu DB" (phonetic).
This will represent all the operations that I want to do against a real database.
Not everything is there yet.
All we have so far is just a "Query of T" method.
I want to be able to query different objects, restaurants and reviews.
The "Ode to Food DB" class that we've been using all along now implements "IO Defu DB".
It implements that query method explicitly, meaning you can only get to this query method
through an "IO Defu DB" reference.
All this method needs to do is turn around and call into the DB context that it derives from.
There's a set method on that DB context that would essentially be asking
for the queryable set of entities.
So if someone wants a query of "Restaurant", all we need to do is turn around
and return a set of "Restaurant".
Then inside the "Home Controller", I can have it work against an
"IO Defu DB" reference instead of a real "Ode to Food DB".
At runtime, when it's actually running on a web server, we'll give it a real "Ode to Food DB",
so when it says "DB.query Restaurants",
that'll actually be something that goes to "Sequel Server".
But when it's under test, the beautiful thing about an interface is the
"Home Controller" really doesn't know what it's talking to, and under test we can have
"IO Defu DB" point to something that just contains some in-memory data.
We do just have to make a couple changes to the "Home Controller".
One is that we can no longer say, "DB.restaurants".
Now we have to say, "I want to query restaurant," and we'll need to do
that in two places, once in the "Auto-Complete" and once in the "Index".
The other change that we'll have to make is that when the controller is constructed,
we'll need to initialize this to point to something.
When we're in a test, we want it to point to something fake that the test passes in.
When we're not in a test, we want it to use a real "Ode to Food DB".
For right now, let me just define two constructors, one default constructor
that will initialize this to the "Ode to Food DB" that we've always been using,
and another constructor where you will pass in an "IO Defu DB", and we'll just assign it.
That'll give a unit test a chance to pass in something for the "Home Controller" to use
that looks like a real database but it isn't.
And with that in place, what I can do inside of the test now
when we're arranging this controller, I can set up a fake database.
So I could say, "DB equals New, Fake Ode Defu DB".
This is a class that I've already written.
What it does is simply implement the "IO Defu DB" interface.
And behind the scenes there's just in-memory data.
It's not the prettiest code in the world with all the generics,
but essentially behind the scenes there's a dictionary of type.
So when you want to query "Restaurant", we'll pull out a bunch of "Restaurant" out of
that dictionary, something that's I-queryable, and hand it over to you.
And there's a method here called "Add Set", which allows you to program the restaurants
that you want inside of this "Fake Ode Defu" database.
In fact, I've already defined a class, "Test Data" that has some restaurants
that it just conjures up in-memory.
So 100 restaurants, every restaurant has a review with a rating of four.
And inside the "Home Controller" tests, what I can do is initialize the database with that,
to add a set from "Test Data.restaurants", and I can use that "Test Data.restaurant" over
and over again for all the controllers that need to query restaurant information.
And now when I construct the "Home Controller", I don't want it to use the real database.
I want it to use that fake in-memory database.
Just with those changes, let's run the test again and see what happens.
And now the index method is still failing, but it's a different exception now.
The exception now is because of our call to "Is Ajacks (phonetic) Request".
We've run into trouble with this before, but I've been leaving it in the
"Home Controller" just to make a point, and that is there's nowhere else in the application
where we have actually gone up to an "HCDP Context Object" or messed with the query string
or cookies or anything like that.
And for the most part, with "ASP.NET MVC", you don't need to do any of those things.
But when you do, you can almost be certain
that it will make the tests a little bit harder to write.
To this "Call to Request.is Ajacks Request",
what's happening behind the scenes is it's looking at the HCDP request.
Well, there isn't one; it sees a NULL reference somewhere, and an exception gets thrown.
Fortunately, with "ASP.net" MVC, there is a way to work around this.
And I have another class defined, if we come over here into the test project.
It is a "Fake Controller Context".
A "Fake Controller Context" is something we'll assign to the controller
and give it a "Fake HCDP Context".
A "Fake HCTP Context", then, is going to have a "Fake Request Object",
and this "Fake Request Object", again, really doesn't do anything,
just returns nulls, just returns empty collections.
All of this is just here so that we don't get that exception.
Very simple implementation, but it's a lot of code just to have that one call inside
of the index method to check if it's an "Ajacks Request".
And using these classes, what I can do is come back into the test and ALSO TELL the controller
that its controller context is going to be a "Fake Controller Context".
And now let's run this test one more time.
It's still going to fail, but at least we've gotten to the "Assert" statement.
The "Assert" is failing because we no longer put a message in the VIEW BAG that says,
"Modify this template to jump-start your MVC application."
We've changed it and gotten away from that starter template,
so this "Assert" really isn't valid anymore.
But now what could we assert.
We just fed the "Home Controller" a fake data source that has 100 restaurants in it.
We only want 10 on the home page, so maybe what I should do is look at the model that's in this
"View Result" and assert that we have 10 restaurants inside of it.
Remember, our "Home Controller" should be returning a sequence
of "Restaurant List View Model".
So what I could say here is that I expect to have an I-numerable
of "Restaurant List View Model", that's my model, and it's equal to "Resolve.model",
which is typed as "Object" because "View Result" really doesn't know what type
of model you're going to have, so if I just do some type coercion here,
then my code should be happy and, now I could write an assert like,
"Assert that R equal 10 is the number of those items in the model."
And finally, run the test one more time, and finally,
we have a passing test that's actually testing something that we want.
And this is the kind of path that you'll go down if you want to isolate your controllers
from actual infrastructure things, program to interfaces, have fake or stub
or mock implementations of those interfaces for your tests.
And we can build a whole course around the best testing strategies, and fakes versus mocks.
In fact, you'll find those courses on "Pluralsight"
if you're a "Pluralsight" subscriber.
I'm just trying to give you a sample of what this would look like.
( Silence )