Let's see what it would look like to test the "Create" action of the "Restaurant Controller".
Here are two tests with less than 10 lines of code for each test.
The first test wants to make sure a controller saves a restaurant when the restaurant is valid.
The second test wants to make sure we do not save a restaurant
when the model state is invalid.
Both of these tests use our fake database to make it easy to test.
In the scenario where there is an error, we set up "Model State" to look like validation failed.
I can do that by adding a model error to "Model State".
You can call "Add Model Error" to simulate an error condition.
You can also call "Add Model Error" inside of "Controller"
if you wanted a real error condition that would display to the user.
But I will point out that you need to be careful.
If you're calling "Add Model Error" a lot in your controllers,
it might mean that your controllers have too many validation responsibilities,
and validation is generally a responsibility you can assign elsewhere.
In this application, we're using validation attributes,
but you could also have a model validate itself.
Once we call the "Create Action", we'll make sure nothing was added to the
"Added" collection of our fake database.
And this demonstrates how fakes have a different purpose than real objects.
Fakes should make things easy to test, perhaps even adding additional properties and methods
to figure out how the object was used by the code under test.
In the "Create Scenario", where we want the "Create" to work,
we can make sure our restaurant was added to the database by asserting that "Added.count is equal
to one", and also check the saved property of the fake database
to ensure the controller called "Save Changes", which will save everything.
Obviously, the fake database has some additional features now for the "Create" scenario
to be testable like this, so let's see what they are.
We'll start with the interface definition.
This interface definition now contains everything
that we currently need to do against the database.
We can query objects, add an object, update an object, remove an object,
and call "Save Changes" to flush everything to the database.
For the real "Ode to Food DB" that implements this interface,
we just need to forward these calls to the "Entity Framework" DB Context API,
calling methods like "Add" or "Remove" on a DB set,
or in the case of "Update" we call the "Entry" API.
Remember, "Entry" was a way of attaching an existing object to the context
so the entity framework would track the object, and it will issue an update statement
because we tell the framework the object has been modified.
The fake database takes a different approach.
When you call "Add", it keeps the object in memory in a collection
that remembers all the added objects.
So during a test, it would be easy to see what's been added,
what's been updated, what's been removed.
We also have a flag telling us when someone calls "Save Changes", so we can write asserts
and make sure that changes were committed to the database.
And the end result is that we can write relatively simple tests,
tests that will execute very fast because all the data is in memory.
We can also control the data in this fake database, and we don't have to set up a schema
or database file or make sure we're pointed to the right database server.
And this represents, as I said, just one approach to testing controllers.
Some people will test against the database; some people will test against in-memory fakes.
You have to find what you are comfortable with,
and what works for your team and for your application.
And the tests here might be tests you want to write,
or you can certainly have different tests or additional tests.
You might want to test that the controller returns the proper "Action Result",
like a "Redirect" result when it successfully saves or updates and object.
And that would also be a valid and easy test to write.
( Silence )