In this module, we looked at test-driven development
and unit testing with "ASP dot" and "MVC".
I demonstrated the test-first development cycle
of red-green re-factor to implement a new feature.
We saw how TDD is more about design than quality control, but a wonderful side effect
of TDD is how we have unit tests in place when we're finished with the implementation,
and that allows us to make changes in the future to the code.
We also looked at unit testing controllers.
"MVC" makes controllers easy to test.
For the most part, you just need to instantiate them and pass
in parameters, and assert on the result.
We just have to make sure the code we write inside the controller is testable.
And we looked at using fake testables to give us complete control over the execution environment
for a controller, and avoid using a database in our unit tests.
If you're new to unit testing, I really hope this module has given you some inspiration
to try it out.