Output caching allows you to store the output of a particular controller action in memory.
ASP.net can then respond to future requests for the same action just
by giving back the cached result and that avoids executing any of the code inside the action.
Because you're executing less code and doing less work,
caching can lead to some pretty dramatic performance gains but you do have to be able
to careful when using the cache to avoid erroneous responses.
I'll show you such a scenario in our demo.
Caching itself is easy to enable using the output cache action filter.
You can cache actions that produce few results and jayson (phonetic) results
or really any type of data oriented result.
You'd primarily want to cache the actions that get called the most or the ones
that are expensive because they execute a slow database query.
Those are some of those places where you would get your biggest win
with the output cache attribute.
The attribute will also work on child (phonetic) actions as we'll see and there's a variety
of options you can specify on the attribute itself like the duration
that the cache items should leave in memory, that's specified in seconds
and what parameters should bury the cache.
This is best understood through an example.
( Silence )
Inside the home controller for the application, let's add an output cache attribute here.
We'll add it to the index action.
The index action represents the home page of the application
and chances are it might get the most traffic of the entire site.
And I say might because I don't really know.
One of the tips to implementing a successful caching strategy is you really do have
to know where your traffic is going.
You have to know what are the most expensive operations in your software.
You have to take some measurements and do some logging in order for caching
to really work effectively but this is just a demonstration
of how the output cache attribute works.
So I'll place the attribute there.
Set a break point at the beginning of this action and then run with the debugger.
( Silence )
And what we should see here is on this first request, we will hit that break point
so we're inside of the index action and you'll notice the one parameter I have to specify
with the output cache attribute is the duration.
How long do I cache the response?
It's specified in seconds and this is 60 seconds.
So now if I press F5 to continue with the debugger, I can now see the home page
and now I can refresh this as many times as I want and the caching logic inside
of ASP.net is looking at the request, seeing that there's a cached response for this request.
So it doesn't even go into my code at all.
It just returns that cached response.
We don't execute code inside of the index action.
We don't render any views.
Everything is just a cached response that's being served back from memory
and not executing code is the best optimization of all.
It's the best way to increase performance and scalability.
Now this also works with child actions.
So let's stop debugging and let me add another action here.
It's going to be a child action.
It's called say hello.
It's also going to be cached and we'll say for 60 seconds.
And I went to change the duration of the output cache for the index action to just 5 seconds
and now inside of the view for this index action,
we will need to call and render this child action.
So let me go into index.cshtml and do a quick html.action.
Please render say hello.
Call into that controller action.
Save everything and let's run with the debugger again
after I set a break point here, inside of say hello.
So F5 and on this first request, we should see that we come into the index action which we do
and we come into the say hello child action.
So I'll continue debugging and now if I refresh, more than 5 seconds elapsed.
So we're back inside the index action and we need to re-execute all of that code
but we don't need to execute say hello again.
So the MVC framework is able to cache that small part of the response independently
and when I refresh the page, yes it has to rebuild everything else
and execute the database inquiry inside the index action
but it doesn't to call back in to say hello.
If I had something that was particularly expensive to produce
and it was relatively static so I could aggressively cache it, that's a good place
to use html.action just to cache the result of something expensive.