( Silence )
In addition to duration, the output cache attribute supports a number
of different settings.
These settings are all available from the underlying ASP.net cache engine.
It's the same engine that web forms will use
which is why I call caching part of the ASP.net infrastructure.
It's not something that's specific to just the MVC framework
but one of these settings is the vary by (phonetic) parameter.
The default setting for this is star or asterisk which means vary by every parameter possible
and that is usually the setting that you want.
That's the default because you normally do not want to return the same cached response
for different parameters and by parameters think of things like query string parameters.
A query string parameter can contain a search term and you wouldn't want
to return the same cached response when someone is searching for a
and b. Those would be two different results for two different search strings but if I do want
to take control over this, I could say vary by param equals none
which means don't vary by any parameter.
Always return the same response regardless of what you see in the query string
or I can say vary by and specify the name of a parameter that I want to vary by.
And you can have multiple names in there separated by a semicolon.
So if I were to say vary by a param search term and someone searches
and passes along the parameter value of a. That would be one cached response that ASP.net saves.
A little bit someone comes along and passes a search term of z.
That would be a second cached result that the ASP.net saves and it would only use
that in response to another request that came
in that says search term equals z. We'll see that in demo in just a bit.
You can also set the cache location.
The default value here is anywhere meaning it will cache on the server
and the client can also cache the result.
You can be very specific and say that the result should only be cached on the server
or on the client or on proxy servers in between.
There's also a vary by header setting.
That allows you to vary the cache based
on a specific HTTB (phonetic) header like except language.
We wouldn't want to return a response
that included English text when someone needs German text.
We'll see how except language works in this module.
And if all fails, you can always do vary by custom.
When you do vary by custom you'll need
to override a method inside the global.asax.cs file.
Inside of that method, you can build your own custom caching string telling ASP.net what
to cache and how to categorize it.
You could look at anything in the request including headers or quickie values.
There's some examples on MSDN that will show you how to do that.
There's also examples that will show you how to setup a sequel dependency.
A sequel dependency will cache a response until data inside of a sequel server table changes.
It sounds great but it's not widely used just because there are a lot of restrictions
on the type of sequel query that can be used.
( Silence )
In Visual Studio, now that we know how the output cache attribute works
with a child action, I'm going to remove this child action
because it's not really providing any value.
It was just here for demonstration purposes.
(Silence) And I'll also need to remove the call to html.action
that was rendering that child action.
And now that we've made that change, let's bump up the duration on the output cache attribute
for our index action and run this with the debugger to see how it behaves with paging.
And as expected that first request comes into index action, I press F5.
We now have a cached response for the home page and I can come up and pound
on the refresh button as much as I like.
The ASP.net run time is always returning a cached response.
Now let me try to go to the next page.
We'll come back into the index action because the output cache directive will vary
by every parameter and previously, we didn't have a page parameter.
Now we do have a page parameter.
The page number is equal to 2.
So it needs to pick up a new response and cache that.
Now we have cached response for page 2.
I go to the next page, same thing.
We come into the index action, produce that response for page 3,
and now I have cached responses for pages 2 and 3.
I can toggle between the two.
It's not going to go back into the index action.
So does this also work for search?
Let's search for a 20.
We come into the index action.
That changed the search term parameter.
We get the response and it appears on the screen correctly.
What if I go to 21?
Again into the index action, come back to 20.
That just serves up a cached response.
Let me show you a problem.
What if I come directly to the application through a bookmark
and I'm looking for search term equals 20?
Well now the browser issued a get request not asynchronous request but a get request
and it's displaying a cached response that was only a portion of the page.
So we're missing the layout view.
We're missing our style sheets.
We're missing our scripts and here's the problem.
The only difference between a full request which is what I just did
that needs the entire page full of html and the AJAX request that we were using previously,
the only difference between those two is an HTTB header known as x requested with.
So the ASP.net caching layer, there's no change in the parameters.
So it will happily return the partial view that it cached to fulfill a previous request
but that's not what we want in this scenario and searching by going directly to the page
with the value in the query string, if that's a supported scenario we need to fix this.
Actually there's two things that we need to do.
First, I'll stop debugging.
( Silence )
And we'll come into our output cache attribute and also tell it vary by a header.
The x requested with header because this will be present on an AJAX request
but not on a whole page request and now ASP.net will be able to tell the difference
between the two and cached different responses.
One with a full page of html, one with just the portion of the page that needs to update.
Unfortunately this often isn't enough.
We're also allowing the browser to cache the response with this output cache attribute
and some browsers won't be smart enough to detect the difference
between those two requests either.
So I am also going to add a location parameter.
To do this I need to bring in a name space for this numerated value, system.web.ui
but now we're only going to allow caching on the server.
And ASP.net will send instructions to the browser
and the response so the response isn't cached.
The browser always has to come back to the server and check.
On the server, ASP.net can just serve up the response
from memory if it has a cached response.
Of course another solution to this problem would be to call a different action for AJAX requests
and that would make a lot of sense.
I combine the two into a single action here because it made it easy for a demo
but it would be easy to change the url for an AJAX request in our JAVA script
and have it call a different action.
And then we wouldn't have this check for request.AJAXrequest.
We would only return a full response.
That is AJAX request method, by the way also looks at the (inaudible) requested with header
to determine if a request is an asynch request.
Now we'll run the application again and just to avoid any strange things.
I'm going to go into the developer tools by pressing F12 and just telling Internet Explorer,
clear out anything that you might have previously cached.
This way we'll make sure that we're starting with a fresh slate when I test
out this functionality with the new parameter values in place.
So let's try the search for 20 and we hit the index action.
That was good.
Try a search for 21.
Again, hitting the index action.
Try an asynchronous search for 20.
That was a cached response which was good and now let's go to the query string
and enter a full request for search term equals 20 and we do, indeed,
come into the index action and the page renders normally.
And that's all thanks to doing a vary by header and only caching on the server.
If we wanted the client browser to be able to cache too, we really would need
to split this index action into two pieces.
One that only responds to an AJAX request and one that responds for a full page.