( Silence )
In reality, it is almost impossible to pick the correct cache duration setting
in a development environment.
You need to put the application into a production like environment.
Put it under load, take some measurements, and then make some adjustments.
You might found out that you're using too much memory and caching requests
that just aren't being used or you might find that you're not caching enough.
For these reasons, ASP.net allows you to specify a cache profile in the output cache attribute.
A cache profile then is something that's stored
in your web.config file and can specify a duration.
It's underneath a section named caching and it's inside of here
where you can put duration values.
As this example demonstrates, you can have multiple cash profiles
and you reference the cache profile by name in the output cache attribute.
I generally recommend using cache profiles instead of hard code and cache settings
because first of all, it avoids repetition in the cache attributes.
If you want to double the duration inside of all of your cache attributes,
you don't have to do a search and replace throughout the code.
You just go to one location in your web.config file.
It's also easier to change the cache settings once the application is deployed
because now all you do is edit the config file and then you avoid changing the settings
in code, recompiling, and redeploying.
And typically when you're doing performance tuning on an application,
you need to run it while taking some measurements.
Then you tweak the cache settings and then you run it again
to make sure you did really get better results and it's not getting worse.
And you'll do this over and over again until you reach some goal like reduced memory usage
or reduced CPU or an increase in how many requests per second your application handles.
( Silence )
Inside our application if I wanted to use a cache profile instead of this hard code
of duration, all I would need to do is come into the root level web.config and somewhere inside
of system.web, create a caching element.
We're going to create output cache settings.
Notice you get intel sense (phonetic) the entire way through and we're going
to create multiple output cache profiles.
So let's add one called long that has a duration of 300 seconds and add another one
with a duration of 3 seconds called short.
And of course, you could have as many of these as you want.
Now I just need to reference one of these from the home controller.
So instead of having a duration, have cache profile equals long.
And the application should behave just like it did before.
Just now I have my numbers inside of a config file instead
of hard coded inside of the controller.
( Silence )