The next topic we want to talk about it is how to localize an application.
There are two important settings for every thread of execution
that determine how an application behaves under different cultures.
The first setting is exposed by the static current culture property of the thread class.
This property tells the run time how to format strings.
For instance, if we have a dot 2 (phonetic) string on a date time or a dot 2 on a currency,
then how should the date time be formatted and what currency symbol should be used?
Is it going to be a euro, a dollar, a rupee or a yen?
Another important setting is exposed from the static current UI culture property.
This setting impacts how the run time performs resource loading which we're about to look at.
You can set these properties in your own code.
For example, if you have one of those sites
where you let the user select what language they want to see and that's in a drop down list
or they click on a flag icon, that would be a scenario
where you would set these properties manually.
Or you can let ASP.net set these properties for you.
ASP.net will set the properties based
on the accept language HTTP header that the client's browser sends.
In order for ASP.net to do this automatically though,
you do have to add a globalization section to your web.doc config file and set the culture
and UI culture attributes to auto.
Let's see how these settings make our application behave.
( Silence )
Inside of the index view for the home controller,
let's do a little experiment with the globalization settings.
So first I'm going to add a code block
that defines two variables, amount which is a decimal.
That's what the m suffix is and sum date
which is a date time representing July 9th of the year 2002.
And now I will add some code to output these two variables by calling two string.
Amount will call two string and pass in a C parameter which means please format this
as a currency and with sum date, we'll just call two short date string.
And before we run the application, I will come into the web config and inside of system.web,
I will add that globalization section that we talked about.
We need to set culture equals auto and we need to set UI culture equals auto.
And now let's see how this behaves.
I will run the application with Internet Explorer and since my default culture
on this machine is United States English, I see the currency value is formatted
with a dollar sign and the date is formatted as month, day, year.
But now let me come into the Internet Explorer options.
So ALT T will open the tools menu.
Come into internet options.
Under appearance, go to languages and here I can set language preferences.
It's from here where I can add a language and in this list, let me select French
and not the Canadian French but the real Francois from France and let me take
that language and move it up in the list.
So this is now essentially my preferred language and I will close this out and refresh the page.
( Silence )
And now my currency is formatted with a comma and a euro sign
and the date format has also changed.
It is now day month year.
So what we've done so far is to see how globalization works
and this is just a starting point for localization.
We've changed how data amounts were formatted but we would also need to go
through the application and take care of string literals like search by name if we really want
to localize those to a specific culture
because all the literal texts in here are still in English.
Let's see how we can change that.