( Silence )
To localize the text, I went to display in this application.
I'm going to rely on resource files.
A resource file is an XML with a resx extension,
r e s x and it stores localized strings for a culture.
It can also contain binary assets like images
but we'll just be using text in this application.
To support different languages, I'll need at least one resource file
for each language that I explicitly support.
The first resource file I create will be the base resource file
and this might have a name like strings.resx.
If I want to produce a version of strings.resx that works with Spanish,
I'd also create a strings.es.resx.
So you can see the language the resx supports, it's embedded in the file name
and it follows a naming convention to describe to the dot.net runtime what language
and what culture a particularly resx file supports.
You can also be very specific about the culture.
So es dash mx would be Spanish Mexico.
In dot.net there's a resource manager that will load the appropriate resource file
for the current UI culture that's set but we generally do not have to interact
with this resource manager directly
because Visual Studio will automatically compile these resources into our project
and generate code to access the resources with a strongly typed class.
If you go to the properties window for a resx file,
you'll see Visual Studio has the build action set to embedded resource.
We'll talk about some of the other settings here when we get to the demonstration
but to use a resource is very simple.
In a view, I can get to a resource with a greeting property inside by going
to the generated class and asking for the greeting property.
This might return the string hello for English but it could also return hola
if the current UI culture is set to Spanish and a Spanish resource exists.
If a resource doesn't exist for the current UI settings,
the resource manager will fall back to the base resource.
Let's go into Visual Studio and see how all of this works.
Inside the index view for the home controller, let me add a greeting to this view just
above the other culturally sensitive information that we're displaying.
And now what I want to do is localize this so it's not a hard coded string in English.
We could display English or French or any other language that we create a resource file for.
So the first step is to create that resource file.
And one of the decisions you'll have to make when creating a resource file is where to create
that because you can have multiple resource files and these resource files could live
in the web project, in this ode to food (phonetic) project.
You could also put them in a separate class library if that was more maintainable for you
and you also need to select what folder these resource files are going to go into.
To keep things simple, I think I might need a resource file just
for the views for the home controller.
And so what I might do in that situation is come into the home views folder and add a new item.
I'll search for res and that should bring up resources file.
I will call this just resources.resx and this will be my base resource file.
It opens up in a Visual Studio resx file editor.
One of the changes that I have to make sure I do inside
of here is to change this access modifier.
It's currently internal.
I'm going to change that over to be public.
This is just required because of the compilation model.
It turns out that razor views are compiled into a different assembly, a different dll file
than our ode to food assembly and without having these resource files be generated
as public classes, we wouldn't be able to see them from our razor views but just changing
that access modifier will set that for you.
Behind the scenes what's happening is there is a class being generated for you.
You can see it if you expand a resources.resx, there's a generated .cs file behind here
and we'll take a look at that in just a second.
First, let me come in and add a name.
So this is how I want to reach a specific resource.
I want to have the greeting resource and this is where I would give it a value like hello.
And now if I save this resources file and open up the generated code,
you'll see there's a class that's generated in the odetofood.views.home name space.
It's called resources and all the way down here at the bottom --
( Silence )
-- there will be a greeting property that I can get to and all the other code that is inside
of here is just code that is required
to have the .net resource manager load the appropriate resource file.
And if I wanted to use this code from an index view,
all I need to do now is replace my hard coded text with the name spaces, the class name,
and the name of the resource that I want to display.
In this case, greeting and at this point,
if anyone comes to the site specifying any language, we're always going to display hello
because this our base resource file.
We don't have a resource file specified for any other languages so everyone gets English.
If I wanted to customize this for say, French, that's when I could come
in and add a second resource file.
So let's add a new item --
( Silence )
-- with the same name, resources.fr.resx and inside
of here I would duplicate the name value pairs.
You can obviously have as many name value pairs as you want but we just have one.
The name is always greeting but this would be the French translation, bonjour.
Notice there is no code generation for this resource file.
Code generation only needs to happen on the base resource file, resources.resx.
All of these files get embedded into my assembly by Visual Studio when it builds.
That's why the build action is set to embedded resource.
So you can think of all this information getting compiled right alongside with your C sharp code
that goes with your application wherever you copy the dll file to.
Well, let's run this and see how it behaves.
( Silence )
On the home page of the application, I'm still configured to prefer the French language.
So I see bonjour.
I see Euros.
Now let me go into tools, internet options, languages, set language preferences,
and move English back up to the top.
Then close all these windows and refresh Internet Explorer
and refresh Internet Explorer and nothing happens.
I'm still seeing bonjour.
Is this a problem with the way I created my resource files?
Is this a problem with Internet Explorer?
Well no, none of the above.
It turns out, once again that we have to be very careful with something that we added earlier
which is the output cache attribute.
In this case, what is probably happening now is I'm making this request
but all the MVC run time caching cares about is that all the parameters are the same,
the x requested with hasn't changed.
It's going to return a cached response that was built for the French language.
I need to tell ASP.net that there's another header that it's need to vary the cache with
and that is the accept language header.
And we actually don't separate these with commas.
We separate these with semicolons.
And now if I build the application, let's try this again.
I'll refresh this page and now we're displaying hello.
That seems good.
And let me go into tools, internet options, languages, set language preferences,
move French back to the top, close one window.
Close two windows.
Close three windows and refresh and now we display bonjour.
So caching isn't interfering with our localization anymore.
And while we're here at the home controller there's something else you should know
about resource files.
There's really nothing that restricts you to using them only from a view.
So I could have a greeting string defined here that is set
to odetofood.views.home.resources.greeting and that would work just as well.
The correct string will be loaded on the UI culture setting and in fact,
you can also use these resources if you want
to build custom error messages for your data annotations.
So let's look at the restaurant review model that we built and we had things like required.
And if the user doesn't fill something out here,
they'll get an error message like the body field is required.
Let's say you wanted to customize that and also customize it for different languages.
In that case, you could come in and you wouldn't use error message.
Error message would just be hard coded text on what you wanted the error message to be.
We want this to be localized so I would specify error message resource type and I would set this
to the type of my resource class, the generated class that was given to me
and I would also specify the error message resource name.
That is what to look up inside of that resource file.
This is where I would provide one of the names that's inside of my resource file.
Greeting, obviously, wouldn't make any sense as an error message but it's the only one I have
in there now so I'm adding it here.
You'd obviously have to create some error messages.
Maybe they would be in a different resource file somewhere in your project
but you could just specify the type of the resource and the name to pull out of
that resource file and then you can have localized error messages too.
( Silence )