Our last infrastructure topic is diagnostics.
Diagnostics help us answer the question just what is our application doing?
When did it start?
When it restart?
Are there any unhandled exceptions?
Are there any authorization failures?
To get this type of information, there are a number of options available.
First, ASP.net does have a health monitoring system you can configure to report on everything
from application start to application end and all the events in between,
exceptions, failures, compilation events.
There are also many third party options for logging and monitoring.
Logfornet is a popular open source library you can reference
to build your own logging infrastructure.
And the patterns and practices team at Microsoft also has an application logging block.
One really popular open source library is ELMAH, e l m a h. That stands
for Error Logging Handles and Modules.
ELMAH can capture events about your application and store them in a variety of destinations,
xml files, text files, databases.
It could even post them to Twitter and it has some prebuilt UI
to show you the events it has recorded.
Let's take a look.