( Silence )
The default configuration for ASP.net health monitoring lives in a web.config file
but it doesn't live in the web.config file that's in the root of your project.
Instead it lives in a machine level web.config file that applies configuration
to every ASP.net application that runs on this computer.
You can find that if you go into your Windows directory.
Go to Microsfoft.net.
Go to framework and then pick the right version number.
We're using Visual Studio 2012 with .net 4 point 5.
So of course we go to the version 4 directory
because version 4 point 5 was an in place update to version 4.
Dot.net version numbers have always been confusing
and dot.net 4 point 5 continues that historical tradition.
We go into that directory.
There'll be a config directory.
It's inside of here where you will find a machine level web.config
that applies configuration everywhere.
I can drag that into Visual Studio and we'll do a search,
control I in here to find health monitoring.
And the two most important sections in here are -- well actually there's 3 important sections.
One is providers.
Providers include destinations for where you can publish events.
You might want to save them in the event log.
In that case, you'd use the event log provider or maybe you want to store them in sequel server
or maybe you want to use WOMI (phonetic) to publish these events.
So those are the built-in providers.
You can always add more providers if you write one.
Another important section is event mappings.
This categorizes all the possible events into buckets with friendly names.
So we have all events which is every event that could happen in the health monitoring system,
lifetime events, request processing events, and all errors.
It is the rules section that will define where to send something like all errors.
What provider do we send these to?
So by default because this is in this machine level web config,
we will send all errors to the event log.
Any unhandled exception that occurs
in the ASP.net application should appear in the Windows event log.
Also, any failure audits should appear in the event log.
You can add additional rules.
The best thing to do would be to take this health monitoring section and mimic
in your own web.config file if you want to reconfigure any of these rules
but the one thing you need to be careful about is not to do something
like send all request processing events to the Windows error log.
It's not designed to handle a high volume of events being pumped into it.
That would be something that you could do with sequel server though.
But because we have these rules in effect, all errors go to the event log,
that means if I have an unhandled exception, I should be able to see
that in the Windows event log and in fact, we still do have a controller,
the cuisine controller, that we wrote a long time ago that has an unhandled exception.
It intentionally has an unhandled exception.
So let's run the application and go there once.
And now something terrible has happened.
Let's see if I can find this in the Windows event log by going
to the gigantic start menu and typing --
( Silence )
-- event and under settings, there's view event logs.
ASP.net errors would be recorded under Windows logs, under application and here
at the very top we can see there's been an ASP.net problem.
It's listed as a warning but it's inside of here where you will find the event message which is
that there was an unhandled exception.
You can find the path to the application where this occurred, the machine name.
You can find out who the web server was running as.
Since we're using IS Express, it's running under my account and there's a full stack trace
that we could use to try to track down exactly where this error came from.
So all of that information's recorded in the event log for you automatically
but sometimes the event log can be a little cumbersome to get to.
Sometimes you want to store things in a way that you can get to them through the web interface
or perhaps, you want to be able to email errors out to the people
and that's when you can turn to ELMAH.
Remember this stands for Error Logging Modules and Handlers.
The easy way to install it is through newget (phonetic).
We'll just do a search for ELMAH and the package I want to install is ELMAH.mvc
because this will allow me to reach the ELMAH error logs
in a nice MVC friendly way just by going to slash ELMAH.
And now if I close this, it's been added to the project.
I'm just going to do a build to make sure all the right files get copied to the right places.
Otherwise, there's no code changes I need to make.
We'll go back to the cuisine controller.
I have a few exceptions pumped in here by pounding on the refresh key
and now let me go to slash ELMAH.
And I can see all the exceptions that it just recorded.
You can drill into the details and see the stack trace.
You can also configure ELMAH to send these via email or store them in different places.
All that configuration can take place in your web.config file.
In fact, ELMAH did add some configuration to my web.config file
and it added some of these app settings.
For instance, who is allowed to see the event log?
Since we now have rules in the application, I could say well only admins.
You can also configure the route that you use to get to see those error messages.
So by default it's ELMAH and just go to slash ELMAH to see the errors, that's very simple.
And one more thing, since we are going to require rules here.
I'm going to explicitly say this requires authentication before you can view it.
You can read more details about ELMAH and ELMAH configuration on the ELMAH website.
( Silence )