In this module, we spent some time with the ASP.net output cache attribute.
We saw how to use the attribute and vary by location and vary by header
to hopefully increase the performance of the application.
I say hopefully because I never took any performance measurements before
and after caching and the only way to know for sure that you've helped is
to start taking hard measurements.
So I encourage you to always take measurements before you start applying cache attributes.
We also looked at the localization features of ASP.net and saw how we can let resource files
and ASP.net take care of most of the hard work.
We saw, for example, how the globalization settings
in web.config can automatically give us different formatting behaviors
for different languages depending on the client's accept language header.
Finally, we took a look at diagnostics and we now have ELMAH added to the application
and watching for errors and giving us an easy way to see the unhandled exceptions that occur.
This was just a quick look at all the functionality that ELMAH can provide.
( Silence )