Hi. This is Scott Allen.
In this module is we'll look at the security features of ASP.NET MVC.
In this module I want to show you how to work with users and roles and also how to use OpenID
and OAuth so your customers can sign in to your website using a third party
like Microsoft, Google, or Facebook.
I also want to show you some of the attacks that you'll face
if you deploy an application on a web server.
So we'll look at cross-site request forgeries
and how to make your application resist such an attack.
We'll start by looking at authentication and see how we can use Windows Integrated Authentication
for internet style apps and forms-based authentication for web applications.
( Pause )