When you authenticate a user, you are verifying the identity of the user.
You might need to know a user's identity because you're building an application
that only specific users should access, like a payroll system.
You cannot let just anyone poke around in the salary information.
Or maybe you're building a website where users post their picture collections.
You might want to know the user's identity just so you can track their photographs
and only allow users to delete their own photographs and not the photographs of others.
So the first step would be identifying the user and making sure you know who they are.
There are three ways to do this with ASP.NET.
The first mechanism is called Forms Authentication.
With forms-based authentication, the website is responsible for providing a page
with an input form where the user can enter their user name and enter their password.
And when they click a log on button, something inside our application is responsible
for making sure they entered the right password.
We'll see how MVC provides a lot of the infrastructure support for Forms Authentication
so it's not as hard as it sounds.
Another way to authenticate a user is to use OpenID or OAuth.
These are open standards for authentication and authorization respectively and using OpenID
or OAuth means your users don't need to create or share a password with your site
and you don't have to store or validate a user's password.
Instead, you rely on a third party like Twitter or Microsoft
to authenticate the user and then tell you who they are.
We'll see this in a bit.
The third approach is Windows Authentication.
Windows Authentication is typically used for internet applications because it uses components
and services provided by the Windows Operating System.
Microsoft also refers to Windows Auth as "Integrated Auth", because once a user is logged
in to a domain, Windows can automatically authenticate them to My Application
if My Application uses Windows Auth.
Although Windows Authentication does work across a variety of browsers
and not just Internet Explorer, it's still best to use for an internet application
that runs inside your company's Firewall and where all of your users are logged
into a Windows domain and you have an active directory server somewhere.
Your users can have a single sign on experience, because once they logged on to their desktops,
they use that identity for your application as well as network shares
and network printers and other internet apps.
If you're building a public website then you probably want to avoid Windows Auth
because users might not be on the same domain.
In fact, they might not even be running on a device that supports Windows Authentication.
And that's where Forms Authentication comes in, because any web browser can let a user sign
into a site using Forms Authentication.
It's highly customizable because you build the log on page
and you control the log on experience.
You can customize how the form looks and how strong of a password that you require.
Forms Authentication relies on cookies by default.
So once a user is signed in to an application, the runtime will store a cookie
in the client's browser so they don't need to sign in again during the same browsing session.
One word of warning with Forms Authentication, is that SSL is required
to make Forms Authentication secure.
Unless I'm logging into a site using an HTTPS address instead of regular HTTP,
then I'm passing in my user name and password across the network in plain text and someone
who is watching network traffic can see my password and steal it.
OpenID and OAuth are also designed to work with internet applications.
When you need to validate a user's identity, you redirect their browser to a third party website,
like a website run by Google or Microsoft,
and the user proves their identity to this third party.
Then the third party will redirect the user back to you with a message
that proves they successfully authenticated themselves.
This all works securely, thanks to the magic of cryptography.
We'll see how to work with these three different approaches to authentication in this module.
And we'll get started by looking at Windows Authentication.
( Pause )