The OdeToFood application we've been working on was created
with the internet application project template.
You might remember that from the first module.
Internet applications use Forms-Based Authentication by default,
but I want to demonstrate Windows Authentication, and changing this application
over to use Windows Authentication is a bit messy.
It's possible but it's messy.
So instead of getting messy I'll launch a second instance of Visual Studio
and we'll create a new temporary project just to look at how Windows Authentication works.
So a new project using MVC 4, I don't really care about the name
because we won't be spending anytime with this.
So we don't need a unit test project either.
I just want to make sure instead of creating an internet application,
I create an intranet application and then I'll click okay and be back
in a second once Visual Studio has the setup.
Now the project is ready to go and Visual Studio will open up a readme.text file by default
when you create an intranet application.
It'll list a couple manual steps that you have to go through in order for this to work
because many web servers today ship with features turned off by default.
And one of the features that is off by default is the ability to do Windows Authentication.
To fix that, I need to come into to the MvcApplication and open up the property window.
And I do that by going to View, Properties Window.
In this case I cannot right-click on the Project and go to Properties.
That takes me to the wrong place.
I need to open up the Properties Window by clicking this or pressing F4.
And that allows me to set some properties on the development server.
Remember the development server is IIS Express.
That's a little application running down here in the system tray.
We've hardly looked at it at all.
It just sits there and runs in the background to process our request.
We need to come in for IIS Express and tell it to enable Windows Authentication.
And that's all the configuration we really need right now.
Everything in an intranet application requires authentication by default.
So it will not let a user in until it knows who they are.
And that means if I run the application,
the first thing Internet Explorer will do is pop up a log in box.
And you might wonder, well, what's so integrated about Windows Authentication
if Internet Explorer is always going to ask me to log in?
But this behavior is peculiar to Internet Explorer
because Internet Explorer will only automatically log you into a site if it thinks
that site is on your local network.
And by default, Internet Explorer doesn't consider local host to be on the local network.
If I want to change that experience I would have to go into the Tools menu in IE,
so Alt T will open up the menu, and then I can go to Internet Options.
Go to the Security tab.
Click on Local Intranet and then go to sites.
Go to Advanced, and finally I reach a dialog where I can tell Internet Explorer
that local host should be considered an intranet site.
And the reason this is important is because if we look at the custom settings
for a local internet, essentially what are all the settings that are applied in this soon,
and I explore all the way down, you'll see right here
that Internet Explorer will only automatically log
on for a website that's in the intranet zone.
And it doesn't matter if you've created an internet site or an internet site with MVC,
this is completely based on IE's heuristics
on determining what's an internet site and what's not an internet site.
But now, local host should be considered in the internet zone
and if I close all these dialog boxes, and close the browser and press Ctrl F5 to run this again,
Internet Explorer will automatically log me in using my current credentials for this machine
or my domain if I have a domain controller.
The machine is WIN8VPC, my user name is Scott and that can automatically display it
because I've been authenticated, even here on the Homepage.
And no log in box was required this time.
Where does this text come from?
That's in the layout view for this application.
If we go to Views, Shared, Layout, we'll find there's a section
in here using User.Identity.Name.
So the user property and User.Identity, they're both available for Windows Authentication
and also Forms-based Authentication.
You can do things like find out the user's name.
You can also use identity to find out if the user has been authenticated
or not and how they were authenticated.
And we'll see User.Identity again when we come back to Forms-Based Authentication.
But for now, this is how Windows Authentication works.
And the one other primary difference between this application and the OdeToFood application,
if I come into web.config, inside of here there will be a section called "Authentication",
and you can see the mode is equal to Windows.
Inside the OdeToFood application, we have that same section,
authentication section, but the mode is equal to forms.
And that's essentially what's telling ASP.NET
if it's using Windows or Forms-Based Authentication.
( Pause )