Now we can look at Forms Authentication in the application we've been building, OdeToFood.
But before we get into the code, I feel we should take a step back and look
at the big picture of how Forms Authentication works in general
and how ASP.NET implements Forms Authentication in MVC 4.
First, imagine the user tries to go to a members only area of the site,
an area that requires user authentication.
We'll see how to enforce this requirement.
But MVC will know when you require authentication.
And when it sees an anonymous user trying to get to such a place,
it will redirect the user's browser to a log in page.
You can configure where this log in page lives
and in an MVC application this will not be a page of course, it will be a controller action.
But to the user it's a page and it's a page where they enter the user name and password.
When ASP.NET does this redirect, it will also save the URL,
the user originally wanted to access.
So if they successfully authenticate,
ASP.NET will automatically redirect them back to where they wanted to go.
It does this by storing the original URL in the query string
with the name ReturnUrl and it will use that value.
So once a user logs in, they don't have to click around the site trying
to find that members only area again.
They'll be redirected right back to it.
If the user cannot get logged in, they'll never get to the members area.
But if they do give the user name and password, ASP.NET will redirect them back and they'll get
to see the content that you're protecting.
ASP.NET also gives the browser a cookie for the application.
A cookie is like a piece of data that the browser will hold on to.
And once a browser holds a cookie for a site, it will continue to send that cookie along
in every request that it makes to the site or at least as long as the browsing session lasts,
possibly longer if you and the user allow it.
Inside of that cookie is some encrypted information letting ASP.NET know
that the user has already authenticated themselves and this means,
as the user is browsing through that members only area or other sections of the application
that require authentication, ASP.NET will see that cookie,
know the user has been authenticated, it's not an anonymous user,
and ASP.NET will allow them to succeed with that request.
It won't force them to reauthenticate or sign in again.
What I'm describing about Forms Authentication isn't specific to ASP.NET,
many web frameworks take a similar approach to Forms Authentication.
They use log in pages, they use cookies, just the names of the pages and the names
of the cookies and query string values change.
Let's talk about how this works in ASP.NET MVC 4 specifically.
First, when you create a new application using the internet project template,
the project template will include everything you need to register a user, allow them to log in,
allow them to change their password, all the basics that you need for Forms Authentication.
All these basics are provided by an AccountController,
you'll find that in your Controllers folder as well as a set of views
in the Views Account folder and there're also some models.
You'll find them in the Models folder.
If you peek at the code inside the AccountController,
you'll see it's using a class named WebSecurity.
And WebSecurity is from a Microsoft library named WebMatrix.
Perhaps, you've heard of WebMatrix.
It's another tool from Microsoft, you can use to create websites
and ASP.NET MVC is borrowing some of that technology from WebMatrix
to implement Forms Authentication.
It's the WebSecurity class you can talk to from your code in the AccountController
to tell it to validate a user's password.
WebSecurity in turn talks to a component known as this SimpleMembershipProvider.
And although there are more layers that what I'm showing here.
Ultimately, you can think of the membership provider as doing the hard work
of storing information in the database.
Earlier I mentioned that Forms Authentication is customizable.
And you can certainly go into the AccountController
and the AccountController views and make as many changes as you'd
like to have the log in form look different.
You can also customize the application by taking control over the underlying SQL Storage.
You can customize what you want to store about a user.
For instance, you could customize the Register screen by asking the user
to name their favorite restaurant, and then store that in a table in SQLServer along
with the rest of the user information that you need.
I'll show you how all this works together and some steps you want
to make to customize the application.
( Pause )