Before we get in to registering and logging in and seeing how to require authentication
in the application, let me show you a few steps you can take to have more control
over what's happening behind the scenes, particularly at the database layer
and particularly if you want to customize the information that's being stored about a user.
The first step I would recommend is coming into the project and finding the Filters folder.
Inside of here you'll find the file, Initialize SimpleMembershipAttribute.
If we open this up, there's a lot of complex code in here
because when you start a new MVC 4 application with this project template that we used,
the internet project template, it's not 100 percent sure
that you want to use Forms Authentication.
So there's a lot of complex code here to make sure
that Forms Authentication is initialized in a lazy manner.
Perhaps you're not even going to use a database in this website.
And in that case, none of this code would have to execute.
But if you've already decided that you are going to use Forms Authentication,
there's no reason to have all of this code.
What you really want to get to is the essence inside of here
which is WebSecurity dot InitializeDatabaseConnection.
This is a call to initialize all the membership infrastructure and tell it,
a name of the connection string that you're going to use to connect to the database,
which is DefaultConnection, the same database we're using
to store a restaurant information is also specifies the name of the table
that will contain user information, its UserProfile,
a column that contains the primary key value for a user, so it can look a user
up given their ID value and also the column that contains the UserName.
You can have as many other columns in this table as you want when you store user profiles,
but you at least need to give it a primary key and the user name.
If we know we're using Forms Authentication, we might as well take this line of code and cut it
out of here, Ctrl X, and run it during application startup.
So I will come into Global.asax.cs
and inside the application start method I will paste that code inside of here.
We'll need to bring in a namespace, so control period and select that first entry,
this WebSecurity class is in the WebMatrix.WebDataNameSpace.
Now that namespace is added and we have legal C# code.
If you want to be consistent, you could wrap up this call into some static method on a class
so everything looks like something .Register.
But right now we'll keep things simple
and just leave initialize database connection right here in the application start.
Now that that is here, there's no use to have this filter.
So we'll come into this filter and delete it.
And yes, the next time you build you'll get compiler errors.
But we're going to fix this.
Before I fix this, there's one more step I want to take.
Inside of the Models folder, you will find an AccountModel.cs file.
Inside of here, there's a class that derives from DbContext, you recognize that now
as the entity framework DbContext.
This is giving the AccountController access to that user's table
through a DbContext derived class.
But we want to control this.
We want to have this as part of our DbContext.
So I'm just going to delete this DbContext.
We don't need it.
We do need something to represent a user profile.
So I might as well start with this class.
It has a UserID and a UserName.
I could add additional properties here.
For instance if wanted to know a user's favorite restaurant then I can include
that as another property in the user profile.
But just so I know that this is my code, I want to own this code,
it's not part of the generated code that came from this template really anymore.
I've customize it.
I'm going to cut it out of here and add it to its own class file.
So let's add a class called UserProfile and I will delete what comes out of here by default
and just paste in that UserProfile that we just had.
I'll need to include a couple of namespaces here, too.
So Ctrl period and bring in System.Component Model.DataAnnotations.Schema.
This attribute is one way to tell the entity framework that when you need
to store user profile information, when you need to store objects of this type,
put it in a table with this name, UserProfile.
We also need to bring in a namespace for the key attribute that's
in the System.Component Model.DataAnnotations.
We've used that before when we added some model validations.
This particular attribute is a way to tell the entity framework
that this is the primary key value for a user.
And by the way, it's also an identity column, meaning the database will manage the values
that get placed into here when you insert a record.
It'll automatically be generated by SQL Server.
And now that we have our own user profile class that can store our favorite restaurant,
I need to define a way to get to that in my own DbContext class.
So I will open this one up, OdeToFoodDb and let's add a property of type DbSet
of UserProfile and we could call this UserProfiles.
And now if you've been watching the previous modules, you know we've made a change
to what we're storing in the database.
We're going to need to do a schema migration.
But before we can do that we have to get the project
to build now that we've deleted some classes.
Let me do a quick build and that would give me a list to work from.
So first of all, if I double-click one of these errors,
this Initialize SimpleMembershipAttribute doesn't exist any longer.
That's okay.
We're initializing things explicitly during application start, so I can just delete that.
Then I'll double click another error.
This one is complaining about UsersContext, we deleted that.
That was what the AccountController was using to get to that UserProfile table.
Now I can get to it through OdeToFoodDb.
So let me just change this to use the var keyword and instead
of a new UsersContext we'll instantiate a new OdeToFoodDb.
Let me try another build, Shift Ctrl B. Now we've successfully built.
Let's quickly migrate the database so we can store our custom information.
I'll open up the Package Manager Console.
We have implicit migrations enabled, so I should just be able to say, update database
and I'll throw in the Verbose flag just so we can see exactly what it's going to do.
And it finished the migrations.
It's running the Seed method.
But you can see where it went out and created a table, UserProfile, that has UserID,
UserName, and FavoriteRestaurant.
We can probably tweak the annotations on UserProfile
so that User Name was an nvarchar max.
It would be much better for performance if that had a reasonable size
like nvarchar 255 or nvarchar 80.
It will be simple enough to do that just using a string length attribute on UserName,
and the same for FavoriteRestaurant.
But at this point, we're good.
We have more control over what's going to be happening in the database.
And now, we can turn our attention to looking at how to register,
how to log in, how to require authentication.
( Pause )