Let's see how Forms Authentication works inside of the application now.
As a user, I can come in and click the Register link.
And this will give me a page where I can fill out the bare amount of information
to create an account, just a User name, a Password, and then confirm my password.
I can click Register and I have an account and I'm automatically logged into the site.
My name appears at the top of the page and that's done using User.Identity.Name,
just like we saw with Windows Authentication in the Layout view.
At this point, I could click on my name to manage my account and change my password.
I could also log off of the site and then come in and log in again.
And all of this functionality is provided out of the box
when we create a new internet application.
The register page for example is given to us by adding a view
to the account folder called Register.cshtml.
And it's inside of here where you can see textboxes to input the user name
and password boxes to input the password and confirm the password.
This is one of the places you'd have to come in and modify if you wanted to force a user
to provide you additional information when they register like the name of a favorite restaurant.
And this view is rendered from an AccountController which we were also given.
Of course that's in the Controllers folder.
And it includes methods like Register.
And based on what you know about the MVC framework so far, you can probably figure
out what most of the code inside of here is doing.
We have a register action that responds to an HTTP GET request
that gives the user a form to fill out their information.
And we have a register action that response to an HTTP POST request and takes information
from the user to create a record in the database.
We also have ModelState and we have a RegisterModel which is
like a view model containing only the information about a user that we need
in the view to get them registered.
These are all concepts we've looked at so far.
So let's focus on what we haven't seen which includes the call to WebSecurity.
WebSecurity is basically a wrapper around membership functionality.
It takes care of data access, cryptography, and all the other code
that you need for Forms-Based Authentication.
Here we can see when I successfully register, there's a call to CreateUserAndAccount,
that's what actually puts me into the database.
So what database do we go to?
Well, if you remember, we placed a call
to WebSecurity.InitializeDatabase in the application start event.
And we passed the parameter specifying the database connection name
to use which was DefaultConnection.
The same connection string that we used for storing restaurant information and that means
if I go to the Database Explorer, and look at our DefaultConnection and open this
up to see the tables, I will see not only Restaurants and RestaurantReviews
which we had before, but also the UserProfile table which we've just added in this module,
that's a table that we're in control of.
And then, there's a number of tables that are used
by WebSecurity, they all have a webpages_prefix.
And if we open up some of these tables to poke around,
you can see the UserProfile table has an ID, UserName, and FavoriteRestaurant columns.
That's exactly what would we expect based on our definition for UserProfile.
And if I right-click on this and select Show Data, we'll see there's exactly one record
in here, the sallen user that I just created has a UserID but no FavoriteRestaurant
because we didn't forced anyone to fill that information out.
We don't have a place yet to fill that information out.
And now if I look into webpages_Membership, what I'll find is it there is a corresponding record
in here that has the same UserID so we can join these two tables together
to get the whole picture for a user.
And this one includes information like a hash password for sallen.
WebSecurity will automatically hash password which is good
because then we're not storing the user's password in plain text in the database.
That's something you almost never, ever, ever want to do,
store plain text password in your database.
And there are some additional columns in here, too.
But overall, the database is now a combination of tables that we used to manage restaurants
and reviews and user profiles, and tables used by WebSecurity
and its friends to manage membership and roles.
And this database was created through a combination of WebSecurity
and our entity framework migrations.
And now that we know where the data is stored, let's go back to the AccountController
and take a look at the second WebSecurity call, the call to log in.
You'll also see this in the log in action which is where we come
after the user has clicked the log on link and they filled in the user name and their password,
they click Log in, we'll end up in this action that simply needs to take that user name
and password and pass it to WebSecurity for validation.
If the model says it is valid and WebSecurity says that we can log in,
what we'll do is redirect back to the ReturnUrl.
We'll see how that works in just a second.
You can think about what WebSecurity.Login has to do.
It has to, first of all, compare the hashed version of this password against the hash that's
in the database and see if they match.
And if they do, they can issue that cookie that we talked about.
Let's actually take a look and see if we can see that.
Here in Internet Explorer, on the log in page, let me press F12 to open the Developer Tools
and let's go to the Network tab and click Start Capturing.
This will capture network request.
And I'll now try to log in with my user name and password, I can click Remember Me
if I want the cookie to stick around between browsing sessions and click log in.
( Pause )
And here we can see what happened.
I posted my user name and password to /Account/Login.
It determine that I logged in successfully so it returned a 302 result which is a redirect,
which says, "Dear web browser, please go somewhere else."
So it redirected me back to that root of the application, the homepage as a logged in user.
And if we open up this response from the web server and go to the Response headers,
then what I want you to pay attention to is the Set-Cookie header.
This is how you tell a browser to accept a cookie.
The name of this cookie is .ASPXAUTH.
When decrypted will tell ASP.NET MVC that this user has successfully authenticated
to the application, there's no need to make them sign in again and now the browser is going
to send that cookie along on every subsequent request.
We can see that if we go back to the summary view and look at this request
that comes back into the homepage.
If I double-click on that, and now we look at the Request headers, so what the browser sends
to the server when it's requesting this page.
Down here in the Cookie section, if I double-click that,
you can see that we send along the ASPXAUTH cookie.
And that will actually go out on every subsequent request now until I close the browser
or actually it should stick around longer because I clicked on the Remember Me check box.
But the other thing I want to show you here if we go back to the summary view and look
at Account Logon, double-click on that to go into the details and look at the request body.
If I scroll over here, you can also see my UserName and my Password.
And so can anyone who might be sniffing network traffic between me and the web server.
So this is obviously not secure and this is why pretty much any reputable website that needs
to force its users to log in is going to use SSL.
They'll acquire an SSL certificate and install it on the web server
and then force the log in process to go through HTTPS.
If you go down that path, that's always a good idea to come into methods like this log
in method and add an attribute RequireHttps.
This is an action filter.
We've talked about action filters in this course but this is an action filter that will make sure
that the request that is arriving is coming over a secure encrypted connection.
And that would make sure that we're not passing any passwords in clear text.
No one should be able to see those traveling over the network.
And now that we know a little bit about how Forms Authentication works,
let's put on our developer hat and see how we can apply it to force users
to authenticate before they reach specific sections of the application.
( Pause )