Now let's look at forcing a user to authenticate.
First, I'm going to remove the RequireHttps attribute that we put on the log on action
because I do not have an SSL certificate set up.
And instead, we'll talk about a different attribute, the Authorize attribute.
Let's imagine that for some reason, you have some secret members only information inside
of the About page for the application.
In that case, what I would want to do is use an Authorize attribute here.
Authorize sounds like it's more about authorization than authentication.
But when you use the Authorize attribute like this with no other parameters, essentially,
you're specifying the type of authorization that says, only authenticated users are authorize
to invoke this controller action.
So before we get into the About action, a user has to be logged in.
And just by having that attribute there, if I do a build and we come back out to the application,
let me go to the homepage and close the Developer Tools.
And from the homepage I'm currently logged in.
So I'll also log off and now try to go to the About page.
And ASP.NET MVC has detected that Authorize attribute.
It knows I have to be at least logged in into this application before it can view that.
So it redirects me to the log in page where I can log in.
And notice that the ReturnUrl includes /Home/About,
it's been URL encoded with percent 2f.
But it's /Home/About is the ReturnUrl, that way once I log in MVC will be able
to redirect me back to where I was trying to get to which is the About page.
Now if you're wondering how MVC knew to send me to /Account/Login when it detected that I needed
to authenticate, that is something that you can configure in an application.
If you look at the root web.config in the project, at the authentication section,
the mode is equal to forms, and we have a loginUrl specified
in the forms element underneath that authentication element.
So the loginUrl tells the MVC framework where to go to authenticate a user.
The timeout value here specifies how long the user will be authenticated after logging in.
And this number is specified in minutes, so 2,880 minutes.
But coming back to our Authorize attribute, like many of these attributes,
you can apply them at the action level.
You can also take something like the Authorize attribute and apply it at the controller level.
So I'll remove it from the About action
and let's just apply it to the entire HomeController.
Now the user would need to be authenticated to do anything with the HomeController.
If there were just a couple of things that you wanted a user to be able to do,
an anonymous user to be able to do, there is an AllowAnonymous attribute.
I can place that-- let's say on the index action.
That will at least allow a user to get to the homepage of the application without logging in.
So let's try this real quick.
Authorize is at the controller level.
AllowAnonymous is on the index action.
So if I log off then I come back out here to the homepage
and it's viewing the homepage just fine.
And if I try to go to About or Contact, now I need to log in.
But before I log in, let me show you a couple of other things that you can do with Authorize.
You can be a little more specific about who is allowed into the HomeController.
You can specify users.
So I could say Users equals sallen, plall.
So you can have a comma separated list of users.
And having that in place, if I login as sallen, I should be able to get somewhere.
So sallen and my password, and now I can get to the Contact page.
But it's not very frequently that you can specify specific users except
for perhaps an admin user or a super user.
It's more common often to include roles instead of specific users.
And then you could say roles equal something like administrators and sales.
These users and roles parameters, by the way,
I should point out that they also work with Windows Authentication.
When you specify users, you'd be specifying users in active directory.
When you specify roles, you'd be specifying groups in Windows.
But now that I've added roles to my Authorize attribute, I've hit a bit of a stumbling block
because I do not have any roles defined.
We saw in the Database Explorer that there is a table where you can store roles,
but I don't have any user interface available for me to create roles.
We'll look at a way to populate some of these membership tables next.
( Pause )