What I'd like to do now is show you how
to automatically populate your database with some users and roles.
Having a database with users and roles predefined is nice to have during development
because if you're building an application that restricts access to specific pages based
on the user's role membership then needing to set up those roles when you start
with a fresh project only slows you down.
I'm a big believer in making it easy to get started working on a project.
There're several techniques that you could use to populate the database.
You could, just write SQL statements that insert data
into the membership tables we looked at earlier.
But I want to show you how to do this with the membership API that is given
to us by the SimpleMembershipProvider.
Remember that's one of the components that working behind the layers
of other components in our MVC 4 application.
And since this provider owns the schema, I think it would be more robust
to populate the database using this provider APIs.
The question then is when and where to populate these roles that we need?
We could during the application start up, make sure that the roles exist in the database.
But since we're using entity framework migrations, we can also use the Seed method
of our entity framework migration class.
Remember, that's in the Migrations folder.
It's called Configuration.cs.
This is where we added a thousand restaurants into the database
so we could do some testing in our AJAX module.
So inside of the Seed method, I'll add a call to a new method
that we're going to write called SeedMembership.
I can use Visual Studio to create this method for me if I just hit Ctrl period
and select that option in the drop down.
That will generate a method stub for me down here that I can now fill in.
The first thing we'll do here is use a call
to WebSecurity dot InitializeDatabaseConnection just to make sure that everything is set up
and the schema is in place for the SimpleMembershipProvider.
I do need to bring in a namespace for this, it's WebMatrix.WebData.
We're using the same parameters that we're using during application start
up when we call this method.
It probably would be a good idea to take this two lines of code and put them
in a static method in a class somewhere so that I can call them from both SeedMembership
and also the Global.asax.cs application start event
and not have this hard coded string (inaudible) duplicated everywhere.
But I'll leave that as an exercise for the viewer.
So once the database is set up, I can go out and get access to the current role provider
and the current membership provider by walking up to a property called Provider
on the roles class and the membership class.
These are static properties.
They give you the current provider that's in effect.
I do need to bring a namespace for this to work, System.Web.Security.
But now I have access to two objects that I can use to create users or see if a user exists,
see what roles the user is in, all the good things that you need to do with membership.
So there's not just a single membership provider that does both users and roles.
Those are actually a little more fine-grained than that.
There's a role provider and there's a membership provider.
I just think of them both really as the SimpleMembershipProvider.
And here is the API that we can use with them.
We can walk up to the role provider and say,
"Is there a role called admin., if not create the role."
And then, "Is there a user with user name sallen,
if not create that user and here's the password."
And finally, check to see if sallen is in the admin role, and if not,
add that sallen user to the admin role.
We always want to check if things exist first before we just add them
because remember the Seed method runs every time
that we execute update database in the Package Manager Console.
We'll be doing that many times as we change the schema and change our models
through development, and we wouldn't want this Seed membership method to try
to insert duplicate data that will actually generate an exception.
But with that code in placed, let me come in to the Package Manager Console
and run update database, that will execute the Seed method
and it will have a disappointing result.
And the disappointing result is an exception that has been thrown saying
that the role manager feature has not been enabled.
It took me a bit of time and debugging to figure this out.
But I finally realized that I needed to add some explicit configuration
to the web.config file for this to work.
So the SimpleMembership stuff just works inside of your MVC application.
That's a real web application.
But here when we're running update database, part of the entity framework migrations.
This isn't a web application and it seems to require a little bit
of configuration to get this to work.
So the configuration goes into web.config
because this is the configuration that migrations will use.
It has all the settings that are in place when that migrations process executes.
And the bit of configuration I have to put in here is just
to explicitly configure a role manager which is the simple role provider
and set it to enabled equals true.
And also explicitly configure the SimpleMembershipProvider
as the membership provider.
And just having that bit of config in placed and saving the file,
I should be able to update database again.
And now, we'll have users and roles in the database for sure.
So that worked.
And don't take my word for it that it just works behind the scenes.
Let's actually test it out.
I'm going to remove the Authorize attribute from the HomeController and we'll place it somewhere
where we might actually want some authorization.
So I'll remove that attribute and while I'm at it,
I'll remove this AllowAnonymous attribute from the index method.
It makes no sense if nothing in here is-- needs authorization.
And instead, let's pretend that we only want to allow administrators
to be able to create restaurants.
That means making a change in the restaurant controller.
Specifically, we'll add an Authorize attribute to the create action
and say that this can only be done by users in the admin role.
And putting this on the create action that responds to a post,
we'll make sure that no one can create a restaurant unless they're an admin.
But I will also put it on the create action that responds to a get request,
just to make sure that someone who is not authorized doesn't come in
and try to create restaurant and fill out all the information
and they don't have the proper permissions that would be a disappointment.
Speaking of which, it might also make sense to go into the Index view for restaurant and here
with the Create New restaurant link appears, we might want to make sure
that we only display this link if the user is an admin.
Again, that mean standard users won't click that and get confused when they have to login.
So there's an API for this, just User.IsInRole, the same user property
where we can see User.Identity.Name.
There's also an IsInRole check, you just pass in the name of the role and that will return false
if the user is not an admin and we won't show that link.
Let's try it out.
I'll run the application and we'll come in to look at the list of restaurant.
And since I'm not logged in, I do not see it create new link.
So let me log in and now my database has an admin role.
We've seeded that into the database.
And I put sallen in that role.
So once I logged in and come in to the list of restaurants.
Now, I can see the Create New button.
And if I were to go directly to this Create action as a regular user, so I'll log off
and paste that URL in here, the MVC framework would decide that it needs to authenticate me
in order to see what role I'm in and that's where I could log in.
And I can now get to that Create page.
And I feel like I can sleep well at night now,
knowing that only administrators can create restaurants in the application.
My application is error tight and a malicious user should never be able to get
through this authorization checks.
Or can they?
( Pause )