One type of attack, you will potentially face
in a web application is a Cross-Site Request Forgery.
I want to make you aware of this attack because it's subtle
and potentially dangerous and it's also easy to prevent.
A Cross-Site Request Forgery or CSRF is an attack a malicious user can execute using
unsuspecting users who are logged in to your site.
A CSRF attack might do something a user will find annoying like log them
out of the site or change the profile name.
But this attack can also be destructive and steal or destroy data.
Let me give you an example.
Let's imagine I'm a bad person who wants to create a restaurant on OdeToFood,
but I don't have administrator access.
So what I will do is go out and create my own web application.
I'll start a new wen application here with Visual Studio, again,
it'll just be a throw away application.
I'll create an MVC 4 application but it doesn't need to be an MVC application.
It could just be an HTML page that I upload somewhere on my website.
I'll use an empty project template.
And now that that's ready, all I'm really trying to do here is build an application
that I can run in IIS Express and point out that it's a different application
than OdeToFood, so it's someone else's website.
And then inside of here, I will add a new item, just a regular HTML page that can be served
up from my site, let me call it, funnypictures.html.
And my goal here is to execute a CSRF attack against someone who is logged in to OdeToFood.
In order to do it, I usually need to know a little bit about what HTML is on the site
that I want to attack, but that's usually not too hard to get,
and the HTML that I'm particularly interested in is the form
that is used to create a new restaurant.
So let me copy it out of the source view of this page and paste that into my HTML page.
And then just clean it up a bit because we really only need a form tag and the inputs
for name, the city, and the country, and hit control K,
control D to do some formatting, that looks better.
And now I'll add the values that I want to get into OdeToFood through an unsuspecting user,
my values and this could represent trying to transfer money or change someone's profile,
anything on a site that only an authenticated user can get to, that's what I want to get to
and place my own values into the application.
And I'll do just a couple of other things to dress this up.
Let's give the form an ID.
I'll just call it the form.
Let me add in inline style.
So nothing inside this form actually displays to the user.
The goal is not to have the user fill this out, the goal is for me to trick the user
into taking this HTML and submitting it to OdeToFood application behind their backs.
And that means the action, we're not going to be posting back to my website.
My website doesn't have anything to do with restaurants.
It's just full of malicious pages.
I'm going to change that to postback to the real website which is over here
on a different port number on this machine.
And I don't even need the user to click a button because I'm going to add some script here
that will just automatically submit this form after a 2,000 millisecond delay.
So what I've done essentially is craft a form to look just like the form that OdeToFood expects.
And now if I run this application or just view this in a browser, as me the bad person,
the malicious user that form gets submitted to OdeToFood which redirects me to the login page
because I need to login but unfortunately I'm not an administrator.
However, if I take this URL and somehow get it to another user who is an administrator,
maybe I'll send a link in the e-mail, use some social engineering,
get them to click on something else that's on another page, thinking they're going
to download a free song or something.
If I get that person to do it, someone who is logged in to OdeToFood all they need
to do is click a link and come to this page and then I get a value into the database.
It will be down here at the bottom.
And of course there's all sorts of things I could do to make this less obvious to the user
that they just posted something to OdeToFood.
I could use jQuery to do the submission in the background
so they never even see the OdetoFood website.
All they see is that page of line where I put a funny picture on there.
Behind the scene something is happening on OdeToFood that they don't know about.
And me the bad person has used someone who is an administrator on OdeToFood as a proxy
and channeled my malicious data through them to get it into the database.
That's a Cross Site Request Forgery.
It works because that other user is logged in to the application.
And because they're logged in to the site, their browser has a cookie.
And because their browser has a cookie, the browser sends that cookie along on every request
that it makes to OdeToFood even if the user didn't intent for that request to go
to OdeToFood, even if me, the malicious person tricked them into sending a request to OdeToFood
that carried along something dangerous.
So when you are building an application that uses forms authentication and you have areas
with form posts that you want to protect with authorization rules, then it's not enough
to just authenticate a user, and authorize them based on their role.
You have to make sure that the form they're submitting to you is a form that you gave them
and not a form that a malicious user tricked them into sending.
It should be your restaurant create form not someone else's form from another website.
And fortunately, this is easy to do with ASP.NET MVC.
It has the concept of an anti-forgery token to ensure that the form post that is coming
in when you create a restaurant is something that you gave the user.
The way we use an anti-forgery token is to go to the restaurant controller
and on this create action, the destination for a post put an attribute
to say validate anti-forgery token.
This is part of the solution.
And just having that attribute in place, if I build the application come back out as a user
who is logged in to the site and try to create something new with any name, any city,
any country, I'll get an exemption
that there was no request verification token that I submitted.
So the way this anti-forgery token works is that we need to go into the form
that will post this controller action and use an HTML helper
that will add a verification token into the form.
The verification token is a hidden input that holds a cryptographically significant value.
So that is basically, added to every form that the user is going
to submit into an authorized area.
That cryptographically significant value is also placed into a cookie in the user's browser.
So when the user submits the form, the form value has
to match the cookie value before MVC will allow that request through.
The idea is that even if a malicious user gives one of your members some evil HTML,
they will not be able to set that cookie in your user's browser
because browsers don't allow one site to set cookies for a different site
and that is how an anti-forgery token will prevent a CSRF attack.
So the evil application that I was building over here,
it wouldn't be enough just to have these inputs anymore.
I would also need to figure out what the user's anti-forgery token is and set a cookie
in their browser, that's just impossible for me to do, so I would give up.
But we need to get this working in the real application
and I have validate anti-forgery token that attribute is on my create action.
I also need to go into the create view for a restaurant and for this to work inside of Form,
I'll just use Html.AntiForgeryToken.
That is all that it's needed and now if I come into the browser let me refresh this page.
And I should be able to create a restaurant with a name of two and a city,
and a country of two just to see if this works.
And down here at the bottom on my list I can see now, I can successfully add that.
So one more quick summary if you're building something that uses forms authentication,
you have form post coming in to authorized areas add an anti-forgery token to the form
and validate that anti-forgery token in the action that is a destination for the post.
Taking these two steps will help to prevent a Cross Site Request Forgery.